<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Packaging and packaging waste</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0027/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-11-17</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>CORBEY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Wallström</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>2</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, in 2001 a total of 65 million tonnes of packaging waste was generated in the 15 old Member States of the European Union. That corresponds to around 17% of municipal solid waste and 3% of the total waste generation by weight. Of these 65 million tonnes, 34 million tonnes – 53% – were recycled, and 60% was recovered or incinerated with energy recovery. Our information gives good reason to assume that in 2002 not a single target out of the 75 different targets applying to Member States was missed. This is a success many would not have believed in even a few years ago. Therefore the Community has built on this success and adopted new and higher targets earlier this year. The new Member States started later in setting up their own recycling schemes. They have nevertheless made significant progress towards fulfilling their target under the old packaging directive at the end of the transition periods agreed in the Accession Treaty. For procedural reasons, a deadline for the targets of the revised packaging directive could not be set within that directive and this proposal was therefore necessary. The Commission believes that setting this deadline for the new Member States is a matter in which Parliament needs to be fully involved. We therefore consider that the appropriate legal procedure is codecision on the basis of Article 95. We can also understand, however, that the new Member States want to have legal security as soon as possible. They should be able to transpose the targets of the revision directive and the deadline under the present proposal at the same time. The deadline therefore needs to be agreed before the transposition deadline for targets expires in August 2005 and I hope that the efforts made to reach an agreement at first reading will be successful. The Commission has proposed a deadline of 2012 for all new Member States. This should allow discussion in Parliament and Council to start from an equal basis. However, I can also accept limited postponement for some of the countries concerned. I am also aware that many Members of Parliament wish to extend possibilities for Member States to encourage re-use systems. This is an important subject and the Commission agreed to study options during the last revision of the packaging directive. However, getting the right balance between encouraging re-use and preserving the internal market is also not easy. I think, therefore, that we should wait for the outcome of the two ongoing studies and discuss this issue on the basis of a report that the Commission will present to Parliament and the Council in 2005. However, if Parliament wishes to point out the importance of re-use in a recital, as suggested in Amendment 4, that is acceptable to the Commission. The Commission can accept Amendments 1, 2 and 3 in full, and Amendment 4 in principle.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

