<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Packaging and packaging waste</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0027/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-11-17</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>CORBEY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Drčar Murko</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen. The objectives in the field of waste treatment to which the new Member States committed themselves during the accession negotiations are not a simple matter for the majority. This also applies to the various types of waste packaging set out in the European Union directive of 1994. All the new Member States have asked for transition periods to be granted. As we know, the Directive was revised during the accession negotiations and higher standards for waste treatment were introduced. In order for the Member States to remain within the realm of what can realistically be achieved, it was logical that they had to receive new, extended transition periods. It is those transition periods that we are discussing today. At present the new Member States are establishing their systems for dealing with waste packaging and in this respect the next three years will be crucial. Let these systems have high standards from the ecological point of view, but they must also be achievable and economically acceptable. In this respect the new Member States are pooling their previous experience and following the experiences of others in the area of legislative options. This entails the use of 'examples of best practice', which they wish to repeat, as well as the use of unsuccessful experiments, which they wish to avoid. In any case they will attempt to integrate various methods and to influence manufacturers to make packaging functional and, at the same time, safe and acceptable to consumers. The method for recycling packaging set out in Article 5 of the original Directive is one of the methods we wish to consider. My own country, Slovenia, supports recycling, as it is logical both from the environmental and the economic standpoint. It has not been possible, however, to overlook the fact that the interpretation of Article 5 of the original Directive has been the subject of numerous complaints as well as legal proceedings. So Parliament and the Council called on the Commission to prepare the statement which we have heard today, a statement that would examine various aspects of the effects on the environment and the internal market. Our political group is happy with the extended deadlines restored to the new Member States by the recommendation in the revised Directive. Taking all the various elements into account, we have reached the decision that it is reasonable if the wording is limited to its original purpose and we do not include anything that is in the process of development or is the subject of expert analysis and current proceedings in the European Court. Thank you.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

