<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Packaging and packaging waste</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0027/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-11-17</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>CORBEY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jackson</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, to follow on from what my two colleagues have just said, I took part in the adoption of this directive with Mrs Corbey and others. We were certainly under the impression that the dates mentioned in the preamble to the directive, as it was finally adopted, were the dates that would apply to the accession states. I therefore have some questions for the Commissioner. It is very nice to see her here for what must be one of her last debates as Environment Commissioner. First of all, have the accession states requested these earlier dates? They are embarrassingly close to the Irish dates. Ireland, as we know, has been looking at this legislation for many years and has done absolutely nothing about it. Were these earlier dates that the Commission is proposing actually requested by the new Member States? If not, on what basis have they been decided? Second, are they based on any cost impact assessment? There must be some additional cost between the dates that the new Member States wanted and the dates the Commission is proposing. I believe that these dates show the way in which the Commission operates. It sees much of this legislation as aspirational. As my colleague Mr Allister has said, we see it as legal texts that are put into operation. If we are not very careful, we will find a mass of used packaging being exported from the European Union to China and elsewhere in order to escape this situation. So could we please have those answers from the Commission?
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

