<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safer use of the Internet</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0033/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-12-02</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Edith MASTENBROEK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Kirkhope</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I will keep my remarks short in order to keep in with the interpreters, whom I much admire. The Internet is a force for good when it is responsibly used, but it is a force for evil when it is in the hands of morally suspect persons or criminals. This report builds on the work that I did for my own report in the last session, dealing with the issues of child pornography on the Internet. This is a very good report and it forms the basis of further work, which we need to do because technology moves on. Technologically, the criminal community often moves on rather faster than the law enforcers. We need to be aware of the fact that this is a highly technologically-based industry. It is also one where we need more codes of conduct, which impinge upon those who make considerable profits as service providers within the business. I do not mind people earning a lot of money but I feel that sometimes this brings with it extra responsibilities, particularly in an area where there is an international dimension. We in Europe must act. We have been dealing with money laundering directives recently. It seems to me that the minutiae in regulations in that area, which we require people to abide by, indicate that we are far too flexible and easy-going when it comes to controlling the Internet. Let us by all means take the Internet forward, let us find new technology, but let us make sure that the people who wish to use that technology for evil purposes are curtailed in their actions for the good of all of us.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

