<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safer use of the Internet</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0033/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-12-02</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Edith MASTENBROEK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Segelström</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, welcome, Commissioner Reding. The report on safer use of the Internet concerns an issue different from many of the others that we politicians are accustomed to deciding about, but the Internet and new technology require political knowledge and decisions. Before I was elected to the European Parliament, I took an active interest, as a female Social Democrat, in the debate about violence, violent pornography on the Internet and the exploitation of children and young people. I am still involved in the debate, but now as both a Member of the European Parliament and as Chairman of the Depiction of Violence Council/Media Council in Sweden, which is responsible for these issues. On the basis of my experience in Sweden, I am especially pleased that the EU is accepting its responsibility for ensuring that the Internet is safer for children and young people and that it will continue to be both entertaining and educational, not only for children and young people but for all who like to surf the Net and use its chat rooms. In the committee, I talked in particular about children’s use of the Internet. This is a lucrative area for the future, and we as politicians must demand that the industry concerned accept its responsibility and pay for filters and other devices that can remove degenerate material on the Internet and offer protection against it. In Sweden, we have been able, by taking part in this EU project on the future of the Internet, to demonstrate the differences between parents’ knowledge of children’s Internet activities and what the children say their parents know. Parents clearly need help in keeping up with developments, which is something we have also been able to offer through the EU project in Sweden by, for example, producing a handbook. I think we must try to continue with such cooperation and exchange of experience in the EU. Cooperation, together with internal reform of the Internet are therefore what are required and, through Mrs Mastenbroek’s report, Parliament is well placed to bring about a safer Internet.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

