<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safer use of the Internet</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0033/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-12-02</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Edith MASTENBROEK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Gyürk</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>HU</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I would like to preface my remarks with a quote from a statement from the Vatican concerning the role of the Internet. The Internet can unite people, but it can also divide them on the basis of ideology, politics, possessions, or religion, if used as an instrument of aggression. Concurring with this, I too think that in principle two possible paths lie ahead of the Internet. It is the responsibility of us all to prevent it from embarking on the second of these: the Internet must never become an instrument of aggression. The safer Internet programme now before us has this as its objective, and I therefore support it. Over the past few years, this initiative has already proven its worth. First and foremost, by fostering the provision of information, it has helped to ensure that the next generation will be more aware users of the Internet. In connection with this aspect of the programme, the provision of information, I would like to add a thought concerning the report. In the new Member States of the EU, including my own home country, Hungary, the rate of Internet penetration is typically lower than elsewhere. One of the reasons for this is an unwarranted lack of confidence in the Internet. I therefore feel it is important to emphasise that providing information on the dangers of the Internet, which I too consider important, as outlined above, should always go hand in hand with raising popular awareness of possible solutions. If this does not happen, we are likely to see a slowdown in the rate of Internet penetration in certain Member States. In this regard, the hotline services that are given special mention in the report are of fundamental significance, although familiarity with such services is very limited, especially in the new accession states. One can certainly say that in this regard there is a need for a true breakthrough, and there is a need for the hotlines operating in the Member States to work together a good deal more effectively. There is therefore still considerable work to be done, but the draft before us can contribute to creating a safer and more humane online environment.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

