<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safer use of the Internet</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0033/2004</CODE>
    <DATE>2004-12-02</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Edith MASTENBROEK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Moraes</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, there are few reports which respond to a real feeling amongst European citizens for a solution, particularly among parents, than this report. Mrs Mastenbroek has completed an excellent report and people who are real experts in this field such as Mrs Segelström and Mr Kirkhope have added their words of support. I want to focus on three or four clear points. One is to congratulate the Commissioner on her words about the proliferation of racist and other violent material, which is on the increase and which is of concern to all of us here in the European Union. I want to raise Mrs Mastenbroek’s very important distinction between illegal material and harmful material. As Mr Kirkhope said, we are dealing here with a hugely imaginative product of technology, something which adds to our freedom and is something that we should handle with great care when we deal with how to curtail some of its excesses. I want to pick up on something practical. On Friday in my constituency I will visit a major charity called Childline. Many children’s charities across the European Union are crying out for the kinds of solutions we see in this report: funded solutions, hotlines. Mrs Mastenbroek, for example, mentioned the possibility of a children-specific hotline being adapted from the hotline approach that we see in the report. We have to deal with safer Internet providers, people who are making a great deal of money out of this technology but who also have a real responsibility. It is for us to publicise that need so that there is some peer pressure on Internet providers. Finally, for the older people amongst us, 3G technology will open out this kind of technology even more. The next generation will deal with it. It has to be protected. This report goes a long way towards doing that.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

