<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Auken</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DA</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I should firstly like to thank Mr Grosch for a really constructive piece of work and to congratulate him on this. We have listened to each other, and I think we are now in a situation in which it is also apparent that arguments have played a helpful role. I think that some sterling work has been done, and I also think it splendid that Mr Grosch has shifted attention away from some rather abstract fight against terrorism, or whatever it was to begin with, to the issue of road safety and of the real terror we have in Europe whereby the number of people killed and maimed on our roads is equivalent to the number of casualties that would occur if one jumbo jet per week were to crash, killing everyone on board. It is really important that we get something done about this, and a prior condition – or one of the prior conditions – for getting something done is, of course, that we have driving licences that can be checked up on and that are recognised throughout Europe. I think it excellent that we have not subjected our elderly people to more tests. It is good that, in this House too, we recognised that most of them are, of course, outstanding motorists who compensate for their reduced reaction times by driving carefully. If only fit and healthy people would put careful driving before over-confidence. There was one point we found it very difficult to understand. There are countries – and I do not believe that the whole of the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats fall into this camp – that apparently attach inordinate value to their driving licences. I think they should take a much more relaxed attitude to their old driving licences instead of cherishing them as if they were things that cannot be exchanged. In that way, we should obtain a driving licence we can use in the rest of Europe. There is no sign of driving licences being exchanged. We tried it in Denmark, and it worked. The world did not come to an end.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

