<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Romagnoli</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, we are debating in plenary an issue on which much time has been spent by the Committee on Transport and Tourism and the rapporteur, Mr Grosch, whom I thank for his diligent and timely report, with which I am largely, although not wholly, in agreement. Mr Sterckx stated that we all agreed with the aim of having a single EU format, although some differences undoubtedly exist. He was referring, in particular, to administrative renewal of licences for the elderly. In my view, this is an area which, in general, requires greater attention. By way of example: I fly a totally harmless machine, one which does not even have an engine. I believe that in the event of an accident, the only victim would be myself and, at most, one other person. Despite that, I am required, in Italy, to take out compulsory insurance, undergo a medical examination every two years and submit to a raft of administrative and other requirements which, frankly, appear excessive when compared to the level of danger to society represented by a motor vehicle which, in the event of an accident, can cause carnage. Accordingly, we have to be very careful. The issue is, therefore, to harmonise an area with significant consequences on the lives of citizens and with obvious social implications for motorists’ behaviour. Thus, we need to harmonise not only a document – it is not just a question of switching from a paper licence to a plastic one – but also people’s performance at the wheel. To this end, we need to ensure that police are able to identify with certainty a driver who may be infringing the Highway Code. I should also like to mention particularly the amendments submitted jointly with some fellow Members concerning the introduction of the AM licence for mopeds. I believe we should be grateful to users of 2-wheeled means of transport because, particularly in countries in southern Europe, they contribute to resolving serious traffic problems, help our environment and improve the quality of life in towns and cities, particularly those with an older, more traditional urban fabric. All dangerous behaviour must be punished and prevented, and there is no shortage of ways of achieving this. However, penalising two-wheeled traffic, which this directive does in part, will, in my view, damage not only our economies but also the quality of life in general.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

