<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Queiró</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I should like to begin by congratulating Mr Grosch on his report and by saying that my main concern in this debate on the future adoption of a European driving licence is that a good idea should not be spoiled by excessive regulation leading to more obligations and obstacles for drivers in the EU. The idea is a good one. Given that European citizens are enjoying increasing freedom of movement, it is necessary to harmonise basic rules intended to foster safety on the roads, to prevent fraud due to the improper use of false licences and to prevent drivers who have been penalised in one country from easily obtaining a new licence in another. Presented in this way, this is a simple message, which will be easily understood by those it is intended for and will be heeded by the public without any difficulty. The problem arises when a good idea, an obviously welcome political initiative, is undermined by the temptation to regulate. What we must avoid, when it comes to beneficial measures such as this one, is an increase in regulatory and bureaucratic constraints and in financial costs for EU drivers, when such steps are always debatable. We must also ensure that no national limitations are created for those learning to ride other vehicles, such as motorcycles. Otherwise, the subsidiarity principle – and respect for practices that have been legitimately established by the authorities in the Member States – will not be duly taken into account. This would then result, in one way or another, in obstacles – sometimes imperceptible ones – being in the way of all European citizens seeking to enjoy their right to drive, regardless of all of the statements to the contrary that we shall all no doubt make. These were the underlying reasons why I supported a range of amendments to the report before us, all of which were drawn up with the aim of making life easier for the public and for the various road sector operators and, at the same time, with the aim of promoting safer road transport. I shall conclude by saying that the most significant of the four European freedoms is freedom of movement.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

