<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Blokland</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, when people have acquired the right to drive a motor vehicle, they should, normally speaking, retain that right for as long as there are no physical or legal objections to them doing so. I do not think that this House is in any doubt about that. What we do question is the form in which the citizens are faced with this, more specifically, the standards for acquiring and retaining that right in the form of driving licences. In addition, driving licences often function as a form of identification, which means that verification aspects are important. I take the view that we should be very careful about establishing someone’s identity, certainly in the case of unknown people. The improper use of ID does not always prove conducive to a sustainable society. That is why it is vital that ID cards should be up-to-date, both visually and technologically speaking. In my view, driving ability can considerably contribute to reducing the number of road victims. Since reduction starts with prevention, it is of vital importance for drivers, both physically and mentally, to be able to take part in traffic effectively. It is quite acceptable for this to be subjected to requirements, for all drivers. These requirements should guarantee the holders’ capability. Mr Grosch’ report puts my mind at ease on that score, and for that I am grateful.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

