<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Titley</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>19</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I welcome the proposals on driving licences because they represent a huge advance in combating fraud, improving road safety and, most importantly, providing legal certainty for the free movement of people. I especially welcome proposals for higher standards for driving examiners. I did not like the Commission's original proposals because I thought they were too bureaucratic and too complex. They would have done unnecessary damage to certain groups such as caravanners, so I congratulate the rapporteur on producing a simpler and more practical proposal. However, we still need to look further into the question of motorcycles, where national practices and problems vary so much in the Member States. In the UK, our problem is not so much young motorcyclists, but middle aged men – like me – having a mid-life crisis, buying a very powerful motorcycle and then killing themselves. We do not have major problems with young motorcyclists because of our requirements for testing, particularly for the moped test. Other countries have different problems relating to motorcycles and mopeds, so I will argue that the proposal made by the Commission and Parliament for a 'one size fits all' solution will not work. That is why, in conjunction with some of my colleagues in the PSE Group, I have brought forward amendments which will allow for a two-track approach that will respect the principles of progressive access. On one track there will be a practical test for mopeds and then two further stages of progressive access. The other track will have no requirement for practical tests for mopeds, but then three stages of progressive access to the most powerful motorcycles. In both cases, with regard to decisions on direct access to larger machines, it should be at the discretion of Member States to adopt a minimum age anywhere between 21 and 27. I would hope that we can resolve this problem of motorcycles during the vote.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

