<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Leichtfried</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>21</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, I should like to deal with two points in this report that strike me as especially noteworthy. Firstly, I am pleased that the Committee on Transport and Tourism has departed from the Commission draft by taking the view that compulsory medical examinations from a certain age should not be imposed by the Directive, because I believe that such a provision would have amounted to unwarranted discrimination. There are no statistics of any kind to suggest that age-related health impairments are a disproportionately frequent cause of accidents. Moreover, it must be remembered that all of us throughout Europe are confronted at the present time with closures, particularly in rural areas, of groceries, banks, post offices, and so on. Many elderly people live in these areas, and it would surely be wrong to take away their licences and thereby effectively put them at risk of not being able to meet many of their basic needs. The second point I wish to address is the question of the ten-year time limit. I was initially sceptical on this point, but I realise that, if we are to create a uniform rule, it has to be accepted that there are countries in which the driving licence serves not only as a certificate of authorisation but also as an identity document. Let me turn this on its head and suggest that, if this ten-year limit is to apply, as I believe it should, it might be worth ensuring that this driving licence serves everywhere as a means of identification. The benefits this brings would make up for the disadvantages the time limit imposes on some countries.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

