<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Wortmann-Kool</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>22</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, first of all, I should like to thank the rapporteur for his important work, because this afternoon and evening have made it once again apparent that it was not easy. I should like to elaborate on a few key points. First of all, we must be really serious about combating European fraud, and thus pave the way for it, but that is impossible with 110 different driving licences in Europe. I do think it vital therefore that driving licences be renewed every ten years and that we move towards one fraud-proof driving licence in credit-card format in another ten years’ time. We cannot leave this to subsidiarity. This Parliament would not take itself seriously if we took a decision and subsequently needed 80 years to introduce it. Secondly, the Commission proposal was too restrictive for owners of caravans, boat trailers and horse trailers which, in accordance with the proposal, must obtain an additional category E driving licence to add to their regular category B driving licence. I am pleased with a majority backing for my proposal so that the current situation can be maintained. Since there is no evidence that this should be unsafe, we should not make the rules unnecessarily complicated. Thirdly, with regard to driving licences for heavy goods vehicles, if we were to follow the outcome of the Committee on Transport and Tourism, gradual access to heavy goods vehicles would even apply up to the age of 24 years. And that is going too far. An 18-year old is allowed to drive a big Landrover but you must be 24 years of age to be able to drive a heavy goods vehicle straight away. That is really too crazy for words and very unfair. That is why, with Mr Bradbourn’s backing, I have tabled an amendment along with the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats, which, as is currently the case, makes it possible to drive a heavy goods vehicle straight away from the age of 21. I should like to urge this House to support this amendment, which is a very important revision. The 10 years are vital to establish a uniform driving licence in Europe and combat real fraud. Thank you.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

