<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Vincenzi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>23</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I too feel strongly about the aspect of promoting road safety, particularly for motorcycles. In this respect, I think it would be useful to harmonise four general principles, which are already included in the directive. I am referring to the principle of progressive access and the fundamental role of training; the need not to discriminate between car drivers and motorcyclists in the issuing of licences; the awareness that speed and the power/weight ratio must be regarded as one of the main causes of accidents; and the fact that the situation across Europe is highly diversified. This diversity should, however, give rise to a strong demand for greater safety and a greater sense of responsibility on the road, but not the establishment of a four-wheeled monoculture over a two-wheeled one. Within this framework, other colleagues in the Socialist Group in the European Parliament and I are tabling some amendments. On the one hand, they are designed to limit the speed of motorcycles that can be driven at the age of 18 and to recognise the differences among the various countries in the types of vehicles on their roads. On the other, they reaffirm the principle of progressive access, rewarding driving experience and practical testing when people step up from mopeds to faster motorcycles and considering that, when they move up from one category to another, people have already acquired the skills of driving in urban traffic and behaving correctly towards other road users. With better harmonisation of these aspects, I believe that the motorcycle issue, which has been raised by many speakers, can be reconciled into a single scheme within the framework of this proposal, on which I congratulate the rapporteur.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

