<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Kratsa-Τsagaropoulou</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>24</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the proposal for a directive on driving licences brings more Europe into the everyday lives of our citizens. Legislation is becoming more accessible, more transparent and more efficient in sectors which are basic to our freedom of movement within a single European market. Our rapporteur, Mr Mathieu Grosch, has come down a long road and has made a huge effort to reconcile various sore points and different practices and has, in his way, contributed to the improvement of this proposal and we thank him for that. Indeed, a harmonised, but not necessarily homogenised system for issuing driving licences will, to begin with, help combat the fraud and confusion which can easily arise today, due to the variety of different licences which exist in the European Union. Issuing licences in the form of a plastic card, replacing old licences within 10 years and the facility, albeit optional, to introduce a microchip facilitate controls and reduce the risk of fraud. The mutual recognition of sanctions will help this, thereby promoting an area of security and justice in the European Union. This proposal for a directive also helps to strengthen road safety, which is the basic objective of the European policy. The right criteria for selecting examiners, their continuing training, periodic medical examinations of drivers, extending the principle of gradual access to driving licences for more powerful types of vehicles are elements which govern the protection of our life, the quality of our life and, finally, our democracy. They are at the heart of the European social model and we should protect them.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

