<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Doyle</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>27</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I hasten to add to Mr De Rossa's contribution that most of those driving around on provisional licences in Ireland are doing so legally – such is the crazy system we have – in case people think that a fifth of the drivers are outside the law. That is not the case. I fully support the third directive on driving licences that is before us and I thank Mr Grosch for the work he has done on it. We are trying to ensure greater freedom of movement for our citizens, to combat fraud and above all to promote road safety. The slaughter on our roads in every one of the Member States needs no underlining from me, and this is but a very small contribution. A plastic credit card-type driving licence would be ideal. The current paper licences lend themselves to fraud. We could have a credit card type with an optional microchip to reinforce further anti-fraud measures. I agree that it should be regularly renewed, again to reinforce anti-fraud protection and to renew the holder's photograph. It would also put an end to driving licence tourism by ensuring one holder, one licence. At the moment, as we euphemistically say in the English language, if you 'lose' your licence you can go and get a European driving licence or get a licence in another country. 'Lose' means having it withdrawn for some major transgression of the law! Harmonising the scheduling of medical checks for professional drivers has to be good and so too having minimum requirements for training for our driving examiners. This area has never been harmonised and it is most important that we go down that route. I would support all driving licences being replaced by the credit card type when they come up for renewal. I know that there is some debate around this and that there are two options. The big problem at the moment is that we must not diminish the holder's right to drive. I think there is a subliminal fear of renewing all paper driving licences, as they come up for renewal. People, particularly the more elderly amongst us, are afraid that their right to drive will in some way be threatened and that they will not get their licence back. We should give assurances that there will be no diminishing of the right to drive and that all driving licences will be transferred as they come up for renewal. I also strongly support the right to pull a trailer or a caravan under 3½ tonnes with a car licence.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

