<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Driving licences</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0016/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-02-23</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mathieu GROSCH</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Koch</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>29</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the common European driving licence is long overdue, not as some sort of supplementary version but as the one and only valid one. While it may be fascinating to flick through the catalogue with the 110 models currently in circulation and study the various periods of validity and security features, it is not practical to operate with such a catalogue. Exchanging old driving licences will not make licence holders observe the highway code any more diligently, nor will it result in vehicles being equipped with better safety devices, but it will improve freedom of movement and considerably enhance people’s security and safety, whether on or off the road. Updating driving licences brings more security without additional red tape and will be effected in full compliance with the subsidiarity principle. Exercising their sovereignty, the Member States should find a host of ways to administer the exchange, for example when vehicles are licensed or undergo their regular roadworthiness test. Both of these take place far more often than the updating of driving licences, involve considerable red tape and are far more expensive too. All vehicle users who drive abroad will enjoy a higher level of safety by virtue of the fact that, when they are stopped for roadside checks and even when they hire cars, their up-to-date readable driving licence will make irritating and nerve-racking complications a thing of the past. Evidence shows that such complications lead to stress, which puts these drivers at risk on the road. In the context of the fight against terrorism, I believe that a verifiable driving licence is an entirely legitimate requirement. The licence-holder must be identifiable beyond any shadow of doubt. In this way, the scope for fraud is reduced, licences become more forgery-proof, and we may be sure that the driver of a bus or of a vehicle carrying hazardous materials is qualified to drive that particular vehicle. If we want to take serious action to combat driving-licence tourism, we need a registry of issued driving licences as part of a network of national registers. If the Committee’s assumptions turn out to be justified, we shall achieve this goal in the year 2030. We should certainly not defer our target dates any further.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

