<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Community air traffic controller licence</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0038/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-03-08</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>SCHMITT</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Janowski</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>UEN</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, members of the Commission, ladies and gentlemen, the issues dealt with in the Parliament and Council directive on a Community air traffic controller licence are key issues in the field of civil aviation safety. We cannot afford to be indifferent or to allow any slackness in procedures and measures in this field, given that any problem could pose a threat to human life and health. I therefore believe that this directive is necessary, and indeed essential. If the sky above us is to be treated as a Single European Sky, then precise and clear legal regulations are needed. These regulations must also cover air traffic controller licences, because the work of air traffic controllers must meet the highest possible standards of responsibility and professionalism. As well as specialised training for work under normal conditions, which we all hope will always prevail, it is important that training be provided for any exceptional situations or crises that could arise. Air traffic controllers must therefore be people with a great deal of theoretical knowledge and extensive practical skills. They must be in excellent physical and mental health, which means that regular check-ups are necessary, and they must be people who can remain calm and in control even in exceptional situations, such as crashes and terrorist attacks, as mentioned by the previous speakers. With regard to knowledge of languages, air traffic controllers obviously need a very good knowledge of English, the common language, yet they should also be fluent in the local language, as this would be particularly important in a crisis. I believe that these regulations should also provide for some kind of feedback, or systematic monitoring of the impact of the legislation, as well as for the adoption of any amendments that become necessary, particularly with regard to developments in electronic and digital technology. Finally, I should like to extend my sincere thanks and appreciation to the rapporteur, Mr Schmitt, for the effort he has put into dealing with this issue. I say this as someone who has helped train Polish civil pilots, as until recently this was my job at the Rzeszow University of Technology. I also believe it would be a good idea if EU legislation on such an important matter were to be adopted and respected outside the European Union. There are no artificial borders in the sky, and the laws of aeromechanics apply everywhere. The principles of aviation safety should therefore be enforced throughout the world, and the European Union may well be able to help ensure that this is the case. Many thanks.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

