<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Community air traffic controller licence</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0038/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-03-08</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>SCHMITT</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Queiró</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, all of us – at least those of us who attended the parliamentary debates during the last legislature on this issue – remember the emphasis placed on initiatives aimed at improving the organisation, punctuality and safety of navigation and air traffic control services and, on a practical level, at creating a single European sky and related regulations. Mindful that managing a complex air transport system and air traffic control system must be seen from a broader global perspective, which encompasses not only air traffic management systems (ATM) but also airlines and airports, we note that this directive will complete an important aspect of the single European sky, namely the harmonisation of rules relating to the issuing of training licences for air traffic controllers in the European area. This will in turn improve their mobility and facilitate the work of cross-border airspace control services. It is also important to clarify the legal situation as regards licences issued by the Member States under national law prior to the new directive’s entry into force; the necessary legal certainty must be provided and the directive must not be applied retrospectively. Hence the importance of the adoption in committee of an amendment covering this aspect, which will hopefully be adopted in plenary with the adoption of this report. We are also pleased about the reference made by the rapporteur, whom I take this opportunity to congratulate on his excellent report, to the fact that, following discussions with interest groups, he was able to conclude that both workers and the industry – the Commissioner referred to this – not only consent to the introduction of a harmonised Community air traffic controller licence, but even welcome it. This also confirms that neither the economic aspects, nor, more importantly, the social aspects of the European single sky, including vocational training, have been overlooked by the Commission or by Parliament. Mr President, I now hope that, when it is put into practice by the Member States, this initiative fully achieves all the objectives for which it was created and that it constitutes a practical opportunity to enhance the effectiveness of ATM services and of air transport safety for the benefit of its users, which, ultimately, we all are.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

