<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Reino Paasilinna</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, this is an example of difficult legislation. However, groundwater is one of our most important resources. Its protection should be taken seriously: indeed, wars are being increasingly fought over water resources. I believe that this proposal for a directive to protect groundwater should come into force despite its shortcomings. As has been mentioned, it will complement the Water Framework Directive. This will be a difficult issue throughout the Union. In my country, Finland, there are thousands of small groundwater areas, none of which will be sources of contamination in the near future, but which now need to be investigated. We nevertheless agree with this law, even if it is not necessary for us. I believe that it is now our turn to reach a reciprocal agreement. Groundwater in Central Europe covers large areas, and these are being threatened by various chemicals. The problem with the aquifers on the Iberian Peninsula is often to do with seawater. We on the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy managed to draw up a statement in a congenial atmosphere, for which I thank my colleagues. Unfortunately, the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats on the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, the committee responsible for this issue, did not agree to support compromise proposal 94 as the other groups did. This directive is needed. The first reading is only an intermediate stage, as the Council’s joint position is very different. It is worth making a combined effort to ensure that groundwater is properly protected. It affects our quality of life, it affects agriculture, and it affects human happiness and health. (Applause)
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

