<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jan Mulder</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to start by thanking Mrs Klaß for the good cooperation I enjoyed with her. As far as the Committee on Agriculture is concerned, two points stood out in particular, and it will not surprise you to learn that the essential one, to which previous speakers have already referred, was that the Committee on Agriculture is also, of course, in favour of clean water. Since something has to be done about this, we can, in principle, support the proposals in this groundwater directive. We consider it vital, though, that different measuring methods be introduced in Europe which reflect climatic and soil type differences. The situation on clay soil is different from that on peat, or sandy soil, and one soil type can also differ from Finland down to the heel of Italy. This will need to be taken into consideration when we measure the 50 mg. Secondly, the Committee on Agriculture wanted to take existing legislation into account. With regard to nitrate, it looks like two directives will be in place soon: the existing nitrates directive alongside the groundwater directive. If, for example, a farmer somewhere in Europe complies with the groundwater directive and is, with 30 mg, for example, below the 50 mg threshold, he will still be bound by the nitrates directive, and it is possible that a farmer with three cows per hectare will fail to comply with the provisions of the nitrates directive but will be complying with those of the groundwater directive, because if we measure the nitrate level, we are below 50 mg. It is then illogical to my mind that we have to ask that farmer to reduce the number of cattle units per hectare. It is one or the other. That is why the Committee on Agriculture has proposed to assess the need for the nitrates directive in 2008. The Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety rejected two amendments in this connection; the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe has subsequently re-submitted them, and I would now like to warmly recommend them to you. Thirdly – and in this last minute, I am speaking on behalf of the ALDE Group – I go along with the idea that clean water should be available, but what we should take into consideration is the cost involved. What are the socio-economic consequences if we introduce certain legislation? This is also the subject of a number of amendments tabled by the ALDE Group, which, needless to say, I should like to see adopted. It strikes me as being absolutely logical that the introduction of directives is not at the expense of everything else. We must have a timeframe in which things are kept realistic and affordable.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

