<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>María Sornosa Martínez</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I would like to begin by congratulating the rapporteur, Mrs Klaß, and all the honourable Members for the work they have done to complement the provisions on the protection of groundwater established by the framework directive with a view to preventing and controlling the pollution of groundwater and establishing criteria for assessing the chemical state of that water. We must therefore take the view that, given that the possibility of purifying an aquifer is very limited, control and prevention are absolutely essential in order to ensure that polluting substances do not build up in groundwater. We must not forget that groundwater is the European Union's most sensitive and important water resource and, in particular, it is the main source of public drinking water supply. Furthermore, and given that the measures to prevent or restrict the introduction of pollutants into groundwater are a vital element of the proposed directive, it is very important, despite what the previous speaker said, that we approve the compromise amendment on Article 6, which we have presented jointly with other Members, in order to ensure that Member States control indirect dumping on the basis of best environmental practices and techniques that are sufficient to prevent such dumping. Commissioner, I would like to point out that, in its proposed annex of polluting substances, the Commission has not taken sufficient account of the fact that, due to the geological nature of the existing sub-soils, there are certain substances, such as chlorides and sulphates, that occur naturally in many of the European Union's aquifers, and that, from a scientific point of view, it is arguable whether these salts should even be classified as pollutants. I would also like to say that the proposal presented to us is not very ambitious, since it is limited to the minimum requirements of the framework directive, but, despite that, I am confident that the work of all of us will lead to a better directive.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

