<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Dimitrios Papadimoulis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Groundwater is a unique natural resource of tremendous value, which is why it must be protected effectively. In our opinion, we need clear criteria for examining the qualitative status of water and a common European denominator, so that these criteria are comparable. We therefore support the need for the gradual elaboration of a common European policy for protecting groundwater, which will, however, also take account of the specific characteristics of each area. We attach exceptional importance to the compromise amendment which we have signed together with other political groups on Article 6, in which we state our wish for intensive protection. The scope of Article 6 must not be confined merely to indirect discharges to groundwater. We also support the need for a list to be created by the Member States, which will include the pollutants which are of specific concern in a river basin district. As there is no European definition of the best practice for farming, we call on the Member States to take additional measures to prevent pollution in this sector. At the same time, farmers need to be supported in their effort to achieve a cleaner environment through rural development programmes, so that the objectives both of the Water Framework Directive and the Groundwater Directive can be achieved. We also propose that the Member States list and conduct a midterm assessment of measures taken to prevent pollution. In this way, prevention can be strengthened and irreversible consequences avoided. The emphasis on prevention, the strict protection of groundwater and measures to prevent its deterioration are both necessary and an investment for future generations. That is why I totally fail to understand those who say that they have no money to invest in the future, in the environment or in our children.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

