<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Johannes Blokland</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, in the eleven years I have been a Member of this House now, I have rarely come across a rapporteur who himself presented a minority view on a report. In all honesty, I find it a bit strange that Mrs Klaß did exactly that. Her point is that the amendments adopted in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety leave too much room for Member States’ own policy. I can only stress at this point that I consider the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety to have done the right thing in adopting these amendments; after all, groundwater is mainly a national issue. When the framework directive on water was discussed, it was acknowledged that groundwater should be treated separately. Not least because of the subsidiarity principle, there can be no legal basis for this daughter directive other than Article 175(1). Groundwater is an endangered natural resource; we do well to give it our attention by exchanging best practice and encouraging better protection, but this is not the place for rigid Europe-wide standards. We already know that it is extremely difficult to measure the content of a substance in groundwater objectively for a region, never mind a Member State. For example, the concentration level of chloride can vary between 20 mg/l and more than 10 000 mg/l within a 10 km radius. Finally, I should like to briefly draw the Members’ attention to the issue surrounding the ban on dumping. Amendment 43 is crucial in this respect. Due to the way in which drinking water is extracted in some of the Member States, namely via infiltration of surface water, it is extremely important not to introduce an absolute dumping ban. I would therefore ask you to vote against Amendment 43, while Amendment 103 of the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe is acceptable. I eagerly await the outcome of the forthcoming vote, although I cannot guarantee that I will be very pleased with it. That will depend on which amendments this House adopts.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

