<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Luca Romagnoli</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, groundwater pollution is caused by percolation from the surface, as a result of the use of chemical substances in agriculture, as a result of organic and inorganic pollution due to surface flows of waste water and sewage, whether free or channelled, and lastly, but no less importantly, as a result of the inadequate lining of waste disposal sites. Illegal discharges, which unfortunately take place in various regions of the Union, both in the new accession countries and in the older Member States, like Italy, cause severe and uncontrolled groundwater pollution. Introducing threshold values for pollutants at the discretion of the Member States is a serious step backwards as regards the protection of the environment. Maintaining a gradual approach on this issue, as the Commission plans, does not in this case mean respecting the rights of individual countries, which is something that we would welcome in many other cases, but will result in harm to the environment and to consumers. By looking at the labels on bottles of mineral water, consumers can perhaps judge whether or not to buy the product, but they cannot do the same for vegetables and cereals. I therefore hope that, in the course of the legislative process, we succeed in amending the directive and establishing identical threshold values for pollutants for all the Member States, so as to guarantee the same levels of toxicity for human beings and the environment.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

