<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ria Oomen-Ruijten</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, it would seem, then, that there are more lists in circulation, but I hope that you will not point the finger at Mrs Herranz García for not having taken the trouble to warn me. I should like to echo the words of thanks to our rapporteur, Mrs Klass, because although I know that she was of a different opinion on certain things, she had a constructive input and was prepared to help support positions that Members from other Member States saw as important. This directive is important, because it is about achieving an ecological balance. Moreover, groundwater is important for agriculture, industry and for drinking water. In the framework directive, we have opted for a basin-led approach, which has a bearing on the assessment of the groundwater directive. It means that it is impossible to apply uniform standards to certain substances, but that uniform measuring methods, and such like, must be established. On a different note, I have tabled Amendment 110 in relation to indirect discharges, with which Article 6 of this directive concerns itself. You may well ask what my intention was in doing so. I am from a province which has to contend with floods on a regular basis. As we are in the process of clearing space for rivers, we will have them widened and use some of the sediment in order to raise their banks. If we adopt this framework directive on water, and certainly compromise amendment 94, which has been tabled by the Group of the Greens, that means that everything that is dug out of these rivers would have to be left beside the rivers for the sake of safety of the province and the Netherlands, and that it would have to be wrapped in foil. The cost involved for the small region I come from is EUR 100 million. Since that cannot be the intention, I am urging you to vote in favour of Amendment 110 and reject Amendments 43 and 94.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

