<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Adamos Adamou</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, groundwater is a basic and valuable resource which we need to protect. Groundwater pollution affects rivers, lakes and valuable ecosystems, increases the cost of drinking water and threatens its secure supply. The Commission proposal on the protection of groundwater needs to be improved, especially as cleaning up groundwater may take decades. As far as prevention is concerned, our objective is to protect groundwater with preventive measures, not to try and simply improve the status of polluted water. We need a proposal which protects from pollution with defined criteria and limits, while the Member States need to be forced to submit periodic reports on the status of their water and the effective measures which they have taken. Amendment 94, which proposes preventing and limiting substances that are persistent, bioaccumulative and toxic and introduces a procedure for controls by the Member States, is a positive effort to improve the report. According to the European Environment Agency, 87% of European groundwater does not meet the criteria for nitrates, while 10 out of 11 countries report a risk of water pollution from pesticides. We need strict criteria for nitrates and pesticides and I therefore call on you to vote in favour of Amendments 101 and 102. Another point is the ecosystems in groundwater. The microscopic flora and fauna help to improve the quality of groundwater and the quality of drinking water. Amendments 96 and 98 introduce groundwater protection zones, while Amendments 95 and 100 call for more research into groundwater ecosystems, which is why I call on you to vote for them.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

