<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Urszula Krupa</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>16</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    The issue of protecting groundwater against pollution in connection with supplying homes and industry is a serious one for every country and conurbation. Concerning the draft directive on protecting groundwater from pollution, it would seem that further work is called for, in particular as regards listing the pollutants that represent the main threats to the environment. It is also necessary to set threshold values for those naturally occurring substances identified as active ingredients of biocides and whose natural concentration is higher than the values proposed. Account should also be taken of the fact that these substances impact on the physiological activity of live organisms. Monitoring and research are therefore needed to establish their impact on human beings. I also feel it must be made very clear that in the interests of protecting groundwater, preventive and educational measures should be taken to make the population aware of the facts relating to water pollution, and to provide information on methods of protection and their implementation. Water should not only be protected through payments for its use, but also through penalties for wasting and polluting it. Furthermore, implementing measures such as legal rules and regulations need to be practical and workable.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

