<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Caroline Jackson</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>18</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, when Mr Dimas replies to the debate in a moment, I would like to ask him if he can specifically reply and give us the opinion of the Commission on Amendments 111, 112 and 94 and the amendments that the previous speaker has just mentioned about nitrates? It would be very interesting for all of us to have the opinion of the Commission specifically on those. I would like to focus quickly on 111 and 112, the two amendments which the rapporteur appeared to endorse in her opening speech, which deal with the application of the universal standards through the groundwater directive. As she knows, this idea was rejected in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, in favour of the framework approach of the Commission on the basis of river-basin management. Are those of us who oppose universal standards correct in saying that river-basin management or local management of the groundwater directive would mean that you do not need universal standards? Many speakers have commented on how important it is to recognise that it would be crazy to try to implement universal standards. Forty per cent of European groundwater is already well over the standard set in the Florenz amendments. I am sorry that as rapporteur Mrs Klaß used her time as speaker to endorse amendments that she knew the committee had rejected. Just a quick second point. The origin of the groundwater directive is really the impact of landfill sites on groundwater quality. Can the Commissioner reassure us that the Commission really is following up the landfill directive? We are told that there are still thousands of illegal landfills in France, Italy and other countries. If this is the case it makes nonsense of our trying to get better standards for groundwater when the origin of the trouble is still in place.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

