<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jens-Peter Bonde</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DA</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>20</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Today, we are to vote on a directive designed ostensibly to protect and improve groundwater in the EU. That is something it may, in some places, achieve, moreover, by means of limit values on the quantity of, for example, spray pesticides in the water. In Denmark, a decentralised system supplies us with groundwater that has not been chemically purified and that we drink directly. For us, it therefore seems wrong to allow poison in groundwater. We need to react not only when a limit value or upper limit has been reached. We must react as soon as we can measure the fact that a pesticide or its breakdown product has penetrated the root zone of the earth’s crust. Pesticides should only be approved specifically on condition that they cannot penetrate the top stratum of the earth and so reach the groundwater. When we can measure the pesticides and their breakdown products in the water, it was a mistake to have approved them, and they must immediately cease to be used. In Denmark, we have by far the most bans on the use of pesticides, but the EU now wishes to lift some of these. This shows that, despite the Constitution’s talk of a high level of protection, the most stringent protection can be removed. It also shows that the so-called environmental guarantee is, for the most part, propaganda. Groundwater is, of course, one area in which special rules in Denmark can be justified, because we drink non-purified groundwater. Not even in the light of this will it, however, be accepted that we are entitled to special consideration. How are we supposed to prove that Danes are more vulnerable than Germans to, for example, allergy-producing and carcinogenic substances. The June Movement’s amendment is designed to ensure that intervention takes place as soon as there is a measurable level of pollution. If this amendment cannot be adopted, I would call upon the Commission to declare that countries in which non-purified groundwater is drunk directly can introduce a higher level of protection. Thank you, Mr President, even though there is not so far a very great deal to say thank you for.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

