<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Bogusław Sonik</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>24</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, groundwater can be polluted in a great many ways and the man in the street is unaware of most of them, hence the importance of measures concerning education and prevention. Schools need to be targeted, and also the main users of water, who are intent on poisoning the environment as if they themselves were immortal. It is crucially important for the Cohesion Fund to remain at the level initially proposed by the European Commission, as it is supporting the enormous task of protecting the waters of the new EU Member States. We should not skimp on building infrastructure, sewage systems and treatment plants, because this is the only way of evening out the enormous differences between the various countries. The natural environment of Central and Eastern Europe was abused by heavy industry working to meet the demand for armaments. It is vital that the Member States meet the deadline for submitting data concerning the condition of groundwater, as such an overview is essential for precise and efficient monitoring in the future. Parliament has raised the issue of the quantitative status of groundwater. The draft directive sets out to deal exclusively with the chemical condition of water, with reference to Article 17 of the Water Framework Directive, so this is not the right time to introduce provisions concerning the quantitative status of water into the draft. Amendment 7 and Amendment 10 should therefore be rejected. Amendment 54 concerns new provisions for the protection of spas and medicinal water sources. It should be supported, as to date EU legislation has not dealt with the protection of these special high-quality waters. Provision does need to be made for them, and I would ask the Commissioner and the European Commission as a whole to pay particular attention to this matter.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

