<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Protection of groundwater against pollution</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0061/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-04-28</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christa KLA?</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Albert Jan Maat</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>28</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I too should like to add my thanks to the rapporteur for her commitment. Good though it was that she should be so committed from the start, the report now produced by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety appears to tend towards tightening up the Commission’s original proposal; Amendments 43, 103 and 94 to it certainly do. I wonder how Parliament intends to deal with those. Acceptance of those amendments will once again result in an increase in the burden and cost, particularly for European agriculture and horticulture – two areas that are self-evidently bound to benefit from clean water. Although the proposal, fortunately, also leaves sufficient room for subsidiarity, it cannot be denied that when the budget for European agricultural policy is reduced and the markets become more deregulated, it will drive up still more the cost price for European agriculture and horticulture. It is unacceptable that this House should on the one hand increase the burden and on the other hand deregulate the markets even further, it thereby puts the European countryside in an impossible position. I would like to urge this House in any event not to make the Commission proposal any more stringent, and certainly to vote against Amendments 43 and 94. I should also like to back Mrs Oomen-Ruijten’s Amendment 110, which would make the groundwater directive considerably more workable with regard to river policy in Europe.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

