<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Multiannual programme for enterprise and entrepreneurship</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0118/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Britta THOMSEN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Britta Thomsen</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DA</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>3</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the framework programme for enterprise and entrepreneurship for small and medium – sized enterprises is an important programme for every smaller enterprise in search of information or funding. In particular, the programme’s financing component has always been very close to the heart of the European Parliament and has consequently been increased each year by Parliament and the Council during the annual budget procedure. The background to the proposal to extend the multiannual programme for enterprise and entrepreneurship by one year is that the functions of the programme will in future be performed by its successor programme, the ‘Framework Programme for Competitiveness and Innovation’, which is planned to run from 2007 – 2013 to coincide with the financial perspective. The time – frame will therefore also coincide with the Seventh Research Framework Programme, which creates scope for better coordination between the programmes. It was initially disappointing for me to learn that the Commission’s proposal to extend the programme by a year involved returning to the level originally budgeted for in the framework programme. I therefore proposed to increase the budget for extension by EUR 9.5 million more than the figure in the Commission’s proposal. That amount was proposed partly because it would correspond to the actual expenditure on the programme in 2004 and partly because it would make the budget for 2006 – the extension year – level with the average for the previous years. At the same time, it should be pointed out that what we have here is a programme that both users and evaluation experts regard as operating smoothly and achieving its objectives. It is important to maintain and extend aid to entrepreneurs and small and medium – sized enterprises in Europe. They are the backbone of the European economy, and their continued growth is a condition of achieving the Lisbon objectives. Finally, the external evaluation report has stressed that the financial instruments in the existing programme in large measure cover the needs of the new Member States. Restricting funds would therefore impede the integration of those countries into the European economy. In the programme’s financing component, the most frequently used financial instrument, the ‘SMEs’ Guarantee Facility’, had provided aid to 112 000 small and medium – sized enterprises in Europe by the end of 2002. Ninety – three per cent of these 112 000 enterprises had fewer than ten employees, but six per cent had fewer than 50 employees. The programme operates smoothly and is wide – ranging, and I was therefore very pleased when a unified Committee on Industry, Research and Energy backed my proposal for an increase in the budget. Since the extension is to enter into force on 1 January 2006, an agreement at first reading was important for both Parliament and the Council. My colleague, Mr Brezina, and I met with the Council and the Commission on several occasions and now concur with the Council about an agreement at first reading involving an increase in the budget of EUR 7 million instead of the EUR 9.5 million I originally proposed. This constitutes a compromise, ensuring that the activities of the programme’s InfoCentre, together with similar activities, can be continued without a break from 1 January 2006, at the same time as the financial instruments are developed and strengthened in order to meet the growing demand from small and medium – sized enterprises throughout Europe. I should like to take this opportunity to express my deep gratitude to the Luxembourg Presidency, which has demonstrated great political flair and a tireless willingness to compromise; to the Commission, which has provided technical analyses and guidance in support of the negotiations; and, finally, to my fellow MEP Mr Brezina, whose active participation in the meetings and unfailing support I valued very highly.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

