<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Multiannual programme for enterprise and entrepreneurship</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0118/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Britta THOMSEN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jan Březina</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, as shadow rapporteur for the report on the Commission proposal amending the Council Decision on the multiannual programme for enterprise and entrepreneurship, and in particular for SMEs, I would like to make several comments on the importance of the extension of this programme. Although we are extending the programme primarily supporting entrepreneurs, and especially SMEs, by just one year until the end of 2006, this is a significant tool which should, in the context of the Lisbon objectives, contribute to and enhance the growth and competitiveness of enterprises in a knowledge – based and internationalised economy. The importance of this decision lies above all in creating a bridge between the current programme and the Framework Programme for Competitiveness and Innovation for the years 2007 -2013. This extension will give businesses easier access to Community support services, programmes and networks, and help to improve the coordination of these facilities. Focusing on the new Competitiveness and Innovation Programme, we are to look into the evaluation of the multiannual programme for enterprise and entrepreneurship prepared for the Commission in November last year, in order to tailor the new programme more effectively and promote entrepreneurship in the EU. Last but not least, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs Thomsen, for the excellent job she has done, not least in smoothly securing this extension and negotiating with the Council an increase in funding from EUR 81.5 million to EUR 88.5 million for 2006.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

