<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Money laundering</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0137/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>12</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Hartmut NASSAUER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>7</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Inger Segelström</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SV</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner McCreevy, ladies and gentlemen, I wish to thank the rapporteur for the fact that we now have a report and for the fact that the European Parliament too is getting to overall grips with combating money laundering and the financing of terrorism. In the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, on which I sit, we have agreed that it is not enough for us to work at combating terrorism as a crime, but that we must also look into the causes of the global spread of terrorism and into where the money comes from. To myself, as a former member of the Swedish parliament, it has long been clear that not only terrorism but also much of the criminal activity in our countries is financed on the basis of everything from the drug trade, legal and illicit gambling, prostitution and the trade in sex slaves to transfers of funds between banks and countries. Obviously, we MEPs too have to be monitored like any other citizens. I hope that the directive will lead to wider discussion in our home countries of what is known as dirty money. The fact is that money laundering does not only finance terrorism. It also corrupts our societies and is thus a threat to democracy. That is why today’s debate and directives are so important for the future, as well as for the European Parliament and the EU.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

