<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Equality action programmes</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0132/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>13</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Rodi Kratsa–Tsagaropoulou</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE–DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>3</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the report which we are debating proposes the annual extension of the funding for the two Community action programmes on the application of gender equality in the European Union, both of which come to an end on 31 December 2005. These two programmes form the nucleus of our action in the field of the European strategy for gender equality and for the strategy of the civil society organisations working in the field of gender equality. The first programme is the action programme on the Community strategy on gender equality, which was adopted in 2000 and helps to incorporate the gender dimension in all Community policies, in order to promote gender equality while, at the same time, safeguarding cooperation and partnerships between national authorities, organisations working to promote equality, social partners and non – governmental organisations. The European Commission is proposing a total budget of EUR 61.5 million, compared with EUR 50 million in the previous budget. The second Community action programme concerns the promotion of organisations at European level in the field of equality. It was adopted in 2004 and supports the operation and activities of women's organisations with a budget of EUR 3.3 million, compared with EUR 2.2 million in the previous budget. The harmonisation of these programmes in the past was – and will continue to be – successful. It gave positive results in various sectors within the scope of its field of action and activity, such as equal pay, reconciling work and family life, the participation of women in decision – making and raising social awareness about changing stereotypes relating to men's and women's roles. We also make a very important step towards pluralism and the more democratic participation of civil society; in other words, by opening up Community funding to all women's organisations, rather than just to certain privileged partners, as was the case in previous years. However, the situation as regards equality in the European Union, including as a result of enlargement and the particular problems which are arising in the new Member States, the lack of participation by women in the productive, economic, political and social process and the discrimination which is faced today by women in particular are forcing us to be bolder in our next moves. In adopting this report, we are successfully and promptly safeguarding continuing financial assistance for the transitional period next year (2006), pending approval of the new financial perspectives, for actions which help to promote equality and incorporate it in all European Union policies. In adopting this report, we are preventing the gap which existed in the Community financial perspectives and speeding up the legislative procedures between the institutions – the European Commission, Council and European Parliament – for the approval of a final decision, as the competent Commissioner, Mr Figel, said earlier. In this way, we shall avoid the bad experiences of the past, by which I mean the amount of time taken to adopt programmes, the consequence of which is failure on the part of the European Commission to prepare proposals for the submission of tenders and for civil society to participate and respond to the European Commission's proposals in time. This is particularly important in this period, when we are all working to strengthen the Lisbon Strategy and economic and social cohesion. Our motion for a resolution also points out that, within the framework of the new financial perspectives for the 2007 – 2013 programming period, we need to ensure that there is satisfactory and discriminate financing of these programmes, which will allow the effective promotion of equality and the development of a fundamental role and the contribution of civil society working for equality in our democratic life. I thank the political groups which worked with me to achieve this agreed motion for a resolution and to speed up the procedures which will extend the life and the implementation of these Community programmes.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

