<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Equality action programmes</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0132/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>13</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Anna Záborská</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I would like to address Commissioner Spidla more directly. The two action programmes will make it possible to provide effective support to the NGOs working in the field of equality between men and women. I congratulate the Commission on its work in this field. Above all, though, let us congratulate the good – faith NGOs for using their useful expertise to enlighten the European institutions, which are too often cut off from the daily lives of the citizens. Let us emphasise, however, the extent to which most of them are lacking one important aspect: the financial resources needed to carry out their activities. The expertise of the NGOs is indispensable to enable us to draft balanced, specific legislation. If the European institutions want to be taken seriously, the political desire for a Union closer to its citizens must be translated into actions. We have much to do in the field of equality. We cannot allow ourselves to exclude some NGOs from the financing. Commissioner, it is my wish that this much – demanded equality between men and women should ultimately apply to all the NGOs active in this field. All the NGOs must be eligible for financing regardless of their size, their experience and where in the Member States they are set up. I would like the services of the European Commission to simplify the procedures, to make them more approachable and more transparent, to expand the possibility of financial support to a larger number of NGOs. Gender equality will not be achieved by large centralised organisations, but by the actions of NGOs on the ground, close to the citizens.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

