<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Equality action programmes</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0132/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>13</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Urszula Krupa</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    As I only have one minute to speak, I should like to make it clear that we are opposed to the implementation of a programme that seeks to promote equal opportunities by breeding hostility between the sexes, or in other words by encouraging women to regard men as the enemy in their fight for better treatment. All that this will achieve is rivalry between the sexes, and this is in fact something we have seen recently in the European Union. Attempts to play down the differences between the sexes are another dangerous trend, which has an impact on various aspects of life, sometimes with disastrous results. It would therefore be advisable to make allowance for these differences, and for men and women to cooperate effectively on the basis of an understanding of them. All human beings are equal, but gender means that men and women are different not only in physical terms, but also in mental and spiritual terms. Women play an irreplaceable role in every aspect of family and social life. The Holy Father, the late John Paul II, gave a very accurate and faithful description of this unique type of care and self – sacrifice by calling it the genius of women. It is an unfortunate fact that some people wish to belittle this genius.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

