<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Equality action programmes</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0132/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>13</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Lydia Schenardi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, this report, which has the merit of calling for the extension of two Community action programmes regarding equality between men and women that I fully support, gives me an opportunity to draw attention to the gaps and deficiencies in this field. Why are there such gaps with regard to respect for the rights of women and what are the reasons for them? We could mention, in particular, ignorance, archaic and sometimes barbaric notions regarding the place of women in society, machismo in the workplace, the guilt of women in this matter. Indeed, when women stand up for gender equality, they are accused of feminism or of hating men. This battle for equality is a tough one, then, and the EUR 50 million or so allocated for 2001 – 2005 seem derisory in the face of rigid mentalities and existing inertia. Because what do we find? The gap between the salaries of equally qualified men and women is still huge, violence is continuing to increase, gender discrimination in terms of access to education, training and employment persists and it is still just as difficult for a woman to reconcile work and family life. One last word on the European Constitution that we in France are being asked to approve or reject. It contains nothing that will make a real contribution to the rights of women, but simply general principles on non – discrimination and gender equality. Even if only for women’s rights, therefore, let us begin by making a stand by voting ‘no’ to this draft Constitution.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

