<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Equality action programmes</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0132/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>13</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Vladimír Špidla</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>CS</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Ladies and gentlemen, I would thank the House for this debate. In spite of its brevity, I believe that we have heard a whole range of approaches to the issue. There can be no question that achieving equal opportunities is a long – term task, and that we often forget how much progress has been made. Incidentally, even though it is only a little over 100 years since women first attended Czech secondary schools in 1871, nowadays over 50% of university graduates are women. In my opinion, we should take a longer – term view of matters, since it is quite obvious that we still have a great deal of work ahead of us. I am in no doubt that British pilots are among the best in the world, and indeed the same applies to British Airways, which is why I am never afraid of flying with that airline. Even though this is an extremely complex field, I am quite sure that it will be possible to find an appropriate solution that makes allowance for women’s legitimate demands. As I said at the beginning of this debate, this programme is a technical extension of the present programme, or in other words of a programme aimed at supporting European organisations that are active in the field of equal opportunities, without any restrictions on the type, form or political affiliation of these organisations.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

