<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safety systems in motor vehicles</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0053/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>14</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ewa HEDKVIST PETERSEN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Paolo Costa</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I apologise as I was misinformed about the times, but I believe that I will be able to catch up very quickly. There are few of us in the House this evening and we are debating issues that are of an apparently minor nature, but I am convinced that Europe is built on details, and these are important details. The two reports on which I have worked, and which are linked to Mr Koch’s report, fundamentally address small aspects: the issue of safety belts, in the case of Mr Koch’s report, and, in my case, the technical implications of anchorages and head restraint systems for bus passengers. It would seem to be a very simple matter, and in essence it is, because we have finally decided to follow the Commission’s proposal, which consists of no longer allowing the installation of side – facing seats in buses since their safety belts cannot be fixed with the same standards of certainty and safety as those of front – facing bus seats. We came across a small problem, however, which relates to innovation. In some countries, particularly in Germany, the concept of conference buses is actually gaining ground. In other words, people can sit around a table even inside a bus. That posed the twin problem of safety, which must nevertheless be guaranteed, and of possibly allowing an alternative service. The solution reached was to allow a trial, permitting the use of these conference buses for five years. At the end of this period, we will carry out an assessment of the percentage of accidents – which we hope will be as low as possible – as already assessed by the Commission, but in relation to a Swiss experiment, in order to roll it out throughout the EU. Such a process will enable us, in a few years from now, to decide whether – and how – we must scrap side – facing seats in instances where speeds are greater than those normally reached in town centres, or whether, in contrast, this new service can continue. Although it was more difficult than we had imagined, I believe that the compromise reached with the Council on the Commission’s proposal is a good solution, and that tomorrow it can allow us to vote on the reports presented positively and with peace of mind. I hope that my fellow Members do so.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

