<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safety systems in motor vehicles</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0053/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>14</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ewa HEDKVIST PETERSEN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Malcolm Harbour</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE–DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, it gives me special pleasure to be here as draftsman of the opinion on the Directive on Frontal Protection Systems, which Mrs Hedkvist Petersen has taken through Parliament so ably. Reflecting on the recommendations made by my Committee, I realise that almost all of these were taken up, which is an unusual situation. We worked together on this proposal for over a year, beginning in the last Parliament. One of the things that triggered my interest was that the original proposal presented by your predecessor, Mr Liikanen, was significantly flawed. I want to pay tribute to your team for having fundamentally reshaped it. The flaw lay in the approach to the soft bull bar. I would like to present you with a little souvenir, Commissioner, in the form of a sample which I took to committee meetings to convince colleagues the proposal needed to be fundamentally revised. The original proposal would have seen such bull bars taken off the market. The testing standards were unrealistic and there were no separate provisions, as Mrs Hedkvist Petersen pointed out, for a separate test enabling these bars to be made available on the aftermarket. As you can see, Commissioner, this is a custom – designed soft bull bar far more resilient than the old type of bull bar. It is thanks to you that these new bars can be kept on the market. I also want to pay tribute to a small company in my constituency called Concept Mouldings, which employs 100 people making these bars and which you have kept in business. I wish to thank you on their behalf. I also want to thank you on behalf of other accessory manufacturers and on behalf of road users, who will now be able to benefit from these bars – though not too often, we hope, as we want to eliminate pedestrian collisions. It is thanks to you that this type of resilient device will now be available on the market. This overall proposal is an excellent example of how Parliament can make a real contribution to practical legislative improvements when it works together with a Commission that is open and sympathetic. The bulk of the work was done by Mrs Hedkvist Petersen, with me simply acting as a catalyst, and I pay tribute to her persistence in working with your services, Commissioner, to secure a first reading agreement that I am delighted to support.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

