<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Safety systems in motor vehicles</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0053/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>14</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ewa HEDKVIST PETERSEN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jörg Leichtfried</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to take this opportunity to underpin what has been said with a few figures. I have discovered that in Austria, the number of off – road vehicles has increased from 117 000 to 170 000 since the year 2000. In 2004, every 14th new car purchased in Europe was an off – road vehicle. On top of that, these all – wheel – drive vehicles are actually hardly ever used off – road any more, but rather, for various reasons, mainly on the streets of our cities. It was therefore high time for the European legislator to respond to this trend, because accidents involving off – road vehicles put other road users at far greater risk than accidents involving other, smaller vehicles. Accidents involving these kinds of vehicles prove fatal in more than twice as many cases as accidents involving standard motor vehicles. We should also bear in mind that one in 22 accidents involving standard passenger cars proves fatal, whereas for off – road vehicles fitted with this kind of frontal protection system, it is one in every eight accidents. The solution that has now been found is a very good one. I should like to congratulate the rapporteur very warmly and reiterate my strong support for higher safety standards being adopted across Europe in this sector. I should also like to suggest that, as we take this issue forward, we might perhaps reconsider whether in the long term it makes sense for such frontal protection systems to continue to be used at all, particularly in urban areas. However, I also understand the arguments put forward by another Member, which at the moment undoubtedly still speak in their favour.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

