<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Nutrition and health claims in labelling</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0128/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adriana POLI BORTONE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Alexander Stubb</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE–DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, for the Italian and the English booths: the match is now 3 – 3, with about ten minutes to go. I knew that the chairman of the Committee on the Internal Market would be happy about that, not probably as a Liverpudlian but otherwise. I have three points. First, I will tell the Commission right off the bat that I am a federalist, but what the Commission is proposing here is simply going too far. It is over – regulation. I wish to focus especially on Article 4, which is one of the most illiberal proposals to pass through this House. It is not our job to tell the consumer what is good or what is bad. That is up to the consumer himself or herself to decide. I have quite a lot of faith in the individual to be able to make his or her own decisions on what food should or should not be eaten. The key is to know the content and then you can make your own choice. If we put in nutrient profiles, it might prevent the consumers from getting the right information. My second point is that I believe diets themselves are more important than the nutrient profiles of individual foods. Different people have different dietary needs, just as Mrs Niebler told us earlier. My third and final point is that it is very important to have clear labels and better information. However, I cannot support needless legislation or the assumption that people do not understand what is said on the label. Therefore, I would argue very strongly that we should remove Article 4 from the original Commission proposal and we adopt Article 11 along the lines that the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety has suggested.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

