<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Nutrition and health claims in labelling</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0128/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adriana POLI BORTONE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Marianne Thyssen</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE–DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I do not know whether the average European now lives more healthily than they once did, but it is a fact that many people are tending, in certain ways, to become more healthy, and I do not think that that is such a bad thing. Needless to say, this has not escaped the attention of the food industry in its zeal for sales, which, we have also noticed, manages at times to find very innovative and positive ways of accommodating the consumer’s sensitivities. What we establish today and what we have, in fact, known for years, is that summary legislation that exists at European level in this area is lagging behind and that it is therefore high time we adapted the legislative framework in a bid to protect the consumer effectively, provide them with useful information, offer sufficient legal certainty, which will, in turn, stimulate innovation and really harmonise the rules within the internal market. The Commission proposal meets these criteria in the sense that it allows for more fact, more benefit, better scientific underpinning and more harmonisation, but a number of changes, as already mentioned by fellow Members, must be carried out. An area which would benefit from cutting back is notification, at least the admission procedure for admitting certain individual claims. In our opinion, control is possible via notification, and a bureaucratic admission procedure is really a bridge too far. Also, we consider the nutrient profiles that are proposed in a proposal for a directive, to carry at least one claim, to be superfluous. That too is taking matters too far and other Members have indicated the reasons why. Finally, I think that we should say that there is no justification for ruling out alcoholic products from any possible claim from the word go. We know that nothing has been left to chance, and that the Commission, the competent or representative organisations from all quarters, and also this House, have put an enormous amount of preparatory work into this. Thirteen years ago, I was a very green Member of this House. My first telephone call to the Commission was one to enquire about the progress made with the health claims, which were an issue as long ago as that. I am pleased that we are, at last, voting on them tomorrow, and I hope that the outcome will be a satisfactory one.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

