<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Nutrition and health claims in labelling</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0128/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adriana POLI BORTONE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Frédérique Ries</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, ‘no added sugar’, ‘high in iron’, ‘low in cholesterol’ or else a current best – seller, ‘high in omega – 3s’, health claims nowadays adorn almost all packaging, and quite naturally influence our choices as consumers. We therefore need to guide the consumer through this veritable jungle, and that is the aim of this excellent proposal for a regulation: first to ensure that the claims are accurate, as a minimum, and then to put an end to those that cause misunderstandings. I will return to my example: high in omega – 3s. In principle, this is very good, but obviously not for products too high in fat, sugar or salt. The text refers to health and nutrition claims, not to advertising, as we heard here today. No product will be banned, and neither will advertising. Quite simply, the honest thing for these products would be to focus the advertising on pleasure, if manufacturers wish, and not on health. That is why it is vital, tomorrow, that we reinstate nutritional benefit at the heart of the text, a criterion that is recognised by the WHO, in particular to combat the disease of this century, obesity, which affects 40% of children in Europe. A criterion that will also ban any form of health claim for alcoholic drinks, which is the least we can do, you will agree. In conclusion, if tomorrow we follow the excellent work of our rapporteur, Mrs Bortone, and change direction, it will prove that this Parliament truly cares about the interests of good – faith manufacturers, I would say, and of European consumers.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

