<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Nutrition and health claims in labelling</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0128/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adriana POLI BORTONE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Åsa Westlund</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SV</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, there are many people who are anxious about the increase in obesity and the ill health it causes to many people and, in particular, to already vulnerable groups: those on very low incomes. This is a major social problem but, perhaps above all, a major problem for the individuals affected. That is why there are also many individuals who try to shop more healthily and to choose healthier food. Unfortunately, their attempts are unscrupulously exploited by companies that try to make products such as cornflakes, soft drinks and suchlike appear more beneficial than they really are. As a representative of the people, I do in actual fact think that those of us here in the European Parliament need to ensure that no consumer is duped into buying products they really do not want. We must therefore demand that the whole of a product’s content be taken account of when health claims are made. Otherwise, I for one shall not be able to support this report. It is obviously especially important that no one be duped into buying drinks containing alcohol, with the problems we know they cause, in the belief that these drinks are beneficial. Health claims should not, therefore, be used on alcoholic drinks. In no respect is this, of course, a matter of prescribing what people should eat. Rather, it is about giving people the right and the opportunities to make well – informed choices for themselves. That is why I in actual fact find it hard to understand how, for example, the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats can think that companies should be entitled to mislead consumers. Do you really not believe that companies can manufacture products that consumers want, but that they have to dupe people into buying them?
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

