<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Addition of vitamins and other substances</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0124/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-05-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>16</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin SCHEELE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Frédérique Ries</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, first of all I would like to thank our rapporteur, Mrs Scheele, for the quality of this report on a very meaningful subject for the citizens of Europe. The addition of vitamins and minerals to a very wide variety of foods is a response to a reality – this needs to be stated – much more than simply to a fashion, the reality of a general change in our eating habits. For example, iron – enriched breakfast cereals have in many cases replaced meat as the principal source of iron in children’s food, and that is just one example among many. That is why we must, in my view, show flexibility on this subject. Let us, therefore, say ‘yes’ to better labelling, but ‘no’ to protectionism and to certain derogations as proposed in Amendment 39. ‘No’, finally, to drawing up a positive list for the whole range of new substances. I would like to finish, but I could have started with this, by asking Commissioner Kyprianou a question: when do you expect to implement the better regulation advocated by several members of the Commission, including you and Commissioner Verheugen? Let me explain. Slicing legislation up like salami – fortifications, health and nutrition claims, food supplements, directives on labelling and more besides – brings nothing but restrictions to us as legislators. Technical aspects are increasingly taking over from policy ones. Therefore, particularly in the interests of SMEs and consumers who, if they are going to believe in Europe, need clear, transparent and effective legislation, I hope that the Commission will very soon adopt this overall, consistent approach that we need in the field of food sector legislation.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

