<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European energy networks</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0134/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Anne LAPERROUZE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Andris Piebalgs</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>2</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs Laperrouze, for having taken over this proposal on the guidelines for trans-European energy networks and for having carried out a focused analysis in her report which was adopted by a large majority in the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy. I would like in particular to express my gratitude for her commitment, together with that of the shadow rapporteurs, in aiming for an agreement at first reading which, I very much regret, has not been achieved. Let me recall on this occasion the objectives of the proposal. The challenge of the proposal is to build a legal instrument that will be efficient in delivering the necessary energy transmission infrastructure, while developing the appropriate cooperation with the private sector and the Member States. The security of energy supply and the functioning of the internal energy market are key policy issues. These objectives are taken up in the trans-European Energy – TEN-E – guidelines aiming at the installation of an electricity and gas network of truly European character by better linking the fragmented national networks. Concerning natural gas, there is a strong growth perspective. The trans-European energy networks policy aims at securing and diversifying additional gas import capacity from sources in Russia, Norway, the Caspian basin region, Northern Africa and the Middle East, and providing the necessary interconnection capacity between Member States. Concerning the electricity networks, the main function is to create and foster a real European electricity market. For this objective, sufficient interconnection capacity between Member States is essential. Since the adoption of the existing guidelines for trans-European energy networks in June 2003, the need has arisen fully to integrate the new Member States and candidate countries in these guidelines and further to adapt those guidelines to the new European Neighbourhood policy. The revision of the TEN-E guidelines proposed by the Commission in December 2003 should be seen as a complement to and an improvement on the existing guidelines. It aims at explicitly incorporating the ten new Member States into the priority projects, as well as the incorporation of essential energy connections with third countries. As to the choice of the projects, we have proposed to introduce a top-down approach, identifying the projects of highest priority on the priority axes from the larger family of projects of common interest. The projects of European interest are those of highest priority. They have the objective of supporting the rapid implementation of the most important cross-border interconnection capacity. To achieve this aim, the projects of European interest need to comply with special criteria. They must be situated on a priority axis. They are of a cross-border nature or have significant impact on cross-border transmission capacity. They must be mature: that means that a firm commitment must exist to start before the end of 2006 and that the projects need to be completed by 2010 at the latest. Another essential element of our proposal is the European Coordinator. The European Coordinator will encourage cooperation with users and operators, and promote the projects amongst private investors and financial institutions. A coordinator may be designated by the Commission and will act in the name of, and on behalf of, the Commission. I now look forward with great interest to your debate on the proposal.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

