<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European energy networks</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0134/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Anne LAPERROUZE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Anne Laperrouze</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>3</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I would like to thank the Commissioner for his kind remarks. Ladies and gentlemen, let me also express my deepest gratitude to my fellow rapporteurs for their opinions, which have been in my mind throughout my considerations and which have made a considerable contribution to the report that I am presenting today. I would also like to thank the representatives of the European Commission and the representatives of the Council for their attention and for their answers to the many questions we have raised. Finally, my thanks go to the secretariat of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy and to my assistant for the help that they have given me. Commissioner, you recalled the objectives of this proposal for a decision. They are to adapt the guidelines to the shape of the European Union of 25 Member States, to authorise the financing of common-interest projects, to make it possible to create an internal market for gas and electricity and, principally, to ensure that there is security of supply via interconnections between the Member States and with neighbouring countries: south-east Europe, the Mediterranean countries, Ukraine, Belarus. This approach to the trans-European energy networks corresponds, in fact, to the approach taken for the trans-European land transport networks. A majority of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy supports the new ideas introduced by the European Commission to define the action priorities, particularly the description of projects of European interest located on high-priority routes and the appointment of a European coordinator, provided, however, that this is limited to complex projects that present particularly difficult implementation conditions and that it occurs in consultation with the Member States. Parliament must also be consulted on the appointment of the coordinator, which is the aim of the amendment proposed by my group. The report voted for by the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy encourages the Member States to cooperate amongst themselves when this is made necessary by the implementation of transnational enquiry procedures taking into account decisive criteria, such as security of supply, the project’s impact on the environment, the opinion of the inhabitants of the territory concerned, and so on. On the basis of information provided by the Council, the Committee on Industry felt that the Council’s recommended approach was consistent and made it possible to simplify the Commission’s original proposal. Thus, the report voted for by the Committee on Industry establishes a hierarchy of projects: common-interest projects that form the basis of the trans-European projects are listed in Annex III and priority projects described as projects of European interest are listed in Annex I. The Committee on Industry did not want to call into question the projects established by the Member States, because it felt that it did not have sufficient competence or information to assess the choice of projects. Nevertheless, following comments made by some of my fellow Members, I would like to ask the European Commission to verify the validity of the projects when this decision is applied. By way of example, our fellow Members from the Baltic States think that it would be more appropriate to have a gas transport network crossing the Baltic States to supply them, rather than an offshore network in the Baltic. As another example, the EHT line between France and Spain is giving rise to very forceful protests from the inhabitants of the region. That is why the financial package allocated to these projects should be increased to EUR 60 million, which would make it possible, for example, to respond better to environmental constraints, which may require more thorough feasibility studies. It is a matter of validating the projects, of coordinating the procedures for consultation between the Member States, of finding the most appropriate technical solutions. Before I finish, I would also like to stress the fact that the Committee on Industry views the inclusion of the transport of olefins in this text as justified not only in view of the importance of such networks in Europe for the European chemical industry, but also in view of the gains in terms of safety and the environment that would result from a reduction in road transport. Besides access to the European Investment Bank, the reference to olefin-related projects guarantees a symbolic European label. It does not, however, enable these projects to benefit from European subsidies under the budget for trans-European networks. I think it is also necessary to consider the integration of the trans-European energy networks into the European corridors that have been proposed for the land transport sector.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

