<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European energy networks</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0134/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Anne LAPERROUZE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Guntars Krasts</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>LV</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>UEN</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I would like to thank the Commission and the committee responsible for the work they have accomplished, and it should be emphasised that the directive which we are to discuss today is particularly important in taking the European Union’s physical integration a stage further. I would, however, like to draw your attention to a few aspects which might stand in the way of achieving the tasks advanced in the directive. Thus, creating interconnections in structured supply systems is not always in the interests of those suppliers who dominate in any particular region. In such cases, investment in interconnections must be assessed from the perspective of medium-term and long-term returns. This requires market principles to be replaced by long-term planning methods to guarantee security of supply for consumers and environmental protection. The thinking is similar when an interconnection has to be created in the interests of security of supply, to overcome an inadequacy of production capacity. In such cases it is not always possible to adhere to market principles, as the time required for recovering the investments may not correspond to the objectives of a participant in the competitive market. In cases where creating new interconnections is not in the interests of participants in the electricity market, creating network elements may be a public service obligation for system operators. Therefore, the choice of the priority interconnection elements of trans-European networks which will be created with the financial support of the European Union should not only be a matter for commercial competition between regions and Member States, as appears from the approach offered by the directive. When making its choice of priority network elements, the European Commission must be guided by the interests of medium-term and long-term security of supply and the creation of the European Union internal market. The European Parliament ought to retain a supervisory role over this process through the budget procedure. In this connection, I should like to draw attention to the fact that the three Baltic States are totally isolated from the European Union’s electricity and gas market. Since Soviet times they have been in a joint electricity supply network with Russia. This ought to be a priority task, a priority area where interconnections should be created.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

