<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European energy networks</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0134/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Anne LAPERROUZE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>María del Pilar Ayuso González</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I would like to begin by congratulating Mrs Laperrouze and thanking her for her spirit of cooperation during the production of this report. The importance of this proposal stems from the fact that the development of interconnections is a necessary condition for the creation of a genuine internal market in energy. Furthermore, the interconnections will provide us with better guarantees for dealing with occasional situations of scarcity of electricity supply. As has been pointed out, following the informal three-way dialogue with the Council and the Commission, it was not possible to reach an agreement with Parliament at first reading. We do not agree with the Council’s desire to eliminate projects of European interest and we support maintaining the categories of project advocated by the rapporteur. We also support the rapporteur’s amendment that modifies the text relating to the post of European coordinator, maintaining the amendment approved in the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, to the effect that the coordinator should be appointed for those projects that raise difficulties and that Parliament should be consulted in relation to the appointment of the coordinator, something that was approved in the case of the trans-European transport networks. I would like to highlight a very important amendment, presented and approved in the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy. I am talking about a new recital 2(a) which takes up the objective established by the Barcelona European Council that electrical interconnections between the Member States should account for 10% of installed generation capacity. It only remains for me to applaud the Commission’s proposal for a Regulation, which is being debated, on the funding of the trans-European transport and energy networks. That proposal, for the first time, provides for the co-funding of projects in the field of energy and not just preliminary studies. I trust that this will be taken into account when establishing the financial perspectives for 2007-2013 because, if the budgetary allocation is reduced, this and all of the European Union’s programmes, such as Rural Development, Life, Trans-European Networks and the Seventh Framework Research Project, will be negatively affected.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

