<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European energy networks</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0134/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Anne LAPERROUZE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Reino Paasilinna</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the trans-European networks are important for achieving the Lisbon objectives. Energy brings synergy. The TEN-E networks in the energy sector will play an important role in the liberalisation of the internal market and in improving operational reliability, as they will enable the EU to connect to suppliers outside the Union. The energy networks should not, however, be treated in the same way as trans-European transport networks. Transport networks are part of the general infrastructure, whereas the TEN-E networks are in private ownership. Accordingly, public funds for the energy networks should be spent mainly on planning and research. In any case, this sum of money is so small for the Union’s energy networks that it will not be a critical factor when investment decisions are being made. A Coordinator would hardly be of any great value either: it would simply create a new organisational level once again. In matters of expertise just a little money should bear fruit. As far as certain details in the report are concerned, I am suspicious about mentioning the priority projects as proposed by the Commission. Their preparation has not been systematic: in practice it has been quite random. Do not let us emphasise the status of certain projects, then, but above all, the importance of Union-wide investigations into what we should invest in. Ladies and gentlemen, we all the while need to ensure that the operational reliability of energy does not lead to wastefulness, but savings. According to new estimates, all energy sources apart from renewables may run out within a few generations, depending on levels of consumption.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

