<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European energy networks</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0134/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Anne LAPERROUZE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Andris Piebalgs</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I wish to thank Members for a fruitful debate. However, we should be very honest in looking at the trans-European networks in the energy field. It is clearly a necessity because the security of our energy supplies depends on our energy networks, and on interconnection as the most important part of it. When we speak about a competitive market, again interconnection is an absolute necessity. From this point of view, I cannot accept that there should be no policies at the European level. So the guidelines are clearly there to justify our approach. We spend EUR 20 million a year on trans-European energy networks. The money is for feasibility studies and perhaps in the future we can provide support for the projects. There have been advocates from the Baltic States for particular projects. At this stage it is clear, as one Member said, that the Baltic States are like an isolated island: there is no interconnection of electricity. There will be interconnection from Estonia to Finland. However, the PowerBridge Project between Lithuania and Poland will never be a reality unless there is Community support for trans-European networks in energy. I strongly advocate the approach we have delivered. Concerning broader support for energy, we definitely need to diversify our supplies. For this reason we are working with all the countries and also with Azerbaijan, which I visited. No European company was involved, but we need to be involved from the beginning. Four countries have signed the Treaty. The Commission could not do so, but we are interested in this project because it concerns oil that that will be used by customers. We are interested in gas supplies but, at the same time, as we are not financing the project we cannot expect to take all the credit. Therefore, we are thinking about diversifying our security supplies. At the same time, as I mentioned, the main sources of investment are from private investors. Therefore the private investors should invest in the project and the Commission, through these guidelines, should provide the necessary political input. So I am very grateful for today’s debate. We will continue our work. I wish to thank in particular the rapporteur, Mrs Laperrouze. As concerns olefin and Amendment 39, I am sorry to say that at this stage the Commission simply notes the importance of olefin networks, without going into detail about the priority sections of this network, which will have to be assessed by the European Investment Bank for every specific proposal for financing. Therefore, the Commission does not propose a financing intervention by means of European Community money. For this reason, we cannot support Amendment 39. However, as I mentioned, the Commission’s and Parliament’s proposal are very close. I wish to thank Parliament again for its very close cooperation.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

