<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Energy end-use efficiency</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0130/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mechtild ROTHE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Andris Piebalgs</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>2</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    First of all I would like to thank Mrs Rothe for her excellent work in producing this report. I would also like to thank the other members of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy who have drafted amendments and worked to improve the Commission proposal. Many of these amendments will strengthen and add coherence to the proposal. As you know, I consider energy efficiency in the Union to be a priority area for Community energy policy. I am gratified that the European Parliament strongly shares this view. The proposal for a directive on energy end-use efficiency and energy services can prove to be one of the most effective tools at our disposal, not only as a means of combating climate change and improving competitiveness, but for improving our security of supply, increasing employment within the EU and establishing a viable market for energy efficiency. As you know the Commission is also in the process of preparing a Green Paper on energy efficiency. This paper is designed to stimulate public debate on the usefulness of improving energy efficiency in the European Union and the best way to do this. The debate on the Green Paper will also focus attention on the energy services proposal and on its role. The proposal for a directive on energy end-use efficiency and energy services has several important objectives and means to achieve these objectives: it sets uniform energy savings targets to be achieved in each Member State through improved energy efficiency and energy services; it is also designed to stimulate market development for energy services and for energy efficiency in general; it applies to distribution and retail sales to most final customers of most types of end-use energy, such as electricity, gas, district heating, heating oil, and most of the transport fuel sector. It is ‘fuel neutral’ in that it seeks to improve energy efficiency regardless of the primary energy involved. We have also proposed that Member States place an obligation on their energy distributors or retailers above a certain size, requiring them to offer their end-use customers energy efficiency measures or, alternatively, fulfil other energy efficiency obligations, while allowing the necessary flexibility. The proposal also sets forth requirements for Member States to promote financial instruments for saving energy, such as performance contracting and third-party financing contracts; to improve metering and consumer information; and to promote the certification of energy service providers and improve the quality and use of energy audits. The proposal also provides for Member State regulators to improve their distribution tariff structures when possible, in order to promote energy efficiency. Two issues that were discussed extensively in the European Parliament and in the Council were the compulsory character of the targets and the measurement systems for energy efficiency achievements. Throughout the debates in Parliament and in the Council, the Commission has maintained its position on the importance of mandatory targets, for both the overall target and for the public sector target. As regards measuring efficiency, Mrs Rothe’s report points out that a system with bottom-up measurement provides the necessary accuracy and robustness and can be further developed with comitology. We also believe that comitology is the way forward because these issues would be too technical and detailed for coping with in the codecision process. We do, however, see a need to maintain some top-down measurements. I will have the opportunity later to comment in more detail on the amendments put forward to this House but I would like already to say that the Parliamentary debates in committee have been extremely constructive, and that we have appreciated in particular the efforts of the rapporteur and the shadow rapporteurs in developing a coherent and consistent report, with many constructive amendment proposals. I look forward to the debate you will have on the proposal.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

