<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Energy end-use efficiency</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0130/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mechtild ROTHE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Corien Wortmann-Kool</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, first of all I should like to thank Mrs Rothe for the dedication she has shown in producing this report. In stating its position, the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs has mainly emphasised the cost-effective approach towards energy efficiency. In addition, we have proposed a number of amendments, on a few key points of which there is, fortunately agreement, but the Committee believes that ultimate proposal does not go far enough, particularly with regard to the flexibility that we have to offer to the Member States where the objectives of energy efficiency are concerned. Consideration should be given to the different degrees of energy efficiency that exist in the Member States. I am pleased, though, with compromise amendment 107, because it provides, or at least can provide, more flexibility for national objectives. That is in itself a good thing, but we should not at the same time stand by the compulsory objectives for each Member State and consequently keep the door open to uniform compulsory objectives being prescribed for each country. I do not think, therefore, that we should abide by the obligation in this respect. Secondly, it is important for SMEs – which make a considerable contribution in reducing energy consumption – to be guaranteed a major role in the market. The requirement that energy suppliers provide free energy audits would harm SMEs and it is therefore a good thing that this has been abolished. Thirdly, this leads the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs to believe that we must promote a cost-effective approach. It is of major importance for energy efficiency to go hand in hand with sound cost-benefit analysis. The proposal to introduce benchmarks will certainly encourage the spread of best practice, but it is important to set up a possible benchmark system in such a way as to ensure that it does not produce paperwork that cancels out the value added by the benchmarks.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

