<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Energy end-use efficiency</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0130/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mechtild ROTHE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Alejo Vidal-Quadras Roca</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I would like to begin by thanking Mrs Rothe and all the shadow rapporteurs who have participated in the production of the report for their willingness to seek points of agreement. It has been a pleasure, as always, to work with such constructive and reasonable colleagues. As Mrs Rothe has already explained, after a long negotiation we have reached a satisfactory agreement on the proposal for a Directive. I believe that this compromise demonstrates the enormous importance that all of us who have participated in the discussion attach to the issue of energy efficiency, as well as considerable agreement on the objectives of this piece of legislation. Security of supply and fulfilment of the objectives we have established in relation to climate change, not to mention those laid down in the Lisbon Agenda, oblige us to take a multi-dimensional approach to energy policy. I believe that it is important to stress the necessary balance between the establishment of ambitious and realistic general European objectives and their flexible adaptation to the specific situation of each Member State. It is fair to acknowledge that some countries have made considerable efforts in the past, which have led to undeniable improvements in energy efficiency, and these achievements must be recognised when it comes to deciding on the objectives to be fulfilled. It is also important to make it clear that the ultimate purpose of this directive is not exclusively to reduce consumption, since in countries in which there are significant sources free of emissions it is perfectly acceptable to take a more flexible approach which is more in line with their economic growth needs. Madam President, I am pleased to reiterate my group’s satisfaction with this new step towards the goal, which we all want to achieve, of combining security of supply, protection of the environment and the competitiveness of the Union’s economy in the global market.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

