<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Energy end-use efficiency</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0130/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mechtild ROTHE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Reino Paasilinna</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, my group supports all possible energy saving schemes. They are vital for us to be able to achieve the Kyoto objectives and reduce our dependence on imported energy. Mrs Rothe has undertaken a mammoth task, and I thank her for it. She has had very broad support for her proposal. The compromises have not come about easily, but now they have the support of the major political groups. The proposal entering the debate is an ambitious one. The proposals for energy saving targets, in particular, are even tougher than those in the Commission’s proposal. Trans-European objectives are a good thing. We have seen that, without them, Member States wriggle out of their responsibilities over and over again. The fact is, however, that the position of the Member States in this respect varies considerably from one to another. This proposal will cost my country a lot of money, as we drew up a list of considerable savings measures a long time ago. In fact, we were got started too early, and now we have to pay the price for that a second time. An annual 1% savings target is therefore unfair, because for Finland that would mean increasing the present costs of financing energy saving by 450 million to a billion euros. It is my sincere hope that we will see a change, and that one day, ladies and gentlemen, we will all be prepared to support directives which seem inevitable but which cost our own country very much when the circumstances are so unfavourable. I would like to point out that we have implemented all the directives that are connected with the Lisbon process.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

