<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Energy end-use efficiency</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0130/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mechtild ROTHE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Manuel António dos Santos</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, as things stand in the market, and in light of the supply model in most EU countries, we will only be able to achieve a sustainable European energy policy if there is a considerable increase in energy end-use efficiency. Consequently, the proposal by the Commission on which this report is based, albeit only one element of a much broader body of legislation, represents a key step on the road towards achieving this objective. This issue is all the more crucial given the fact that energy efficiency levels are known to vary a great deal between the Member States. This creates discrepancies and, worse, waste, which is utterly unjustifiable in the context of a future internal market. The model proposed by the Commission is based on rules that are clearly laid down, yet it is also sufficiently flexible and workable, and will encourage the 25 Member States to save energy. Mrs Rothe approaches the issue from both a global and a specific perspective, which is welcome and helpful. Proposing more ambitious targets for energy saving – and structuring those targets on three different levels – enshrines active intervention on Parliament’s part. This sends out a clear message to the Council that the Union’s energy policy aims are being complied with. Also relevant and worthy of note are the objectives set for the public sector – which are even more ambitious – and the creation of an energy efficiency fund accessible to every supplier of energy services, which will benefit households and small and medium-sized businesses, although it must be acknowledged that implementing them will be no easy task. Given the current state of economic development and the practical realities of the internal energy market, further incentives must be put in place to encourage energy efficiency. Global energy policy is about far more than efficiency, however. It is increasingly based on ever-broader new energy sources, and on the safe integration of the Trans-European networks, a philosophy that corresponds to the way in which the transport networks currently operate, as has been mentioned in this House. It is also essential to move towards tariff and contract harmonisation, thereby giving real dimension to European energy policy.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

