<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Energy end-use efficiency</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0130/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mechtild ROTHE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Catherine Stihler</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I welcome this directive, as it will primarily help energy users to reduce and monitor their electricity consumption. This measure will require companies to give energy consumers accurate information to allow them to regulate consumption, compare their consumption with a normal user in a similar building and in an ecologically efficient building, and assess the environmental impact of, for example, the CO2 emission levels of the energy they consume. Consumers deserve to have full and fair information on their energy use. The UK gas and energy watchdog, Energywatch, does an excellent job in giving information to consumers. For example, if you type in your postcode on their website you can find out who is your cheapest supplier. We all know that efficiency is absolutely essential. I hope implementation of this directive will be fast-tracked in Britain to make it easier for consumers to play their part in reducing energy consumption and tackling climate change. The directive will require the introduction of smart metering services that allow consumers to check at a glance how much energy they are using and how much it will cost. The new meters are obviously part of a package of measures that will also force energy companies for the first time to give individual consumers accurate and detailed bills, along with information about the environmental impact of their energy use. Climate change is one of the fundamental challenges facing us today and it is vital that we reduce carbon emissions across Europe to help meet this challenge. Progress in this area will require radical changes and investment decisions and behaviour by governments and individual households. This directive will enable people and businesses to assess accurately the environmental and financial impacts of their energy consumption and make informed choices on how to reduce such impacts. I fully support this directive and I welcome the work of the rapporteur.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

