<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Infrastructure for spatial information in the Community (INSPIRE) </TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0108/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>3</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Frederika BREPOELS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>1</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>María Isabel Salinas García</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I too would like to begin by congratulating the rapporteur, as well as all the shadow rapporteurs, on their work and dedication in trying to improve this proposal for a Directive and on trying to reach a compromise — which has not been possible, but there has been an attempt — with the Council at first reading. I will begin by pointing out that there are still currently certain significant problems in the Member States with regard to access to spatial information and its use, due, amongst other things, to the fragmentation of data sets and sources, gaps in availability, lack of harmonisation between data sets at different geographical scales and duplication of information collection. I therefore do not have the least doubt about the usefulness of this new instrument, which is fundamental to the drawing up, application, monitoring and evaluation of environmental policies at all levels and of policies or activities that may have a direct or indirect impact on the environment. We in my group are therefore pleased that the Member States can guarantee the interoperability between spatial information systems and, in this way, eliminate the obstacles that still exist. One important aspect, which I would like to refer to, is that of funding. In this regard, I would like to stress that, according to the calculations of the European Commission itself, the application of this Directive will cost EUR 5 million per Member State, which represents 1% of the total spending on spatial information, while its application is expected to bring environmental benefits worth more than EUR 30 million per Member State, although it will perhaps be necessary for the directive to clearly establish the legibility conditions within the framework of the existing Community financial instruments for the costs of the planned actions. Furthermore, I believe it is appropriate to base the Community infrastructure on the spatial information infrastructures established and managed by the Member States, in full application of the subsidiarity principle, but amongst those infrastructures, particularly when the Member States, such as mine, have several levels of public administration. Finally, I would like to thank both the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety and the Council for their understanding, so that this proposal can provide for an analysis of soil erosion, since we must not forget the current significance of the progressive loss of soil throughout the European Union, and I would also like to express my concern about the specific role that the European Environment Agency should play in terms of creating the infrastructure necessary for the correct application of our objectives, since I still have some doubts in this field. I would like to echo the congratulations expressed by this House, particularly to the rapporteur, and I believe that this mechanism that we are going to approve tomorrow will undoubtedly provide more clarity within the European Union's mechanisms.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

