<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Infrastructure for spatial information in the Community (INSPIRE) </TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0108/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>3</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Frederika BREPOELS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>1</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Vittorio Prodi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I, too, would like to thank Mrs Brepoels for the work she has carried out, which we carried out together. The Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe endorses the report, insofar as it represents a very significant coordination effort between the Member States. The Council’s short-sighted attitude is regrettable, however, because, on the one hand, it has confined itself to environmental applications and, on the other hand, it has made little use of the Commission’s coordination capacities. The Commission can carry out a far more important role. Such a short-sighted attitude will require these topics to be re-examined in future, when it will be necessary precisely to make the document more general and to include possible areas for implementation – which will soon be extended by the availability of satellite systems, in particular GALILEO. These possible areas include, for instance, air, land and sea navigation assistance, support for land use and monitoring, which is yet to be taken to its logical conclusions, and the collection of statistical data with georeferenced points of reference, which could provide suggestions for further correlations. In our legislative capacity, however, we must also consider the need to draw up fewer documents, of a more general nature. I hope, therefore, that we can return to this topic, precisely in order to make it an extremely important instrument, since we need it for much more than the environment.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

