<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Infrastructure for spatial information in the Community (INSPIRE) </TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0108/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>3</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Frederika BREPOELS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>1</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Gerard Batten</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, this directive should be named Expire rather than Inspire, considering the detrimental effect it will have on the Ordnance Survey mapping agency of Great Britain. Ordnance Survey has been in existence for 215 years and has a long and distinguished record. Over the last 20 years or so, it has built itself up from a government-funded organisation into a successful commercial enterprise. Under its current arrangements, it has responsibility for its own finances and freedom to develop new customer-related initiatives. Inspire puts all that at risk and will undermine its successful commercial operation. Why is this being done? Once more we see the dead hand of EU harmonisation and the EU’s need to control every aspect of its Member States’ lives. Also evident in this directive is the sinister presence of Galileo, the EU’s ‘big brother’ spy satellite, its eye in the sky. How much more effective that will be when the EU has control of national mapping services. According to the Commission’s own report, those involved in the formulation, implementation, monitoring and evaluation of policies, particularly the Commission itself, will be the main beneficiaries of this proposal. The British Government should have told the EU to get lost. However, we can always rely on its cowardice and craven surrender to the EU. I would ask you to vote against this directive, but knowing your insatiable appetite for more and more legislation, I know I am wasting my breath. Perhaps the growing torrent of damaging legislation imposed on the United Kingdom might help to bring the British Government and its people to their senses and bring forward the day of Britain’s unconditional withdrawal from the European Union.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

