<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Infrastructure for spatial information in the Community (INSPIRE) </TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0108/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>3</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Frederika BREPOELS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>1</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Eija-Riitta Korhola</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the success of the Community’s environmental policy depends very much on the availability of reliable scientific data and the trouble-free transmission of that data. The availability of spatial data is a necessary precondition for scientific evaluation conducted on the basis of environmental legislation. The standardisation of spatial data collected from the Member States has still not made any great progress, as there are still serious barriers at Community level that are hampering the exploitation of the available information. We must therefore try to improve the way spatial data is used and accessed, to facilitate the planning, implementation, monitoring and evaluation of policies. The purpose is to provide a knowledge base to take decisions on policies relating to the environment and in this way promote sustainable development. That is the goal. The Community has various instruments at its disposal to help improve access to reliable data, in particular public sector data, in the first place, and later standardise it to make it comparable at Community level. One of them is the directive on public access to environmental information, for which I myself was rapporteur. The problems observed when it was being discussed should now be taken into careful consideration as we debate this proposal for a directive which would create a legal framework for the establishment of an infrastructure for spatial information in Europe. One problem with both these directives is that it is feared that losses of income for certain data providers will result. I would therefore advise that we tread carefully right now, to avoid surprises. The most important objective is to reduce obstacles that hamper the shared use of data, particularly environmental data, among public authorities. The Community’s spatial data infrastructure will supplement the directives on the re-use of public sector information and public access to environmental information. I myself think it is very important that in establishing a spatial data infrastructure we should focus specifically on environmental policy, in which case there would be practical grounds for the centralisation of information.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

