<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Infrastructure for spatial information in the Community (INSPIRE) </TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0108/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>3</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Frederika BREPOELS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>1</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Stavros Dimas</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, first of all I would like to thank Mrs Salinas García for underlining the fact that the benefits of Inspire will by far outweigh the cost. Regarding Mrs Brepoels’ comments on intellectual property rights, I would like to stress that these are not significantly compromised by the proposed directive. In particular, it does not in any way affect the principle of co-existence or ownership of intellectual property rights. Intellectual property rights held by public authorities must be exercised in a way that is compatible with the aim of Inspire, which is to ensure a maximum of data selling between public authorities, as well as public access to the data. Nevertheless, to answer some of Mr Batten’s concerns, the proposed directive explicitly allows public authorities to charge for data to be downloaded by the public. Mr Seeber is right in his comments on comitology. This is indeed a technical directive and many of the detailed rules, for example on how to ensure interoperability between data systems, can only be decided at expert level. I agree with Mrs Korhola. I would like to stress that the Inspire proposal builds on the access to information directive, incorporating the same type of restrictions on public access to information, and is fully complementary with the Aarhus Convention. Generally, I am very pleased to say that I can accept a large majority of the amendments proposed, at least in principle. A few of the amendments aim to clarify the obligations on public authorities in relation to public access and data selling and to provide safeguards for data providers in relation to intellectual property rights. Amendments 3 and 26 can be accepted in their entirety, while Amendments 28 and 29 can be accepted in principle. Most of the other amendments seek to provide technical clarification of the proposal. Some of these – Amendments 8 to 12 – are intended to make the structure of the text clearer and can also be accepted, although Amendment 9 introduces further small changes which can be only partly accepted. Some amendments introduce other clarifications and can be accepted, while a number of others require some rewording or further clarification, so can only be accepted in principle. There are just six amendments that we cannot accept. Amendments 2 and 7 seek to extend the scope of the directive to include data held by Community institutions and bodies. While we have no problem with this in substance, it would create substantial obligations on Community institutions and bodies and this cannot be done in the context of a directive. Amendment 30 deletes a reference to measures taken to prevent distortion of competition and would make the text unclear. Amendments 52, 53 and 54 give Member States more time to implement certain provisions of the directive. Delaying the implementation of key provisions will, however, also delay the benefits that will result from their implementation, an option which is not favoured by the Commission.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

