<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0104/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-09</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adamos ADAMOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Adamos Adamou</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>3</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Madam Vice-President, today we are debating the 27th amendment to Directive 76/769 relating to restrictions on the marketing and use of certain polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in extender oils and tyres. This is an important development, if you consider that the European tyre industry produces around 300 million tyres annually and uses 250 000 tonnes of extender oils, which are incorporated into the rubber matrix and remain in the rubber used for the end tyre. These oils contain certain quantities of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, which are classified as carcinogenic, mutagenic and reprotoxic substances, as well as persistent organic pollutants. I should like to start by congratulating the Commission on its initiative to extend Annex 1 to Directive 76/769 by the addition of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons to car tyres. I consider that its proposal is a very good proposal. Taking as a starting point the protection of public health and the environment, as well as public safety and the smooth functioning of the internal market, and following consultations both with the Commission and the Council, as well as with the tyre and oil industry and non-governmental organisations, I tried to draft a balanced report, which was amended accordingly by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety. The main issues which concerned us were the duration of the transitional period for the application of the directive, the method of detecting the toxic substances which would be used and the question of exemptions from the directive. Following consultations with the Council and in cooperation with the shadow rapporteurs, a package of amendments was proposed, which has been endorsed by most of the political groups. As you can see, I have recommended the tabled amendments, so that we can bring this matter to a smooth conclusion at first reading. In detail and as regards the transitional period, which is considered necessary in order to develop new types of tyres with extender oils which contain the minimum quantity of the substances which concern us, it is proposed that it be extended to 1 January 2010. We should point out here that, for environmental reasons, we decided to take account of the date of manufacture of the tyre, which is marked on the tyre itself. That is because the destruction of tyres remaining in stock is also harmful – perhaps even more harmful – to the environment and, of course, we are also helping industry to dispose of these stocks. The European Federation of Tyre Manufacturers has assured us in writing that it can apply the criteria in the directive to all types of tyres, including tyres for racing cars, aeroplanes and special vehicles and vintage cars, without any risk to driver safety. We therefore propose that there should be no exemption in the application of the directive. Today I received three faxes protesting that we should grant extensions. I have spoken to all three senders and, when I explained the compromise proposal, they appeared to agree with it. One of them even apologised for his ignorance. As regards the methods for detecting and defining polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, the Commission has proposed limiting the quantity of benzo[a]pyrene, the substance which will act as a marker for the entire group, to 1 mg per kilogramme or, taking all listed PAHs, to no more than 10 mg per kilogramme. In the past, industry has used IP 346 method of the Institute of Petroleum for PAC-dimethyl sulfoxide extract, which must not exceed 3%. Its inclusion has been proposed, given that it is the traditional method used. So much for extender oils. As far as the oil content in car tyres is concerned, as ISO 21461 method has been developed in order to detect this type of oils in tyres, it is proposed that it be defined in the directive as an addendum to the Commission proposal. Finally, the last amendment concerns retreading, on which the Commission proposal contains no provisions. Tread for retreading may not be placed on the market if it contains extender oils exceeding the limits indicated. To close, I should like to thank both the shadow rapporteurs, for their excellent cooperation, and the secretarial staff of the Committee on the Environment, as well as the Council for its constructive proposals and cooperation, which will allow us to bring this matter to a close at first reading.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

