<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0104/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-09</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adamos ADAMOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Robert Sturdy</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I hope the Commissioner has finished texting everybody to say that they have got the tyre manufacturers sorted out. Obviously he has not, as he is not listening to what we are saying. I congratulate the rapporteur on his report. It was a difficult and very technical report and required a certain amount of skill. I also wish to congratulate the tyre manufacturers, because over the years they have improved road safety, the availability of tyres and also the tread and the capacity of the tyre to stick to the road. That was why I know that my fellow rapporteur had a slight problem with the date 2010. I realise that he wanted to stick to the original Commission proposal of 2009, but a number of tyres could not be changed for that date and that is why we opted for the date on the tyre. I am delighted to hear that he has accepted that. It is good that the Commission and the Council have accepted, because we have come forward with a compromise package for its acceptance. Particularly in the current climate, after the French and the Dutch votes, people often see the Council and the Commission – the Commission in particular – as aloof from Parliament, the only democratically elected body that represents the electorate. Mr Adamou quite rightly mentioned Annex I and I am grateful to him for going through all the technical details for something we totally accept and agree with. This report is a triumph for Parliament and I am delighted that we have come up with a compromise package. I am just sorry the Commissioner is unable to listen to what we are saying and is too busy texting people.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

