<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0104/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-06-09</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Adamos ADAMOU</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Eija-Riitta Korhola</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I wish to thank the rapporteur for his work in support of the Commission’s policy and the excellent compromise he has proposed. As the Commission line is broadly acceptable, Parliament should support it without watering down the issue to any greater extent. The legislative initiative under discussion is a natural extension to the directive that was drafted in Parliament’s last term and in which we laid down limit and target values for impurities in the air and PAHs for 1996. As we now decide a suitable timetable and limit values for PAH emissions passing into the rest of the environment, we have a challenging task before us. PAHs are everywhere and they occur as multicomponent blends. In international toxicology assessments several carcinogenic compounds have been identified among PAHs. PAHs do not dissolve in water, they accumulate in the food chain, and they return to the carbon cycle when released into the environment, thus causing lasting damage to nature. Accordingly, we should agree common testing procedures in order to bring emissions under control swiftly. For a long time now development and testing work has been conducted on tyres, and, indeed, the first tyres containing a safer oil are already on the market. Traffic, in which the tyres that are used and the limit values for their extender oils we now want to regulate, is in itself ecologically problematic. Traffic emissions are one of the commonest and worst spreaders of PAHs into the air we breathe. It is from tyre debris in particular that large quantities of compounds in the form of small particles are released into the environment. A particular problem with tyres and extender oils is benzopyrene, which, unfortunately, is very often used in these products. This PAH is the best-known and worst carcinogenic substance. We must now define sustainable limit values which will reduce emissions of benzopyrene into the environment to a minimum, at the same time recognising the necessity of extender oils in the tyre industry.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

