<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Security of electricity supply and infrastructure investment</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0099/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-05</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>GILES CHICHESTER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Reino Paasilinna</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I wish to thank my colleague, Mr Chichester, for his excellent work. We have become so dependent on electricity now that we even switch on lights during daylight, such as now. The power cuts in recent years have clearly shown how vulnerable we are. As always, the greatest harm affects the less fortunate, the poor and those of limited means. That is why the Member States and the Union should stress the importance of the security of supply, even though we still have no viable internal electricity market. This is just what is being emphasised in this proposal. Unquestionably, investment needs to be made, for example in transfer capacity, so that congestion can be eliminated. This way the internal market can be developed for the benefit of the consumer. Congestion should therefore be eliminated, which will make exchanges of electricity more effective and the network more stable. It will also facilitate market access conditions. We have to ensure that the same is also true of cross-border networks. There are significant bottlenecks associated with them, of course. The reliability of operations, so important for the public and for business, and the non-discriminatory nature of the market are compatible goals. Member States should ensure that competition is opened up and that existing legislation is implemented. Sluggish implementation of laws slows down Europe as a whole. It is a train that we find difficult to keep running at speed. I would like to remind you all that the Barcelona European Council asked for an assessment at the European Council next spring of the extent to which the internal market for energy has been implemented, and thus the extent to which this proposal has been made part of national legislation. Of course, we also need investment in infrastructure and interconnections. In addition, and in line with the Lisbon Strategy, we should enhance cooperation with the business and scientific worlds. Ecologically speaking, the primary focus should obviously be on energy efficiency and the latest environmental technology. Mr Chichester’s report is in favour of these basic principles of the Union. Ladies and gentlemen, my group supports Mr Chichester’s whole position. We are left with just one task, which is to secure the reliability of this, our common resolve.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

