<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Security of electricity supply and infrastructure investment</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0099/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-05</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>GILES CHICHESTER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Esko Seppänen</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FI</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the rapporteur, Mr Chichester, is right in assuming that we are all unanimously agreed that energy consumption is growing and the share of electricity in our use of energy is increasing. The uninterrupted production of electricity and its secure supply are therefore important. It is the rapporteur’s opinion that the Commission has been too preoccupied with market mechanisms, instead of which it should have proposed some concrete action. Neither does our group believe that the market alone can solve all the problems of production and ensure the security of supply. We in the Nordic countries have bad experiences of the effects of market mechanisms on the price of electricity consumers pay. Electric power passes freely between the Nordic countries: Finland, Sweden, Norway and Denmark. Its price in the Nordic network is determined in their common electricity exchanges. The price reflects the fact that it is determined by marginal power produced at its most expensive, in other words, according to the highest possible price. This market mechanism is very unfavourable for consumers. The fact is that nuclear and hydro-electric power plants obtain the same price for their electricity on the coldest winter days as what is paid for the electricity that comes from coal-fired power stations, which are the last to be connected to the network. When the price of electricity from coal rises still further due to emission rights, the emission-free nuclear and hydro-electric power stations will receive compensation accordingly. For consumers a price mechanism of this nature is totally unsatisfactory. The Nordic electricity markets are a good example of the market not being able to solve all the problems. They are furthermore able to put up the price of electricity in a way that cannot be regarded as acceptable. We need government measures to safeguard different areas of investment.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

