<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Security of electricity supply and infrastructure investment</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0099/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-05</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>GILES CHICHESTER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Vladimír Remek</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>CS</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Ladies and gentlemen, at this point in time I regard the Chichester report as a good compromise, which is why I too will vote in favour of it. Security of supply can naturally be viewed from a number of perspectives, but in my opinion we should not concentrate solely on back-up systems and other technical aspects. After all, optimising the flow of electricity at critical times, or should I say peak load times, could have a considerable impact on the reliability of electricity supply, as well as reducing necessary reserves and costs, and, most importantly, providing greater security at times of potential crisis. I therefore believe that now is the time to set up some sort of independent international coordination centre. Systems are being connected and electricity trading is moving at a faster pace, which means that there is an increasing need for timely and more detailed information about electricity flows. Regional coordination is already in place between the Czech Republic and its neighbours, for example, and the same is true elsewhere. Why should we not provide a framework for such activities in the shape of an independent coordination centre for the EU as a whole?
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

