<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Security of electricity supply and infrastructure investment</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0099/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-05</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>GILES CHICHESTER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Andris Piebalgs</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>14</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to start by commending the rapporteur on the job he has done. The method used to find the best possible solution for the proposal made by the Commission is very admirable. The result is extremely good. At the same time I should like to say that we have faced the same objective. All of us would like to strengthen the security of the supply of electricity. That means that we should find a way to secure long-term investment, stability of investment, conditions for investment, standards for transmission system operators and also inter-connection capacity in the European Union. Strategically the Commission has agreed with all discussions going on in the Council and Parliament. The only difference we have is on how to strengthen the connection capacity. From that point of view I very much hope that the proposal based on the collaboration between the Council and Parliament will work. If it does not, then perhaps we will need to find other methods to strengthen inter-connection capacity, because it is the link in the European energy supply. In general, as already mentioned, this directive definitely cannot rule out blackouts in some places in the European market. It definitely decreases the risks of such a blackout and strengthens the role that the energy sector plays in the well-being of European citizens. Even though the Commission expresses a reservation on one particular issue, if the directive is agreed on this basis at Parliament's first reading, the Commission will welcome this directive. I ask the House to support the compromise amendments tomorrow.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

