<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Stavros Dimas</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>2</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to thank the European Parliament, the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety and, most importantly, the rapporteur, Mrs Isler Béguin, for her detailed and constructive report. My thanks also to the honourable members of the Committee on Budgets and Temporary Committee on the Financial Perspectives for their contribution to the report on LIFE +. LIFE + is the financial instrument for applying Community environmental policy proposed by the Commission for the period 2007-2013. Alongside application, the programme has resources for improving environmental governance and for financing information and communication actions. This proposal is a positive arrangement for financing the environment. As the reports which the Commission prepared for the Council made clear, LIFE + makes provision for an average annual increase in financing of 21% compared with current levels. In addition, it makes provision for the new programme to shift from a project-based approach to an approach based on national programmes. This safeguards greater flexibility for the Member States, so that they can deal with their most pressing environmental needs. This approach implies even greater subsidiarity than at present. Thus the regional and local factors which often lead the way in the application of environmental legislation will be able to have their say on the planning and application of the programme. I am aware of Parliament's evaluation of the Commission proposal. However, the Commission considers that most spending on the environment can be better financed by the financing institutions which are very strong financially, by which I mean programmes for the Structural Funds and rural development programmes. So far there have been three noteworthy developments in our efforts to safeguard the integration policy: firstly, the adoption on 21 June of the regulation on rural development; secondly, the strategic guidelines on rural development relating to the regulation, in which clear reference is made to Natura 2000, and thirdly, the strategic guidelines on regional policy which the Commission adopted last Tuesday and which concern the protection of nature and species. Consequently, the Commission is implementing the policy of integration in the environmental sector. LIFE + will not be able to undertake projects of the scale and breadth for which provision is made in the programmes in question, which is why LIFE + is being called on to supplement these programmes by focusing on the development of environmental policy, as often called for by Parliament, by supporting the exercise of policy, a point on which Parliament has frequently expressed an interest, by improving environmental governance with the participation of civil society and by disseminating information, so that European citizens can understand the objective and repercussions of environmental legislation. These objectives coincide with the wishes expressed by Parliament and, through it, by European citizens, which is why I consider that the Commission proposal is the right proposal.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

