<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Cristina Gutiérrez-Cortines</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, before commenting on the characteristics of this project, I would like to express my thanks not just to Mrs Isler Béguin, but also to Mrs Lienemann, the other shadow rapporteurs and the officials and advisors who are working extremely hard to reach a consensus on this project. We have achieved extraordinary consensus in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety: everybody has introduced their points of view and, although there are apparently not many amendments, a new spirit has been introduced and the LIFE programme has been enriched, in cooperation with the Commission. How has it been enriched? In my opinion, we have introduced several new aspects. Firstly, this project has placed great emphasis on the management of natural resources. It is also of great educational importance in terms of teaching how to govern and manage the environment. Furthermore, we have insisted on an institutional presence in the form of the municipalities and regions as local authorities that have to re-evaluate their resources. In this regard, I would also like to stress another element: the introduction of landscapes deserving of respect that have not been integrated into the Natura 2000 list, such as certain rivers, but which may be important shared spaces. There is another innovation: the concept has been introduced, and the idea strengthened, of international projects and cross-border projects. Why? Because natural spaces are usually in border zones and in mountainous areas. Rivers are a clear case in point: the logical thing would be to create a LIFE for rivers one day, because rivers cross many countries. Furthermore, I must say something else: we have created a market spirit for Natura 2000. We believe that, in this case, we must imitate United States policy by creating banks for wetlands and banks for natural areas, so that the Member States can compensate proprietors, creating, shall we say, an area of exchange of ownership for the Natura 2000 zone. In this way, the companies and many others who also have to take initiatives on the ground may contribute economically to compensating, by means of the ‘polluter pays’ principle, for their passage through those protected territories. They may do so through active and positive policies for the conservation of the natural environment, funded by private bodies and by institutions. This is therefore not just another LIFE programme; it is a project based on a consensus which I believe has been guided by great common sense; I therefore congratulate everybody.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

