<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Frédérique Ries</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    (FR) Mr President, I should like, in my turn, to thank our rapporteur, Mrs Isler Béguin, for the quality of this collaborative work and her energetic commitment to this issue. During the June part-session, our Parliament, in its resolution on policy challenges and budgetary means of the enlarged Union, sent out a very clear political signal for protecting the planet, nature and biodiversity. It is essential to ensure the smooth operation of the Natura 2000 network, the core issue of this debate. Mrs Lienemann has just reminded us of this. The experts in the Commission have, moreover, calculated that Natura 2000 will need EUR 21 billion over seven years. We are aware that the Fund for Rural Development and the Structural Funds are not going to meet all of these needs. We therefore have to strengthen LIFE +, the specific financial instrument for the environment with which we have been equipped since 1992. I should therefore like to address two main criticisms to the Commission, which I share with our rapporteur. The first concerns the initial sum of EUR 300 million, which is, of course, hugely insufficient. Behind this battle of figures, it is Europe’s desire to take up major challenges such as air quality, water quality, spatial planning and sustainable waste management that is at stake here. The second criticism is as follows: I believe that the European Commission must not offload its responsibilities with regard to the environment. The strategy of integrating the environment in all of the Union’s policies has its limits, Commissioner. That is why the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe will support Amendments 42, 43 and 44. The European Parliament will always support you in opposing this kind of environmental Europe, an environmental Europe that in certain respects is in decline, and in all respects is optional, and which is imposed by certain Member States that appear to have chosen to withdraw into themselves.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

