<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Johannes Blokland</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, first of all, I should like to add my own thanks to the rapporteur for all the work she – together with the other Members – has done, but I should nevertheless like to make a few observations concerning the proposal on which we will be voting later. It would appear that some Members expect a great deal of support for nature policy from the European Union. I share this hope, for I too take the view that the European Union, by creating ecological networks, can make a positive contribution to our continent. We should not, however, pin all our faith on Europe, certainly where the funding of these Natura 2000 sites is concerned, for these sites are, after all, designated by the national authorities, assisted by European experts, and so it is acceptable that some of the funding for preserving them should come from the European budget. Ultimately, though, the primary responsibility for them lies with the Member States. In my view, it is very understandable that the funding should follow need, and various amendments underline this. We should only do and fund at European level what Member States cannot manage for themselves. We should not reverse the position by wanting to pay for everything and checking afterwards to see whether the Member States would like to make a contribution. I would therefore call for Member States to be given a greater role in funding and for them to be helped out only as and when EU funding is actually justified.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

