<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>John Bowis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the G8 leaders in Scotland are exercised about the sustainability of our world. If they travelled a little way to the Cairngorm Mountains and the Abernethy Forest Reserve, they would see one of Europe's Natura 2000 sites, covering 13 000 hectares of ancient Caledonian pinewood, moorland, lochs and mountains, which is the habitat for rare species such as the capercaillie and the black grouse. The former, which was previously thought to be the bird most likely to become extinct in the United Kingdom within 15 years, is now doubling its numbers. The reserve, with its osprey centre, attracts some 100 000 visitors a year and GBP 1.7 million a year and provides 87 jobs in a previously poor rural economy. We are seeing such results all over Europe, from Scotland to Spain to Germany. The Iberian lynx in Spain has been saved by Natura 2000. In Brandenburg, where the great bustard population had fallen from 4 000 in the 1930s to a few hundred, 9 500 hectares of monoculture have transformed its prospects and also brought economic benefit to an economically depressed area. We are talking about our European heritage, which we have a duty to protect. LIFE + is the new financial instrument that, with the Structural Funds and Fund for Rural Development, will enable Natura 2000 to continue to succeed. On 8 June, Parliament voted for ‘a significantly strengthened LIFE + programme’. I know that the budget will not be easy this year, but we pick up the proposal for a ring-fenced amount of EUR 21 billion over seven years in that resolution of 8 June. We suggest how LIFE + could be significantly strengthened. LIFE III, with its three components of nature, environment and third countries, has been a success in all respects, but particularly perhaps in the Natura 2000 sites of LIFE Nature. LIFE + will take this forward and this report will help that process. I hope that the Commission will respond supportively, constructively and imaginatively.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

