<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Anne Laperrouze</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the LIFE + environmental programme is crucial for supporting the implementation and development of environmental policy. It therefore has to act as a stimulus for implementation and as a catalyst for innovation and change, and thus enable action to be taken across the board at European level on the priority areas. Based on our successful experience with the current LIFE programme, LIFE + has to be the vehicle for assessing and monitoring conservation status, for drafting action plans on the recovery of species and for actions linked to the operation of the Natura 2000 European network. Demonstration projects concerning the establishment and protection of Natura 2000 should continue to be funded since they provide European added value. Environmental policy, however, amounts to more than just Natura 2000. That is why I am against Amendment 35, which proposes allocating 90% of the LIFE + programme to the funding of Natura 2000. LIFE + should actually adopt an approach that provides proportionate support for the four crucial subject areas in the Sixth Environmental Action Programme: climate change, the preservation of biodiversity, the environment and health, and the protection of natural resources. Finally, I should like to say that I share the rapporteur’s opinion that projects must continue to be selected at Community level to ensure that they provide European added value.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

