<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Françoise Grossetête</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I believe that words truly need to be turned into deeds, because delivering speeches about saving the planet and sustainable development is something that we do constantly in this House and elsewhere. Unfortunately, when the time comes for us to equip ourselves with the means to act, there is no one to be seen. Parliament is not in agreement with the European Commission, which has made choices with which we cannot concur. Commissioner, we understand that the funding for LIFE + must be integrated into the EAFRD and the ERDF. That is a question of transversality; we can accept it even if we might also regret it. However, we know how local elected representatives behave. When choices have to be made between different priorities, economic priorities and environmental priorities, it is well known that, unfortunately, it is the environment that suffers and is the victim of those choices. That is why Europe absolutely has to display authority in what it wants and why it is crucial to provide for specific funding, inter alia, in Natura 2000. Natura 2000 is an important policy that Europe wanted, that it has been difficult to persuade local elected representatives on the ground to accept, that has been difficult to understand and difficult to implement. Yet it is precisely now, when we need to manage the Natura 2000 sites, that the European Commission is taking a step backwards. That cannot be true. Today, the Commission no longer wishes to assist in funding the management of these sites. Some of them will not be covered by the EAFRD and the ERDF because they are neither farming areas nor woodland areas. What will we do in those cases? I will remind you that LIFE + is a financial instrument and that we would appear not to be giving ourselves the ability to negotiate most effectively with the Council. Commissioner, you ought to assist this Parliament in its financial negotiations with the Council. We need you. We are at the stage of first reading and we have to show our determination, our determination to protect the funding that is absolutely crucial to us. We have a very good compromise, and yet we have the feeling of being abandoned by the Commission. That really would be regrettable.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

