<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>María Isabel Salinas García</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, my group feels proud and happy today with the report that has been handled so well by the rapporteur, Mrs Isler Béguin, and also by everybody whose work has enriched it. Codesision is our strength, and this is inspired by the need to fulfil the environmental objectives that the European Union has always claimed are a priority. With regard to resources for the Natura 2000 network, this report is not asking for the impossible. The Commission is as aware as this Parliament of the difficulties caused by the financial perspective but, if you want me to tell the truth, I believe there are solutions that can be found through good will and decisiveness, as in this case. Perhaps an increase in funding for the network must also be accompanied by a better redistribution of the necessary resources. Of course, Commissioner, people should not be made to pay for the sins of others. By way of example: we cannot carry on calling on the Andalusian rural agents to tighten their belts further, both for the maintenance of the network on the basis of their legitimate responsibility as farmers, and for very specific and necessary actions, such as the preservation of the Iberian lynx. The Commission will remember better than I the excitement with which the Natura 2000 network was launched. Since then we have seen a hopeful process with legislation and programmes that make our environmental priorities a reality. All of this investment of resources and excitement cannot now come to nothing. LIFE + must be a powerful guarantee of the maintenance and strengthening of what we have created so far, also with regard to habitats and the variety of species we have. In this regard, and without calling into question the legitimacy of co-funding, nobody can deny that maintaining the network means — and this must be the case — high costs for certain Members and in particular for Spain. My country, together with Denmark, has the greatest amount of protected area and, furthermore, 29% of this area is in my community, Andalusia. Commissioner, sometimes we have to make efforts, take a position and be courageous. I would urge you to continue investing in the protection of the environment. It is worth it.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

