<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Bogusław Sonik</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the proposal to integrate existing environmental support programmes into a single financial instrument, LIFE +, is justified since it provides a guarantee that actions will not be duplicated. It is also a sensible idea to harmonise and simplify principles and procedures. The aim of the LIFE + programme is to safeguard funding for actions that will be ineligible for support under the EU’s other financial instruments. Given the current challenges we need to address in the field of environmental protection, this approach is entirely justified. The key problem we face with regard to the LIFE + programme, however, is fulfilling the tasks of co-financing, creating and implementing the Natura 2000 network. The priorities set for the LIFE + programme give due consideration to issues relating to the protection of nature and biodiversity, including the Natura 2000 network. At the same time, however, it is emphasised that co-financing for the Natura 2000 network is only to be provided on a complementary basis, which means that support is to be provided under the European Regional Development Fund and the Cohesion Fund. I am concerned at the fact that whilst the concept of the Natura 2000 network in Europe has evolved, this has not been backed up by an appropriate guarantee of funding for the creation and maintenance of this network. No clear details have been provided regarding the principles according to which funding can be obtained for protection measures for Natura 2000 sites between 2007 and 2013, and this will undoubtedly mean shortfalls in funding for the Natura 2000 network. It will then be impossible to implement many much-needed protection measures. For example, the majority of areas designated as Natura 2000 sites in Poland and other countries will not be covered by the funds indicated. Such areas include land that is part of national forests, or peat bogs, swamps, natural grasslands, dunes, moorlands and scrublands that are not used for agricultural purposes. In the context of the European Commission’s letter of 6 January 2005, which suggested that consideration be given to the possibility of extending the list of Natura 2000 sites in Poland, which could mean that up to 20% of the country would be covered by such sites, a guarantee of separate funding for the establishment of the Natura 2000 network has taken on even greater significance for Poland and other countries.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

