<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Evangelia Tzampazi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>20</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I would like to take my turn in congratulating the rapporteur, Mrs Béguin, and the shadow rapporteurs for the excellent work which they have presented. The need to finance LIFE + has a clear European dimension and value. The deterioration in the environment and ever increasing environmental issues, often of a cross-border nature, make it necessary to change the pan-European and global approach. In order to achieve this, it is necessary, together with investments in the environmental sector, for environmental actions under all programmes to be monitored both inside and outside the European Union, in order to ensure they function better and are more fully coordinated. The concept of protection of nature and biodiversity needs to be introduced as a basic feature in thematic priorities for the financing of the LIFE + programme, as a basic line of approach and actions in the new financing tool. This programme will need to be in a position to finance other actions, such as Natura 2000, which no other programme can cover. Thus there will also be a commitment from other financing instruments to meet such requirements. Commissioner, I believe that the increase which the European Parliament is calling for is the minimum required for the serious operation of LIFE +, which aims at basic aspects of environmental policy, which are information, awareness-raising among citizens and, most importantly, control of the application of this policy. (Applause)
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

