<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE +)</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0131/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-07-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>2</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marie Anne ISLER BÉGUIN</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Stavros Dimas</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>23</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    You are right that this EUR 21 billion comes from a study that we carried out at the Commission and it proved that we need at least EUR 6.1 billion yearly for these programmes. Of course, Mr Böge’s report had a reference to this. The amount was brought down by the amendment to EUR 7.35 billion for the seven-year period, so actually the money you spoke of before was not made available by this report. Again I have to repeat that, if we had this additional EUR 7.35 billion, we would ensure that it would be spent through the relevant funds for Natura 2000 and the other environment programmes. I must underline that, with the integrated approach, we are going to use the structural funds, the Cohesion Fund, and the Agricultural Fund in order to get the money we need. The guidelines that were voted on last week and two days ago will really help us in this respect. The Fund for Rural Development, and especially Axis 2, which deals with land management, will get at least 25 % of the rural funding of EUR 22.2 billion. This will also help greatly with programmes which the Member States have an interest in financing as they have a legal obligation to finance projects relating to Natura 2000.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

