<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jacques Barrot</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>2</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, on 14 July 2004, the Commission adopted a proposal for a regulation on the implementation of the deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation. You are going to debate this proposal in a few moments. I would like to thank the European Parliament for having supported the Galileo programme from the very start. I would particularly like to thank Mrs Barsi-Pataky for her excellent report and for also having supported, with a great deal of intelligence, the Galileo programme. We want to set up, at European level, the first worldwide satellite radionavigation system specifically for civilian purposes, a project that ties in with the European Union’s growth strategy as defined by the Lisbon European Council in 2000. It truly is the first great European industrial and space project. This is a technology that is developing and being applied at a tremendous rate. The capacity developed as part of this programme also means that the European Union will now be first in line to benefit from what is shaping up to be the great technological revolution, following the IT and telecommunications revolutions. The development phase of the programme is running smoothly. The first experimental satellite is expected to be launched in December 2005. This will be followed by the construction and launch of the first four satellites in the Galileo constellation. The current development phase will be followed by the deployment phase, and then by the commercial operating phase. The system will be brought into operation progressively between 2008 and 2010. The institutional framework retained for the deployment and commercial operating phases differs significantly from that of the development phase. During those two phases, the construction and then the management of the system will be entrusted to a private concession holder working under the control of the Supervisory Authority, a Community agency created by the Council regulation of 12 July 2004 to act as the licensing authority. The choice of a concession contract emerged as the most appropriate way to ensure the success of the programme in the framework of a Public Private Partnership. The proposal submitted to you aims to provide financing for the Community contribution to the Galileo programme during the deployment and commercial operating phases. It provides for a financial contribution from the European Community amounting to EUR 1 billion for the period of the new financial perspectives for 2007 - 2013. This amount will be transferred to the Supervisory Authority, which will make use of it in line with the provisions of the Council regulation of 12 July 2004. In addition, the proposal bases the programme on a specific legal instrument, consistent with the future European space programme and better able to respond to the need for good financial management. We will need to create a specific budget heading for the deployment and commercial operating phases of the programme, for three reasons. Firstly, the programme has now reached maturity. It has taken on a dimension that goes far beyond the sectoral policies pursued by the Commission. Secondly, the scale of the activities imposes requirements of transparency and budgetary rigour, as well as scrupulous supervision. Thirdly, the institutional and budgetary frameworks must be clear and consistent from the point of view of the concession holder for the system, on whom the Community will impose comparable requirements of transparency and consistency. I would stress the fact that the financing of the Galileo programme by the Community budget will be time limited. The commercial revenues generated by the operation of the system should ensure financial stability over time. I would remind you that many third countries  China, Israel, India and Ukraine  plan to participate in the programme. I would add that the Commission will ensure that the future concession contract provides for the repayment of public financial contributions if the profit earned by the concession holder exceeds a certain threshold over time. In conclusion, the proposal for a regulation put before you responds to the requirements arising from proper implementation of the deployment and commercial operating phases of the programme, to the requirement for good financial management and to the need for a grand European project that has reached an advanced stage of maturity. That, Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, is what I wanted to say to you. I very much hope that Parliament will follow Mrs Barsi-Pataky’s lead and give us all the support that this great project needs. It will indubitably bring the European Union many technological successes, and will make it possible to create many jobs connected with its various applications.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

