<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Etelka Barsi-Pataky</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>HU</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>3</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    The European Parliament has closely followed the development of the Galileo satellite radio navigation system from the outset, and through its involvement in the legislative process, Parliament has participated in bringing it about and shaping it. On the basis of the Galileo programme, a Community infrastructure will be created that truly deserves to be called a project ‘made in Europe’. This new global-scale infrastructure differs from its predecessors (the GPS and GLONASS systems) in that it is designed for civil and commercial (and not military) purposes, and as a result has become a joint project of all 25 Member States. The legislation before us concerns the financing of the deployment and initial operating phase in the period 2007-2013. We could, of course, have placed this regulation on the agenda of the plenary sitting, after agreement was reached on the Financial Perspective. I will give you the following reasons as to why we did not do this. Galileo is a PPP project involving both Community and private finance, and having a concession holder. Negotiations on the concession contract have begun, and so I felt that Parliament needed to make all the decisions that it wants taken into account in the negotiations. 1. It is important that Parliament should state, in its Opinion, that it supports the inclusion of a contribution of EUR 1 billion as a specific budget line in the Financial Perspective. 2. The Community will not only provide financial support for the project, but will also allow the concession holder to retain the revenues from the licences and other related rights, although the Community will retain ownership of these licences and rights. 3. Parliament recommends integration of the EGNOS programme, which ensures compatibility with the American GPS system and is a precursor of the Galileo programme (rather like introducing marketing). 4. Parliament expects the concession contract to contain provisions relating to the sharing of profits or revenues (from such a time as the project begins to generate profits or revenues, of course). 5. Since this is a PPP project, Parliament is willing to undertake financial guarantees and to share liabilities (but of course only when it is familiar with the concession contract and able to discuss this issue). 6. In the interests of the programme’s success, Parliament expects the implementers of the Galileo programme to keep to the deadlines. Parliament will check and monitor this constantly, in its annual budget debates. 7. Parliament supports the inclusion of research on GNSS satellite navigation in the 7th Framework Programme for Research and Technological Development, and at the same time recommends also including development of Galileo user applications in the Competitiveness and Innovation Framework Programme, specifically with the involvement of small and medium enterprises. 8. Parliament explicitly welcomes the PPP form of implementation. However, given that this is the first Community PPP project, Parliament recommends that it should have observer status on the Administrative Board of the Supervisory Authority, which will be on a one-off basis and will not include implementation tasks. This recommendation was also made by the previous Parliament, but I would like to point out to my fellow Members that the European Commission does not agree with it. The report was also discussed by the Committee on Budgets and the Committee on Transport and Tourism. Their opinions are an integral part of the report. I would like to point out that I will be tabling an oral amendment tomorrow on the basis of the interim agreement reached with the Committee on Budgets, and the ‘shadow rapporteurs’ are already aware of this. The amendment is technical in nature and concerns the withdrawal of the reference to 2004 as base year. I would like to express my gratitude for this excellent opportunity for conciliation and cooperation with the European Commission. To conclude, I would like to inform Parliament that the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy discussed the report several times, and adopted it unanimously at its June sitting.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

