<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Den Dover</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I served on the Committee on Budgets for many years as the United Kingdom Conservative spokesman. I recently moved to the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy and I have also served for many years on the Committee on Transport and Tourism. So this evening, although I have to apologise that Mr Lewandowski is unable to participate in the debate, I want to give this project our full backing. In the early years, we had reservations. We thought that the American system did not need a European alternative. However, the British and the Conservative Party have been brought round. I pay tribute to the rapporteur and the constructive attitude of the Commissioner on this subject, which is extremely important because of the added value that Europe is bringing to it. We have managed to achieve a great deal of progress to date and we need all 25 countries to pull together to achieve success in the future. I also admire the way that accountability is uppermost in this proposed regulation. Parliament and the Council need to be fully convinced at all stages that the proper steps are being taken and that accountability and transparency are the order of the day. I particularly welcome the involvement of the small and medium-sized enterprises, because they see this as a huge opportunity for them to increase their knowledge of technology in commercial concerns and to back up the very large operating body that will provide overall supervision. I also agree with the method by which they were appointed; it was slightly contentious at the time, but the results have been successful. I wish the project every success. I hope we will make sure that accountability is always the order of the day and that any financial guarantees that have to be given by the Council or Parliament are most carefully adhered to.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

