<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Nikolaos Vakalis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, I too wish to take my turn in welcoming the Commission proposal and Mrs Pataky's report. I am also optimistic that, in taking the Galileo programme to its next two phases, this unique European plan will be able to fulfil its full operational potential. Nonetheless, allow me a word of criticism. The Galileo joint undertaking, which will continue up to May 2006, made provision in its statutes for the facility for undertakings in the western sector to invest in its capital to the sum of EUR 5 million for large undertakings and EUR 250 000 for small and medium-sized undertakings. This was obviously to give the original political agreement between the two administrative members, the European Community and the European Space Agency some sort of corporate form; a corporate form which, supposedly, would be able to attract private capital. Unfortunately, not one single undertaking has subscribed to the capital of Galileo. However, this was only natural and only to be expected, given that there were no incentives for any such investment. It would therefore appear that we have a problem between public/private partnerships in theory and in practice. I call on Parliament to address this weakness and to control the Commission accordingly.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

