<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Norbert Glante</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I must, of course, extend particular thanks to Mrs Barsi-Pataky, with whom I have had a very good working relationship. I have been familiar with this subject area for a number years and it is one I have often had to handle. Mrs Barsi-Pataky has got to grips with it with astonishing speed and her cooperation with the shadow rapporteur has been very frank and transparent. The result of that has been a very solid vote in the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, with no votes against the report. What that also shows is that this House is still backing this project, albeit with misgivings here and there. Buying a project, a device, or a system is one thing, but it is just as important to develop one’s own systems and perfect one’s own technology. That I see as being the most important thing about this project. As has been said, the civil project in the European Union is meant to be set up as a public-private partnership, and the experts believe that it will create up to 150 000 jobs. For once, I believe them: their prognosis may well be accurate if we manage to get the project up and running relatively quickly, to find applications for it and produce this solution in Europe rather than importing it. If the forecasts are to be realistic, we simply have to succeed in this. Having a third of the EUR 3.5 billion subscribed from public funds and two-thirds derived from private sources gives Europe the chance of getting this project on its feet. I am optimistic about the prospects for the capital being put up once the projects and the concession contracts are in place. What is, of course, important is that we make the public funds available, and that is where I think we may still come a cropper, for the Council has not yet been able to agree on the Financial Perspective, one of the items in which is – of course – this EUR 1 billion for this project. We have already done our homework, but if the Council cannot manage to make these resources available and to secure funding by the end of the year, then it will be possible neither to get the concession contract signed nor to put any satellites into orbit. If nothing happens by December, then the frequencies are lost to us. We have, I think, had more than one moment of decision with regard to Galileo in the past; it is unfortunate that it was always the Council that put the brake on developments for a while. I hope we will make it this time. My group is giving this proposal its wholehearted backing and will be voting in favour of it. I am aware of Mrs Barsi-Pataky’s oral amendments; having conducted negotiations, I think we can go along with what she proposes. I do very much hope that the Council’s mind will not be as narrow as the checks on the shirt I am wearing today, and apologise for not having had the opportunity to change. I will look more respectable tomorrow.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

