<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jorgo Chatzimarkakis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, there is no doubting the fact that this Galileo project is of the utmost strategic importance and, as a public-private partnership of such great dimensions, unique in the EU. I wish to thank the rapporteur for her efforts, not only on my own part but also on behalf of my group. There is one point on which I would like to give her very strong backing, and that is her demand that the European Parliament, as the budgetary institution, should have a seat on the Administrative Board. Our institution’s budgetary role does indeed mean that we should be fully informed about the financial aspects of the Galileo project. There are very practical considerations behind this, for third countries have acquired smaller holdings – China in particular, which bought a share in our project on 30 October 2003. Having wanted to invest a total of 20 million in what is a 3.5 billion project, it gave notice of the intention to buy 5 million but paid only 2 million. This amount – 0.06%, a thousandth, of the total – puts China in full possession of the know-how that Galileo has to offer and gives it unrestricted access to it. I have conducted my own inquiries in Oberpfaffenhofen and seen how our know-how and intellectual property are not secure. I ask you, Commissioner, to do everything in your power to prevent our technology from being sold off to others. While we want third countries to be involved and markets to be conquered, we must also see to it that our intellectual property is protected. Let me particularly draw your attention to an amendment – No 22 – tabled by my colleague Mrs Hall, which is aimed at ensuring that, at a later date, when commercial operations begin, the European Union gets its contribution repaid, in other words, that there is a real distribution of profits. This debate is a significant one, and deserves to have more people observing it and listening to it. That is something we cannot change. I wish the rapporteur, Mrs Barsi-Pataky, every success in getting her report through.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

