<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Lydia Schenardi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, now that we are entering the development phase of this remarkable programme, as well as its deployment phase in which all of the space- and ground-based infrastructure will be created, it seems to us that two points are still vague. Via the Galileo programme, and in line with the Lisbon strategy, Europe is in the process of creating the first satellite positioning infrastructure on a global scale. This will bring us economic and strategic autonomy with respect to the US-owned GPS. This autonomy, however, seems to be incomplete, as it reveals a flaw in terms of political autonomy. Indeed, even though the intention is to secure personal data and to make the provision of information more reliable, this project, although it respects national sovereignty and strictly follows the subsidiarity principle, is purely for civilian purposes. It therefore leaves Europe dependent on the US military system for defence applications, and there is no real guarantee that the service will continue in the case of crises similar to the Gulf War, for example. Moreover, the risks involved in the transfer of technology via extra-European international cooperation do not seem to have been taken into account. Indeed, in the case of China, a financial partner in the Galileo programme, we cannot ignore the political origin and the potentially dangerous military interests, a field in which space technology can also be used by missiles. The same is true of commercial practices that may be reprehensible or else incompatible with European interests. In the circumstances, we call on the Commission to present a proposal that aims to safeguard the independence and room for manoeuvre of this programme in order to make Europe truly independent and to limit, or even to avoid completely, the risks of technology transfer in cases regarded as potentially dangerous.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

