<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Erna Hennicot-Schoepges</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, Commissioner, I would like to start by thanking our rapporteur, Mrs Barsi-Pataky, for having finalised her report in record time. When we consider how long it took the Council of Ministers to reach a decision –  almost a decade  – the European Parliament can be proud of having recognised the true importance of the Galileo project. European cooperation with regard to satellite radionavigation is an innovative project for the future in view of its public-private partnership, which should be able to create, we are told, 150 000 new jobs in the field of new technologies. This is a project for the future that will be able to prove that the countries of Europe are capable of stimulating the growth of new industries, of creating employment and of improving their citizens’ quality of life. The management methods of this project raise an important question and we would like Parliament to be informed of the initial results and of the operating methods in this matter. Commissioner, not everyone is certain that the management method chosen is the most appropriate one. With regard to the heel-dragging demonstrated by the Council of Transport Ministers, I would suggest that the Commission should now initiate projects to benefit from satellite navigation by drawing up alternative itineraries to sensitive points on our motorways, in order to improve the mobility of citizens and to make the most of this new facility as soon as it is available to us. The importance of this project for terrestrial research and observation must encourage us to fully exploit it and to encourage space research projects, whether as part of the seventh framework programme or at the EASA. To this end, an observer’s position for Parliament on the Administrative Board would enable us to be better informed and to coordinate activities in this area. Finally, one last question, Commissioner: do we have the human resources needed to implement this project? Are we sure that the 150 000 jobs will be filled by qualified persons; and what will our future needs be? How should young people prepare themselves so that they can have access to these jobs?
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

