<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Erik Meijer</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, these days, we can see on a screen where we are and in what direction we should be heading to get to our intended destination. It is to be hoped that this useful invention will be used to enhance our well-being rather than to wage war. Were such a system not yet in existence, it would have been a good idea to examine at European level whether something like this were technically feasible and could be put into production. There would then be a good reason for not farming this project out to accidental inventors and to entrepreneurs who hope to cash in on it, but instead making a joint effort and using Community funds in the process. It is now too late in the day for this. Europe can no longer be the first one. Such a system, originating from outside the EU, is already in operation and has conquered the European market. The Galileo plans add not much more than a competitive battle involving existing systems. Community funds are now mainly used to subsidise enterprises in the electronics and aviation industries. This will cost the European Union and its Member States increasingly more money to the detriment of more useful tasks. That is why there are those in my group who have never supported this project.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

