<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Christine De Veyrac</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Madam President, first of all I must congratulate Mrs Barsi-Pataky on her report and particularly on her proposal to provide the Galileo programme with an ambitious Community budget, following on from what Commissioner Barrot defended. I consider a package of EUR 1 billion for 2007-2013 to be justified for three main reasons. Firstly, the nature of what is at stake: this programme involves nothing less than ensuring Europe’s independence in space, while at the same time offering a host of new services to professionals and to private individuals. Secondly, with Galileo, the EU is fully committed to financing investments in the future. Thirdly, this sustained budgetary commitment is justified by the expected return on the investment: according to various estimates, Galileo should be exceptionally profitable, with an expected cost-benefit ratio of 4.6. For all these reasons, the EU must make an ambitious commitment to this programme, and I hope that the Council and particularly the UK Presidency, which talked a great deal a few months ago about the benefits of future spending, will go down this path. As it is very late, I will not tell you about all the assets, which are real and important, that the town of Toulouse can bring as the headquarters of the Galileo concession.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

