<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Deployment and commercial operating phases of the European programme of satellite radionavigation</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0212/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Etelka BARSI-PATAKY</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Patrick Louis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>16</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I am delighted that our committee is unanimous in its support for this project. It is vital for: - technological reasons: this is an innovative project and is an improvement on the guarantee of services provided by the US-owned GPS. - economic reasons: the sector needs to retain an appropriate level of activity. There will be a large number of direct or related jobs. - strategic reasons: Galileo improves the autonomy of our defence systems. - political reasons, because the project keeps the EU to its purpose. The EU has limited itself to creating the conditions for the emergence of the necessary new activities. The amendment requiring the concession holder to repay the investment illustrates this spirit. The autonomy of nations is strengthened. The PRS goes in this direction and enables each country to gain access to a technology that would be unattainable for them on their own. This cooperation also includes countries outside the EU. In conclusion, this project shows that true cooperation does not need a Constitution. This is a good project; let us hope that it will soon find its place in the budgetary plan.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

