<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jacques Barrot</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>2</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I will begin by warmly thanking your rapporteur, Mrs Jöns, and the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs for having carried out a high-quality piece of work and by also thanking the draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality, Mrs Figueiredo. The future PROGRESS programme will play a decisive role in the development of social Europe. In this context, it aims to bring together the four Community action programmes on which the implementation of the social policy agenda up to 2006 is based, as well as a series of budget headings concerning working conditions. The proposed approach will contribute to simplifying the instruments, both in legal terms and from the point of view of managing them, and to rationalising the budget structure. It will also enhance the clarity, visibility, coherence and consistency of the instruments and will prevent overlaps. The Commission has always been very keen to ensure that the revised text preserves this simplification and this rationalisation. That was the case with the initial proposal, and the majority of the amendments that Parliament has seen fit to suggest are also directed to this end. I would be pleased, Mr President, to listen to Parliament’s observations, standing in once again for Mr Spidla, who has been detained by the EU-China Summit.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

