<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Raymond Langendries</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I would like first of all to address Mrs Jöns in order to congratulate her on her excellent report on PROGRESS. I am equally delighted by the quality of the debates we have had in committee and by the very interesting compromise amendments, of which I would specifically like to point out the following. I believe that interesting amendments have been made to the Commission’s text, particularly with regard to Parliament’s role itself. It should be recognised, Commissioner, that the Commission’s initial text treated us somewhat as the poor relation when it came to the evaluations of a programme actually extending over seven years (2007-2013). I think it is worth remembering what the Commission was proposing concerning the role of Parliament, namely the simple forwarding to Parliament of an ex post evaluation focused on the entire programme, an evaluation drafted by the Commission one year after the programme’s conclusion. I believe that the proposals being submitted by the Commission respond to the need for Parliament to intervene directly and throughout the entire seven-year period covered by such an important programme. They are also particularly acceptable to the Commission. Secondly, through the use of compromise amendments, Mrs Jöns has drawn attention to the particularly important role of non-governmental organisations and of social organisations. Everyone will be in agreement in recognising that, from a national and transnational perspective, these organisations play a particularly important role in the framework of the specialised networks belonging to them at EU level. It is therefore only natural that they should participate in devising, implementing and monitoring the programme. It is equally clear that promoting the direct exchange of experiences can ensure a greater understanding of the individual nature of events taking place in different countries; it is, moreover, only in this way that exchanges on strategies, good practices and innovative strategic approaches will bear fruit and endow the evaluations with the quality scientific approach they require. I will say one final word on financial and budgetary matters since they remain the core issue. It should be pointed out that the sum of EUR 628 million, proposed by the Commission, falls well short of the amount recommended in the Böge report on the financial and budgetary package for 2007-2013. I would like in particular to emphasise that the success of the PROGRESS programme essentially depends on the amount awarded to it, and it is clear that the amount proposed by the Commission is by no means acceptable.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

