<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jan Andersson</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SV</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I too wish to begin by thanking the rapporteur for what is, typically, an extremely good report. We have taken a positive view of this proposal concerning PROGRESS and the amalgamation of the previous four programmes. This may mean better coordination, less overlap and more efficient use of expenditure. Amalgamation is therefore to be welcomed. The programme has a role to play in the Lisbon strategy that is, of course, not only about competitiveness but also about a social Europe and a less stratified society. It is a fact that unemployment is too high at present. Social protection systems and social integration do not operate in ways that are entirely satisfactory. Gender equality is not always to be seen, and there is still discrimination. This programme is therefore extremely important. I wish to comment on a number of aspects also addressed by the rapporteur. Firstly, the pooling of experience, including transnational experience. It is incredibly important to make the most of the programme’s innovative character, for, at national level, we conduct labour market policies. These programmes must be creative and innovative and be extended across national borders so that everyone might benefit from what is being done through different projects. Secondly, gender equality should not just be applied specifically in one area. Instead, it must permeate all parts of the programmes and of PROGRESS. I also wish to emphasise the accessibility aspects. Disabled people are now excluded from the labour market to a greater extent and have more difficulty being integrated into society. It is therefore important for the accessibility aspects, broadly understood, to be integrated into, and taken account of in, all parts of the programme so that disabled people can participate in the labour market. The same applies to the social integration of people who come from other parts of the world and who are not part of the labour market. I myself have experience of working in Sweden on the Swedish programme. I wish to emphasise what the rapporteur too mentioned, namely that both sides of industry, as well as non-governmental organisations, must be involved in the whole of the work, designing, implementing and supervising the programmes. They will be a major resource in the work being done firmly to establish these programmes at national and regional levels. The financial aspects have already been touched upon. The Commission’s proposal would make far too few resources available and is too old-fashioned. Social Europe is an area on which we must concentrate when we create the long-term budget. That is why the proposal by the committee responsible, put forward here in Parliament and recommending more resources, is to be preferred. Now, the subject of a social Europe has been taken up by the British Presidency. In this context, the need for a properly resourced PROGRESS programme should also be evaluated.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

