<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Luigi Cocilovo</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would also like to take this opportunity to thank the rapporteur for the excellent job she has done, as well as all the groups and my colleagues in the committee, who have helped, through the amendments they have tabled, to improve an initiative that we are very pleased with. In my view, the greatest merit of the PROGRESS programme as part of simplification and rationalisation efforts is the renewal of a commitment to priorities that are crucial for achieving the Lisbon Strategy’s objectives, by providing instruments that are appropriate, albeit not fully balanced. When we talk of investment in aspects such as human resources, training, employment services, efforts to achieve higher employment rates, the promotion of crucial qualitative and quantitative employment levels and at the same time an agenda for social cohesion, we have in mind objectives that should not be seen solely as a compensatory or offsetting appendage to a Lisbon Strategy focused exclusively on the economic sphere, but that form an integral part of it. For these very reasons, I believe that it is fundamentally important to propose and plan a reinforcement of the financial framework, but we also place considerable emphasis on the success of this proposal, including the section relating to an increase in the cofinancing ceilings, which are essential in promoting a decisive and determining aspect of the programme: an upgraded role for partnership. If the social dimension does not play a leading and decisive role in planning and implementation, commitment from the institutions alone will probably fall short of the objectives. Other issues have already been dealt with by other Members, and so I have dwelt on just a few points that, in my view, are crucial for the success of an option that is decisive in the relaunch of European strategies for development and the system’s competitiveness.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

