<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Bairbre de Brún</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    (The speaker spoke Irish) Mr President, I welcome the report by Mrs Jöns and thank her for her work. In particular I welcome the emphasis placed on social inclusion, gender mainstreaming, people with disabilities and the role of the NGO sector in this programme. I also want to throw my support behind calls for an increase in the financial aid proposed and for a co-financing rate of 90%, rather than 80%, in relation to the role of NGOs and social partners. Let us be clear: the current economic strategies are driving more and more people into poverty within the European Union, and our hope is that PROGRESS can help play an important role in the fight against social exclusion. The strengthening of gender equality should be supported wholeheartedly by this Parliament, especially those elements which emphasise actions promoting gender equality that aim to combat discrimination and access to employment, career development, pay and training, and that fight the causes of poverty and social exclusion. This is a real and immediate issue for women in particular. In Ireland, for example, the gender pay gap has substantially increased for women and the gap between men's and women's pay in Ireland is among the largest of any EU Member State. Irish women are paid 17% less for the same work as Irish men and, according to a recent report by the Central Statistics Office, one-parent families are three and a half times more likely to experience poverty. If we want to see fundamental change within society and bring in this fundamental change in mindsets and conditions, we must support this programme and this report. I will be voting for this. (The speaker spoke Irish)
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

