<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Derek Roland Clark</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, employment and social solidarity go together. The greatest social benefit, the greatest solidarity, is for people to have jobs. However, fuller employment will not come about through bureaucratic plans and schemes such as Lisbon, which the rapporteur and others seem to think will help and which is now discredited, surely: halfway through its time span and less than half implemented. Employment is encouraged by removing restraints and scrapping regulations. I point out again in this House that those countries that have not adopted the euro have the lowest levels of unemployment. However, it goes deeper. In the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs in July, David Blunkett, the United Kingdom Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, said that we must not work against Member States, that different countries have different solutions and that defining best practice is the first step. Therefore, we must observe what others do and learn from each other, taking and adapting from each other what suits best. We must not conjure up new projects with ever increasing budgets. The rapporteur rightly says that red tape must be cut through but is sceptical about the European Union's ability to do so. Likewise, David Blunkett said that many regulations were being passed which were impossible to implement. Just so: the first measure to be discarded is this well-meaning but artificial attempt to create social solidarity. I voted against it in committee and I ask this House to do the same.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

