<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Richard Howitt</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I warmly support my good friend and colleague, our rapporteur, Mrs Jöns, in her work to strengthen this funding proposal. It underpins our European work on the critical issues of discrimination and social exclusion that continue to hold back so many people in our societies. If the Lisbon Strategy is to mean more than just words, Parliament is right to expect a significant increase in funding for this area. If politicians in Brussels are genuinely worried about disengagement and alienation, as reflected by the votes on the Constitutional Treaty and in other ways, it is right for us to insist that the Commission should strengthen, not weaken, the role of both social partners and of non-governmental organisations in this programme. I strongly support combating all forms of discrimination. As many colleagues are aware, I have a specific interest in working with the disability movement. I would like to remind Parliament and Commission that this is the programme which provides the core funding to enable disabled people, and indeed other groups that are discriminated against, to meet and to represent themselves at European level. If we fail to allow this, we exclude the most disadvantaged people from our work in the European Union. I remember very well the budget crisis back in 1998, when the funding for such NGOs was called into question in a wholly unjustifiable manner. It was resolved at political level by the Member States, on the clear understanding that the work of these organisations on combating discrimination is vital in pushing forward the EU agenda. Let that be remembered today. I want to reiterate that it is important for these networks to be independent and capable of representing the concerns of their members. The Commission too often sees them as agencies for promoting and implementing its work. No, they must represent the views and experiences of disadvantaged people themselves. I believe in gender mainstreaming, but it should apply to disabled people too, with disabled, not able-bodied, people representing them. Our amendments, which provide for adaptations, accommodations and accessibility and include publicity, are absolutely crucial in ensuring that disabled people are involved. Finally I want to express support for the small disability organisations for blind and people, or people with intellectual disabilities. They too have a right to meet at European level and we should not forget them and try and lump people together in large groups. There is room for all organisations, large and small.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

