<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Siiri Oviir</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ET</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, esteemed colleagues. Solidarity is one of the most fundamental principles of European integration. In this regard, the neighbouring Scandinavian countries serve as a good model for my home country Estonia. Finland, Sweden and Denmark have some of the highest human development indicators in the world. At the same time, they occupy positions at the peak of economic competitiveness. In order to achieve the Lisbon development objectives and find an appropriate social model to meet the challenges the European Union will face in the future, we should certainly keep their valuable experiences in mind. The decision under discussion, which would establish a programme for employment and social solidarity in the Union, is a substantial step towards the creation of a more uniformly developed social environment in Europe. In connection with this, I would like to emphasise that non-governmental organisations can be effective partners to national governments, and as motors of civil society, these are also responsive social indicators. In order to increase and improve the progress of this programme, and also its implementation, I, as one of the co-rapporteurs, suggested that the rate of cofinancing should be raised to 90% of the total expenses of NGOs. This is a significant measure which will especially help the 10 countries that have most recently joined the European Union to catch up more quickly with the others. A prosperous Europe is a goal towards which we all strive. Today, the new Member States in particular require support in order to work as equals with the other Members, without eating into the other countries’ budgets. We must ensure the stability of democratic processes, and this is directly connected with social stability. The measure of raising cofinancing is also important because both the associated candidate countries of the European Union and the western Balkan states included in the process can participate in the programme. In conclusion, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs Jöns, for her expert work, and also you, my good colleagues, for your attention. Thank you.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

