<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Κyriacos Τriantaphyllides</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, we agree with Mrs Jöns’ report – and I wish to congratulate her – because we believe that safeguarding high levels of social protection and participation of the workers, at a time when the rules of the market and of profit prevail, is our urgent duty. We consider that all workers have the right to work and live in an environment of equality and social cohesion and therefore stress, among other things, that immigrants are not second-class workers or citizens. The enjoyment of equal rights and equal opportunities and their social protection and integration are non-negotiable. The same also applies to people with disabilities, who must also have access to work and whose social integration must be promoted and confirmed. The European Parliament can and must have a fundamental role in the monitoring and application of the PROGRESS programme. The citizens of the Union and every person must have the right of participation and of equal opportunity in the society in which they live and this can only be achieved when profit policies do not steal a march on social policies. We consider that the PROGRESS programme, with the improvements approved by the relevant committees, including the increase in funding, can at least play a role in safeguarding a certain level of social cohesion by giving work to those who have been socially unprotected in the past and, ultimately, by achieving social protection for all workers without cutting corners and without discrimination.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

