<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Anna Záborská</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>16</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the European PROGRESS programme will henceforth encompass the former European Gender Equality programme in the form of a section on equal treatment of men and women. I congratulate Mrs Jöns on her report. Without doubt, the Lisbon challenges impose the need for an agenda to achieve a rationalised social policy in terms of spending and monitoring. Yet, will the new European social policy enable women to gain full recognition for all the functions they perform? Will the value of their work be better recognised by integrating the policy of equality into that of employment? Etymologists set us thinking. The origin of the word economy, oikos , house, and nomos , rule, explains that economy is a desire to run a house efficiently. In all domestic or professional spheres, in the market or non-market sector, women know how to make use of scarce resources and turn them into something else. They know how to satisfy everyone’s needs and desires and to redistribute the outcome of what they produce. Around 30% of women’s economic output is not even accounted for. That earned the US economist, Gari Becker, a Nobel Prize. In my country, behind the Iron Curtain, women did not expect to receive a pay slip, nor unemployment benefit to support those close to them. They only worked to ensure their own survival and that of their family. Lisbon wishes to fight against impoverishment in Europe and for greater social justice. The clearly identified commercial criteria are widely debated here. Let us make no mistake, a significant effort remains to be made to identify the work of women, the driving force behind the networks of solidarity, including the economic indicators of our nations’ accounts. Solidarity in the economy calls on us to conduct politics in a different way and to establish relations between human beings based on public-spirited and socially aware behaviour that respects everyone’s differences.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

