<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> PROGRESS</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0199/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-06</DATE>
    <ITEM>15</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Karin JÖNS</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Rodi Κratsa-Τsagaropoulou</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>17</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the debate on PROGRESS, the new Community programme, is being held at a very important time. Firstly, the recently enlarged European Union has as its basic aspiration the difficult objective of economic and social cohesion in today's environment of low development levels and regional and social inequalities. Secondly, the European Union is preparing to enlarge towards south-east Europe and to start accession negotiations with Turkey, a large country with serious problems in all sectors. These developments relate directly to our political plans and to our financial perspectives. Thirdly, the social problems of European citizens which the PROGRESS programme is designed to combat lie at the heart of speculation about the effectiveness of our social model and the credibility and viability of the European Union. For these reasons, we expect a great deal of the PROGRESS programme in terms of its structure, its collective and coordinating character, its adequate funding, the potential to mobilise social and economic agencies and, more specifically, to give numerous agencies at national and regional level the chance to participate, because we must not forget that our administration to date is making European citizens say that we are supporting and cooperating with the professionals of the European programmes and not the real, basic protagonists. I should like in particular to highlight the need to integrate the gender factor into all sectors in which action is taken, in all evaluations and reviews, both interim and annual, of the PROGRESS programme, as the Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality emphasises in its opinion. We have a great deal of experience in the European Union today from the application of equality programmes at Community and national level. At the same time, women have a great many problems in connection with discrimination, unemployment, poverty and exclusion. We therefore need to work in the new framework which we have before us, in the PROGRESS programme, with political perspicacity and appropriate administrative mechanisms, in order to respond to the aspirations of women and resolve their problems.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

