<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Roberta Angelilli</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>UEN</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, this proposal for a recommendation undoubtedly represents an advance for the protection of minors and human dignity, particularly in terms of safer Internet browsing for children and also guaranteeing a right of reply in relation to inaccurate information disseminated through any type of medium. It is a pity, though, that the legal basis chosen for this recommendation should be Article 157 of the Treaty, which is intended to ensure the competitiveness of European industry, instead of the more appropriate Article 153 on the protection of consumer interests. It is also a pity that the legal form chosen should have been a recommendation that, as is well known, has no legally binding force. In spite of this, it is very important that this report focuses on strengthening the protection of minors, through education programmes on information media designed to also enable adults, parents, teachers and trainers to teach minors to make proper use of the information media, especially the Internet. Also extremely important is the commitment to fight the danger of child pornography, especially on the Internet, which is to be combated through informative and preventative advertising campaigns. As the rapporteur also stated, the Internet is a formidable tool for communication with the entire world, but it should be safe and trustworthy. For this reason it is important for the Commission to agree to set up a European toll-free number to supply information on existing filtering systems that can also simplify the submission of complaints to the relevant authorities and the reporting of dangerous sites. In addition, it could be a good idea to promote the adoption of a seal of quality for providers, so that users can identify whether or not a particular provider is regulated by a code of conduct. Finally, another important point is the possibility of creating filters that will prevent at source the computer transmission of child pornography and other material that constitutes an assault on human dignity. To conclude, I would like to thank the rapporteur and all the Members who have worked together to draft this text.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

