<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Vasco Graça Moura</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, Mrs de Sarnez’s outstanding report has brought Parliament face to face with a problem which is a long way from being resolved and which will take a long time to be resolved to a satisfactory degree, although the adoption of the proposed recommendation could prove a highly significant step in the right direction in this area. The protection of minors and human dignity is an issue that raises fresh problems on a daily basis and increasingly requires both firm action and appropriate teaching in conjunction with a broad spectrum of the people directly involved in the issue. Specific responsibilities must be taken on, good practice must be exchanged and close cooperation must be established between all of the stakeholders involved. Yet we must ask ourselves if this enough. Can we expect, for example, that the mechanisms of self-regulation and co-regulation will prove a genuinely satisfactory solution to the problem? What is needed is a sea change of mentality in terms of competitiveness and the production of content, with a view to rejecting the illegal and harmful products that are increasingly invading all audiovisual areas and what are referred to as online services. This issue covers areas as diverse as the protection of human rights, the development of personality, family and school education, and the construction of citizenship; in other words, it goes to the heart of democracy and freedom. Consequently, the substance of the recommendation before us should, at various levels and from a variety of perspectives, involve the European and national authorities, the audiovisual industry, and Internet providers and users, along with, on a broader level, authority figures who deal most directly with minors, such as parents, educators and teachers. It is also essential, however, that technology develops and improves so that the measures included in the recommendation can be made genuinely effective: from signalling systems to filtering, from classification to clear guidance on whether a particular practice is legal or otherwise. Direct contact with the minors themselves; they must be in a position to activate protection mechanisms; child protection agencies and similar associations must become involved; and academic training and learning that takes account of these considerations must be provided. Tricky and complex self-regulation procedures should also be promoted, whereby institutions and businesses foster self-evaluation and civic awareness. This, for me, is the most difficult aspect, because it will entail a radical change of mindset and behaviour in an era of fierce competitiveness and thirst for profit. Changes must also be made to national laws whereby all of these factors can be brought together and can run smoothly, in such a way that we can achieve at least some of the objectives. Let us hope that this becomes a reality in the not too distant future. I therefore feel, Mr President, that we should congratulate Mrs de Sarnez and vote in favour of the report before us.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

