<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Christa Prets</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the Lisbon Strategy resulted in the introduction of the European Union’s e -Europe Action Plan, the aim of which is to speed up the achievement of the new-economy objectives, particularly those involving the Internet, by 2010. The Action Plan also includes measures to be taken by Member States with a view to achieving Internet security. Internet security means not only the use of smart cards and virus protection, but also protection from harmful and illegal content. I would therefore ask the Commission to strengthen this aspect in future e -Europe action plans, and at all events to include specific measures. In Austria, for example, 80% of young people use the Internet and, of these, 50% go on-line nearly every day. It has been established that there are currently around 260 million pages with pornographic content circulating on the Internet. The trade in sex, particularly child pornography, on the Internet is booming, and so Parliament’s call for the protection of minors cannot be repeated too often. We must also take care that we do not, in our pursuit of increased competitiveness, overstep the bounds of human dignity. Measures must be demanded and implemented at political, entrepreneurial and educational level. Parents should also be involved. The objective must be to achieve a uniform level of protection of minors and human dignity with a view to improving the competitiveness of audiovisual, information and on-line services in the long term. Filter systems must become more widespread. It should not be possible in future for minors to gain access to websites with content involving, for example, child pornography or racist or violent material. Information and awareness-raising campaigns, continuing education of teachers and instructors, and also the introduction of a quality label for providers subscribing to a certain code of conduct, are urgently required. Although voluntary self-regulation is a good thing, it does not offer adequate protection of children in the face of the proliferation of harmful content. Equally important is the requirement for the right of reply, which should also apply to all new electronic communications media – audiovisual media and on-line services, in other words – but must of course also take into account freedom of expression and the specific nature of the service concerned. It is regrettable that this is only a recommendation and that we have to content ourselves with making demands of the Member States. I should like, instead, to see regular monitoring that would enable us to exert public pressure and thereby separate the good from the even better.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

