<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Alfonso Andria</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Mrs Reding, ladies and gentlemen, I would like first of all to congratulate my colleague Ms De Sarnez for the effective and innovative approach she has taken to a subject with extremely delicate ramifications. The huge growth in the reach of the Internet has recently drawn the institutions’ attention to the need to safeguard the rights of minors, which should be protected especially carefully in so far as they are among the main possible users of the web. I am well aware of how difficult it is to find the right balance between two requirements: firstly, that of ensuring that minors can benefit from the wealth of information that the web can provide, and secondly, the duty to prevent the danger that the Internet might become a tool for deviancy and miseducation for minors. For this reason, the combating of the circulation of content that is harmful to human dignity and the civil and cultural development of minors is of fundamental importance. On the other hand, it is also vital not to slow down but in fact to speed up the process of development of the sector, by promoting new audiovisual media and information services, but in an environment of calm and trust. In fact, if effective tools to protect the public interest are not rapidly identified and used, these new media and services may not be able to achieve their full potential from the social, cultural and economic viewpoints. I agree with the rapporteur when she states that, in order to ensure the protection of minors in the utilisation of new information technologies, various actions must be taken simultaneously at three levels of responsibility: politicians, the industry itself and the educational system and parents. I therefore support the proposals she has made, particularly those aimed at implementing information campaigns for citizens to alert public opinion to the dangers posed by an inappropriate use of the Internet, the promotion of training for the trainers, through initiatives specifically aimed at teachers and educators on the risks of the Internet for minors, and the distribution of information packs to pupils and parents. Finally, I urge the European Commission to promote the setting up of a single toll-free telephone number for the whole of the EU, to receive information and complaints about harmful sites. This would make it easy to compile a list of such web domains, partly with the aim of possible legal action against the authors. It would also make it possible to give very useful data and news to the Member States that currently do not have such a reporting service, which fits in well within the strategy of protecting minors.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

