<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Michael Cramer</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, like almost everything else in life, the Internet has its good and bad sides, not only for minors, but also for adults. I speak from experience, for there is much to be found there that bothers me, too, even though I am not a minor. The problem facing us consists in striking a balance between freedom of information, which we all agree is a good thing, and the protection of minors. We must not, however, go too far in doing this. In the United States, there were plans to apply certain filters, but these blocked all the information on breast cancer, for example, because the word ‘breast’ was banned as pornographic and all the information on it was filtered out. We should make these risks known: this kind of scenario is unacceptable. Our vision is one of both children and adults being able to handle the media in an independent and self-confident manner. In order to achieve this, we need websites suitable for children – because, of course, minors require particular protection – on which children can practise constructive behaviour from an early age, that is to say the ability to recognise positive and exclude negative Internet content. Of course, we also need effective filter systems of the kind that do not overshoot the mark. We need systems to filter out pornography, and also racist and violent content; I should like to see these particular filters for adults, too. We need continuing education for teachers and instructors in schools and educational establishments so that they, too, are able to pass on to children the information they require. In addition, we need to introduce a quality label so that we can advertise a good example and thereby subsequently outlaw bad examples. We intend to table an amendment to ensure that there are not too many strict filters, but that these are nevertheless effective and capable of protecting our children.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

