<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Manolis Mavrommatis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, I should like to start by congratulating the rapporteur on the fulsomeness of her work and my honourable friends for their speeches on the proposal for a recommendation by the European Parliament and the Council on the protection of minors and human dignity and the right of reply in relation to the competitiveness of the European audiovisual and information services industry being proposed through the De Sarnez report. There are a great many findings, but the main fundamental conclusion which led to this report is still the European Union's inability to monitor urgently and effectively the application of its individual directives. We conclude from the amendments which we had the opportunity of tabling and voting for that, achieving the objectives in the area of the media, led by television without frontiers and the new technologies in the information sectors, such as the Internet, depends on cooperation between politicians, the audiovisual industry and parents, responsibilities which touch on the quality of the product offered, of training programmes for young people, of the protection of dignity and of the right of reply when morals are offended and citizens' personal data are divulged. To close, I recommend the direct and uniform application in the Member States of terrestrial digital television broadcasting, which will allow parents to control programmes, especially the programmes to which millions of European citizens, including minors, have access as a result of rapid technological progress and, finally, the production of information broadcasts with a strategy against acts of violence against minors and support for victims in the form of psychological, moral and material assistance.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

