<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Nikolaos Sifunakis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the development of new technologies in the information sector and the spread of the use of the Internet have brought very important benefits in the dissemination of knowledge and information and have facilitated communication between people to a very great extent. However, technology often also has negative results when it is used for the wrong purposes, especially when there is no proper legislative framework to regulate its use. Thus today there are millions of pages of pornography on the Internet and, as our rapporteur Mrs De Sarnez noted earlier, young people spend more time on the Internet than in front of the television. Consequently, it is the duty of legislators to ensure that this tool of the freedom of expression does not become a dangerous medium for minors. This recommendation has precisely that objective. It proposes innovative and specific measures to control Internet sites with illegal and harmful content. I believe that these measures respond to a considerable degree to citizens' concerns. We need to congratulate – and I for my part congratulate – Mrs De Sarnez, with whom we had the opportunity to hold numerous discussions via our committee and, of course, the work carried out by all the members of the Committee on Culture and Education and all the contributions on this issue are now here before the House ready to be voted on. This is a text which is a decided improvement on the Commission's initial text. Finally, as far as the right of reply is concerned, there need to be common principles in all the Member States so that the protection of people's dignity, honour and reputation can be safeguarded effectively. If we continue to have different conditions for exercising the right of reply in the various Member States, there is a danger that people facing inaccurate accusations with ulterior motives will be unable to make appropriate use of this right.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

