<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ljudmila Novak</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I welcome the report and I am in favour of the protection of young people who are exposed to dangers in the media and in particular on the Internet which their parents and teachers may not be fully aware of. There is, therefore, an urgent need to inform and educate parents, teachers and all of society, and to alert them to these modern-day dangers. However, the kind of adult supervision that can prevent all dangers does not exist. Violence in society and violence among young people is growing and various sections of the media and electronic games must also bear some responsibility for this as it is via these very means that young people learn the skills of violent behaviour, identify with negative role models in such games and thus become immune to the suffering of others, or they may even enjoy such suffering, regarding it as something normal. At a time when we are fighting terrorism in every corner of the world, such images of violence are helping to support and strengthen it here. Since the most important thing in the world of business is generally profit alone, countries must make use of regulations and laws to impose restrictions and also make sure that such restrictions are respected and that appropriate measures are taken when infringements occur. On the other hand, all those who make their living from the media or from young people must take responsibility for their actions. Industries must provide a description of the contents of what they propose to sell, which will facilitate the classification of web pages and make it possible to formulate abbreviations and advisory messages and to provide appropriate filtering. I wonder whether it is only violent contents that actually bring profits when there are so many important things in life that could be communicated to young people in an interesting and informative way, and which at the same time could contribute to a better society and to better relations between people.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

