<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Aloyzas Sakalas</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>LT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I welcome the speaker with such a carefully prepared document, and I believe the document will be instrumental in helping us protect our children from harmful content disseminated through the mass media, including the Internet. I would like to point out that the Internet, and the Internet cafes in particular, are the least controlled of all information media. According to a Gallup survey, as many as 63% of Lithuanian children browse the Internet, of whom as many as 33% are 7–10 years old, and only half of the parents show any interest in how their children do that. As many as 90% of those interviewed believe that the most harmful content on the Internet is pornography, whereas 54% of the respondents pointed to violence-related information. 36% of the respondents ascribe such content to paedophilia and 13% to religious sects. I fully support the proposals and amendments presented in the document. The Lithuanian authorities have been quite successful in managing locally produced Internet sites, and we do not have any problems in this respect. However, we face serious problems with content from abroad, since it is virtually outside of any control. Therefore, I believe that following the adoption of this recommendation the Commission should prepare an appropriate directive. Children’s psyches should be protected from damage by any sort of content, and that is a task and responsibility for all of us, including the Commission.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

