<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Luis Herrero-Tejedor</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>14</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Thank you, Mr President. Please believe me, Mrs De Sarnez, when I say that your report is really very good. We should guard against complacency, however, and always aim high, so I would venture to point out three issues in relation to which I believe we could have gone a little further. The content of the report deals with subjects that differ so much from each other that it is difficult to find a common denominator. It refers to the protection of minors on the Internet but also to the right of reply and discrimination. I believe, and I am addressing this to you, Mrs Reding, that we should make it possible for each of these issues to be the subject of a specific recommendation. Secondly, an express reference is required to the necessary respect for freedom of expression, because the protection of minors that we have laid out in this recommendation could lead to situations in which the restrictions extend to adults, and that would be a violation of Article 10 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. In this regard I agree with what Mr Sifunakis has said. The United States Supreme Court rejected the Communications Decency Act for a similar reason and because no right is without limits. I do not believe that we should make the same mistake and we should be cautious. Thirdly and finally, I would like to point out that I believe the scope of this recommendation has been unnecessarily restricted, because we have talked a lot about minors as viewers of unwanted audiovisual content, but we have not focussed on minors as passive subjects. When we refer to paedophilia, we forget that it is children, minors, who are the object of this type of illicit information and I believe this report should make some reference to that point.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

