<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Competitiveness of audiovisual and information services: protection of minors and human dignity</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0244/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Marielle DE SARNEZ</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Laima Liucija Andrikienė</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>LT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Today we are considering a truly important issue that concerns every family and every one of us: the protection of minors, our children and grandchildren, from harmful pornographic, violent and drug-related Internet material. This is undoubtedly a most important task, requiring immediate measures. This is also an international problem going far beyond the boundaries of the European Union, thus calling for the efforts of the entire international community. The most recent statistics suggests that children spend more time browsing the Internet than watching TV. In this respect it is necessary to point out that there are about 260 million pornographic sites, in addition to many others teaching how to commit crimes or produce drugs. In Lithuania we have noticed that websites promoting the use of drugs and registered on European servers are immediately transferred to America as soon as any threat arises, and this makes our task even more difficult. Our experience has shown that in an attempt to protect under-age persons from harmful Internet content the self-regulation of Internet service providers is no longer an adequate measure. In so far as the technical means are available, it is necessary to legally bind Internet service providers to install filters that screen harmful sites and to oblige them to block such sites on the server. I am convinced that it is absolutely necessary to harmonise the laws of the European Union Member States on the protection of under-aged persons from the harmful impact of the Internet. I welcome the proposal to arrange courses in schools for children and parents on the possible dangers created by the Internet and the means of protection against such dangers, as well as the proposal to open free telephone lines for people to call and report on Internet sites harmful for children. Another justifiable proposal is the idea to create a domain specifically designed for children and to have the content of the sites registered therein regularly scrutinised by an independent authority. In conclusion, I would like to express my strong confidence that in order to avoid even more serious problems in the future we should declare, in the entire European Union, zero tolerance of any harmful Internet material promoting pornography, violence or drug addiction, especially material targeting children and under-aged persons.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

