<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Patrizia Toia</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the infants and children of Europe need and are entitled to benefit from special medicines, that is, medicines that are expressly designed and made for this type of patient. From this point of view, we are all aware that the current situation in Europe is testimony to a very inferior level of development. This positive and important regulation thus needs to be adopted urgently. It is based on certain vital points, which I will go over briefly. The creation of the Paediatric Committee is of great importance, as is its composition: it must be made up of high-level, authoritative and independent figures, in view of the extremely delicate tasks for which they will be responsible. They will have to assess the paediatric investigation plans, approve them and evaluate their results. The Paediatric Committee will have to create a databank, a network of skills, to be able to avoid – and this is absolutely necessary – duplications of these experiments, and to achieve a position where consideration can be given to the ethical and human aspects necessitated by experiments on such a fragile group of people as sick children and their families. Another vital point is the incentives/responsibility, incentives/prescriptions mechanism. The Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, for which I am the draftsman, has as you know approved a proposal for a proportional system. I would therefore like to call on Mrs Grossetête and the other Members who are in favour of different solutions not to demonise our proposal but to try to understand that each of us, representing only ourselves and our own ideas, has put forward what we each believe to be the most appropriate solution for paediatric medicines, and thus child health. A proportional solution, which could be extended past the six months, might also help those medicines that are very expensive because of the research involved and that have a small market to have a longer extension. In any case, regardless of the position that this Parliament adopts, I ask the Commissioner to agree with this proposal, by giving a positive opinion to enable an assessment mechanism to be created which, after a certain period, will enable us to understand what the best proposal is in the light of the facts. This is the most important point, because our children, the children of Europe, have the right to see their needs and their requirements met.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

