<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Hiltrud Breyer</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, we welcome this regulation. The fact that over 50% of the medicinal products used in Europe to treat children are neither tested on children nor authorised for paediatric use is preposterous and no longer acceptable. Why has the pharmaceutical industry, which is, after all, always preaching personal responsibility, not seen fit in the past to conduct these very studies itself? This is an indictment of the pharmaceutical industry: it is out to make a killing, a huge profit. That is why I think it appropriate that we should be honest about, and make no bones about, the fact that this debate in this House is about how this regulation must not be allowed to become the means whereby the few help themselves to the profits they are interested in. We must also, then, seek to lay down very clear conditions. We are not just talking of a couple of million euros here, but of sums into the millions and billions. I agree with those Members who say that patents need to be protected for a shorter period of time. We have re-tabled an amendment to extend patent protection to just four months, and I should once more like to ask all my fellow Members to support this amendment. We need, however, to make the conditions even clearer. These medicinal products must have a therapeutic benefit. After all, it is senseless to knowingly allow children to be made guinea pigs in tests in the absence of any therapeutic benefit: this is unacceptable. The clear aim must be for rewards to be reserved exclusively for those whose clinical trials have been successful. Only if we really act together on this can we truly speak of a success. We should not, however, allow this to give rise to an industry wish list; the focus must be on the interests of the children.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

