<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Johannes Blokland</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>IND/DEM</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to thank the rapporteur for her excellent report. I can also support the majority of the amendments that have been adopted by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety. Even so, I voted against the amended report in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, because I was disappointed that the duration of the patent extension had not been amended. It will be plain to everyone that for many medicines, a six-month extension is not necessary. The extra costs involved in research that is necessary to obtain approval for paediatric use are relatively low, but that is not the case for all medicines. For some drugs with a low turnover, the six-month extension may prove necessary after all in order to recoup the costs. That is also the thrust of the amendments tabled by our group. We would like to see a three-month extension put in place by way of standard, and provide for an additional three-month extension for those medicines where this proves too short. That is fair on everyone and cost-saving for national health systems. It would be irresponsible on our part to apply the six-month extension to all products. After all, health insurance is expensive enough as it is. I would therefore call on everyone’s support for Amendment 89 tabled by Mrs Breyer, Mrs McAvan and Mrs Corbey or Amendments 91 to 93 tabled by my group.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

