<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Irena Belohorská</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SK</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Like my forespeakers, I would like to thank rapporteur Mrs Grossetête for her work on this important document. Its aim is to improve the current state of affairs, which is untenable from the medical point of view and, from the ethical point of view, it is unfair to children, to say the least. I believe that it does not require medical education to understand that a child is not just a miniature adult. Children are individuals whose metabolism is very different from that of adults. It is not possible to simply reduce the dose of medication needed to treat a child proportionately to its weight. For, we know that medications often have side effects that are well tolerated by adults, while they may lead to serious health complications in a child. I realise that it has not been easy to acknowledge the medical viewpoint, requirements and recommendations of the physicians while at the same time respecting the often legitimate claims and demands of the pharmaceuticals industry. But, what bothers me more, is that the discussion about this directive in Parliament concentrated on whether patent protection should last six months, three plus three or four plus two. From the aspect of priorities, this fact is not important or decisive. What is important and urgent is that children get the final product – a medication developed with due account of and respect for the distinctive status, that of a child. Our ultimate aim is a healthy child. If, as a by-product, we have a happy pharmaceutical company, then we have achieved what we have intended and had to do.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

