<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Miroslav Mikolášik</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SK</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Today we have the opportunity and the responsibility to decide about the health of our children. In this discussion we should be focusing on the medical considerations, and not allow ourselves to be influenced solely by financial considerations: who will profit or who will lose. As a doctor I am in favour of and strongly support the view that research into paediatric medicines must always be compulsory, safe, highly professional and subject to constant checks, if for nothing else, because there is still a shortage of medicines for children, and because the development of new substances must go ahead. We should also realise that the development of medicines for children should not be based on the premise – already mentioned several times before – that a child is just a reduced version of an adult. Children have their own specific characteristics, completely different metabolism, and different susceptibility to medicines, as Dr Belohorská said just before me. The European Union must set out binding regulations for all Member States that will not harm the health of children, but that will ensure the availability of high-quality children’s medicines within optimum timescales. Also for this reason the debate in our committee took account of the widest variety of viewpoints of major stakeholders and their professional arguments, and I therefore propose, with full support of my political group, that the incentives for manufacturers take into consideration the costs borne by the manufacturer in developing the drugs, and that at least a minimum period of time be set during which the newly developed medicine may not be manufactured by generic companies. Responsibility teaches us to check, after six years, the effectiveness of the measures taken and, if necessary, to adapt the established parameters accordingly. In finishing, Mr President, I would like to voice my support for rapporteur Françoise Grossetête’s idea to set up the MICE (Medicines Investigation for the Children of Europe) agency. In this way we will be able to ensure that all children in the European Union will have the same access to first-class medicines, and I call upon you to take that responsibility.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

