<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Mojca Drčar Murko</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>14</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I believe we need to establish a system of appropriate rewards for the holders of patents on medicines who have to carry out compulsory clinical trials for the use of such medicines in paediatrics. However we must take steps to prevent the accumulation of rewards under this regulation and other areas of European legislation. A large part of the debate has revolved around questions that have already been superseded by the establishment of a sensitive balance between the producers of original and generic medicines in the recent revision of European pharmaceutical legislation, questions such as ‘Who will get more?’ and the like. When we also take national health budgets into account the picture changes. The entry of producers of generic medicines into the market increases competition, reduces the cost of drugs and reduces the strain on health budgets. If such a goal is to be reached and the producers of original medical products are to be reimbursed for the true additional costs they incur as a result of clinical trials, it makes sense for European legislation to be based on verified information regarding these costs. The unjustified short-term extension of the market monopoly on drugs produces large profits and places unjustifiable new burdens on health resources.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

