<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jiří Maštálka</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>CS</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>16</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Ladies and gentlemen, I agree with the comments made by previous speakers, who said that the draft regulation that has been submitted to the House is not only of great significance, but also urgently needed, and that it should provide the greatest possible benefits to the youngest citizens of the European Union. As a doctor, I believe that the draft’s most important feature is its attempt to afford greater protection to child patients, in view of the fact that they constitute a particularly vulnerable group of patients. Further welcome developments include backing for information on medicines being as widely available as possible, as well as provisions guaranteeing greater protection for child patients in clinical research. Similarly, I am delighted that the MICE programme has been set up for independent research into certain medicines. Turning to the paragraph in Article 36 that has provoked such debate, it is my opinion that a three-month extension of patent protection is adequate for the time being. I should like to congratulate the rapporteur on her work on this dossier, which has been far from easy. It is my firm belief that there will be a positive outcome to the vote on this draft regulation, which will bring benefits in social, health and also ethical terms.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

