<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jan Tadeusz Masiel</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>18</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, this draft paediatric regulation is a welcome development for all of us. It is an expression of our concern about the health of children in Europe, and also, in the long term, of children in non-European countries. Nevertheless, it should not be forgotten that the negative financial impact of the regulation will be greater for some countries than for others. As former Commissioner for Enlargement, Mr Verheugen is probably better acquainted than anyone with the major financial problems facing the health service sector in Poland. Unduly long periods of protection for patents and registration data would have particularly harsh consequences for less wealthy countries whose market economies, which act as a guarantee of normal economic conditions, have only been in place for a short time. We should take joint action to ensure that the pharmaceutical sector does not earn excessive amounts at the expense of the public in the Member States, since this sector has in any case no cause for complaint about profits. I am opposed to the pharmaceutical sector receiving anything other than minimal rewards, and I am in favour of opportunities being made available as rapidly as possible for the production of generic medicines. As Mrs Roth-Behrendt concluded, however, the quality of children’s health care is more important than the amount of money saved.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

