<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Frederika Brepoels</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>19</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, first of all, a word of thanks to our rapporteur, Mrs Grossetête, for her enthusiasm and perseverance with which she has fought for the health of all children in the European Union is certainly in order. At long last, research and development of children’s medicines are given the attention they deserve. Enterprises can, and should, be rewarded for investing in research of this kind, only incentives of this kind will ensure that they continue to invest in new medicines for children. Moreover, we should not overlook the fact that they employ thousands of people in the process. A fixed six-month extension of the supplementary protection certificate is preferable for all kinds of reasons, but transparency and sound agreements are key words in this respect. We must consider the potential implications of a patent extension for all children in the world. In Belgium, for example, it was Dr Janssens who made Sporanox, his antifungal, available to the developing countries, but now that Janssens Farmaceutica has been taken over, it will be interesting to see whether the new owners will adopt the same line. In addition to attention to research, it goes without saying that the government must also continue to guarantee accessibility to medicines. Let me give you an example: in Belgium, the manufacturer of Rilatin independently increased the price of a box of tablets from EUR 2.60 to EUR 6.52, the level of the European guide price. The increase for parents of children with ADHD is prohibitive, certainly if you consider that there are children who need a few boxes a day. The pharmaceutical industry can, and must, therefore be stimulated in the area of research, but should, at the same time, consider the people who have to pay for those medicines. I have just one more question for the Commissioner. Apparently, products not covered by a supplementary protection certificate, including certain AIDS medicines, do not qualify for an extension if research is carried out during the period of patent protection. Can the Commissioner confirm this, and if so, is it possible for this clause to be changed at this stage?
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

