<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Genowefa Grabowska</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>20</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the regulation on paediatric medicines is necessary for everyone, and in particular for children, or in other words the youngest citizens of the European Union. Its aim is to ensure better medicines at reasonable prices that every mother can afford. I should like to congratulate the rapporteur on her work on this regulation, which will allow us to send a positive message to our voters. It will demonstrate that Parliament supports the development of paediatric medicines, and that we attach a great deal of importance to the treatment our children receive and to their health. Although we made a number of mistakes when drawing up this draft regulation, fortunately we still have a chance to rectify these mistakes during tomorrow’s vote. Firstly I wish to express my opposition to what are termed double rewards, that is to say, the granting of financial assistance twice to the same investigations or investments. Secondly, I believe that it is a mistake to waive the requirement for a paediatric medicine to be registered in all Member States before additional patent protection may be obtained. Paediatric medicines should be registered and available in all Member States, and not merely in a few. I cannot consent to certain EU citizens being deprived of the chance to receive treatment using new and improved medicines, and I find it intolerable that companies producing such medicines should be rewarded regardless. This is unfair in social terms, unjustified in legal terms and contrary to the principle of equality. It should not be tolerated by Parliament. Thirdly, I have serious doubts regarding the proposal to extend patent protection for paediatric medicines, as every new medicine is in any case protected by a patent, regardless of whether it is used to treat children, women or elderly people. There can be no doubt that extending patent protection would limit access to the market for generic medicines. We should not consent to this. Every mother would pay any price to protect the health of her child, but the question I would ask is why mothers should pay more, given that Parliament could adopt amendments that make it possible for them to pay only as much as is necessary.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

