<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Vittorio Agnoletto</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>22</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the approval of this regulation represents an important advance: today the majority of European minors take medicines whose effectiveness and safety has not been documented in children and adolescents, who are therefore exposed to greater risks than adults are. However, the implementation of the regulation will depend on the activities and responsibilities of the scientific committee which, while working within the EMEA, must retain its independence from the pharmaceutical industry in the interests of children. The proposed control activities of this committee should be made public, to enable all citizens to be aware and informed of what it is doing to improve their health. The implementation of the register of clinical and pharmacological experiments involving children and the creation of a European paediatric form, to be regularly updated, will also be important. In addition, in order to set up the MICE programme, envisaged by the regulation, it will be necessary to clarify the financing methods and how they interact with the EU’s framework programmes. The prolongation of a patent by six months is yet another gift to the pharmaceutical multinationals, in total disregard of the health of children and running counter to the objectives of this very regulation. The pharmaceutical industry is the industrial sector that in recent years has distributed the highest dividends to its shareholders, and it certainly has no need of even greater profits!
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

