<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Evangelia Τzampazi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>24</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, it is an uncontested fact that public health is one of the most valuable social commodities. After congratulating my honourable friend, Mrs Grossetête, I should like to draw the House's attention not only to the basic outlines, but also to the details relating to public health, access to quality services and the creation of reliable control mechanisms. Special attention needs to be given to the question of the production, testing and marketing of medicinal products, mainly due to the obvious need for greater transparency, given that direct and indirect financial interests attach to the production and marketing of these products and a whole set of medical practices and actions depend, either at research level or at application level, on their use. We need with this report to safeguard the important right of child patients to protection both from the needless administration of medicinal products and from their subjection to treatment or research protocols of unknown value and efficacy. Medical and paediatric research programmes, licensing requirements for medicines and post-marketing studies must become beneficial means, both for patients and for medical and pharmaceutical research centres, so that we can safeguard maximum possible medical efficiency. Creating a strong system of risk management, creating a list which will be given to all health agencies, companies and workers involved and providing the facility for informing patients about the treatment protocol to which they are to submit and its anticipated therapeutic value constitute, in conjunction with the foregoing, a strong system of protection and improvement. There are no scales for weighing the health of children against financial interests. (Applause)
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

