<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Frédérique Ries</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>25</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I would like, in my turn, to thank Mrs Grossetête for having adopted the same philosophy as was applied to rare diseases: mobilisation against the injustice suffered by some patients, in this case children. Recently, the Belgian paediatric association rang the alarm bell: 50% of medicinal products prescribed to children and almost 90% of those used in intensive care are not approved for paediatric use. Clearly, this regulation is urgently needed: research and development are expensive and we must support the efforts that will be required of the pharmaceutical firms, and thus also support the fixed period of six months during which they will not be subject to competition from the sector. At the same time, we must promote lower-cost paediatric research, the clause regarding review in six years, the MICE programme for paediatric research and, as is vital when children are involved, measures aimed at avoiding the unnecessary duplication of studies that meet this requirement. It is this delicate balance that we need to maintain in our vote tomorrow, a balance that meets the expectations of paediatricians, families and the millions of young patients in Europe.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

