<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Medicinal products for paediatric use</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0247/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-09-07</DATE>
    <ITEM>9</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Françoise GROSSETETE</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Günter Verheugen</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>33</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, first of all, I should like to thank all the speakers for their overall support. There does seem to be a broad consensus in the House that something needs to be done in the field of medicinal products for paediatric use. I have listened very closely and should like to start by dealing with the question posed by many Members; that is, whether the Commission can guarantee that the funding required to ensure the necessary scientific and research-policy safeguards for this legislative proposal will be made available within the Seventh Framework Research Programme. The answer is yes, I can assure you of that. I have already reached the appropriate agreement with my fellow-Commissioner Mr Potocnik. The Seventh Framework Research Programme makes clear reference to child health, and I am assuming that the Commission will be deciding on the relevant programmes in just a few weeks, as planned. It may come as a surprise to hear this from the person responsible for enterprise and industry in Europe, but I should like to reiterate categorically that what interests me here is neither the interests of enterprises nor those of industry, nor even the interests of national health authorities; my one and only concern is the interests of the children to whom this proposal relates. I have been dismayed to hear a number of arguments here this evening that clearly betray support for cold economic interests. I wish to make it perfectly clear to you that the Commission will have nothing to do with this. We shall not deviate from our proposal on the crucial point: the duration of the Protection Certificate. This is the cornerstone of the whole proposal, without which the European pharmaceutical industry – which is of course privately organised – will not produce the necessary research investment. It may sadden you to hear that the European pharmaceutical industry needs to make a profit, but that is just the way it is, and neither I nor anyone else in this House can change that. That is why we have an interest in the European pharmaceutical industry generating revenue: it will invest heavily in research only where it sees the prospect of financial gain. There is no way of getting around this. Some of the things I have heard here are naïve, at best. Appeals are of no use whatsoever in the face of the profit-driven mentality; only clear free-market incentives. We are creating such incentives, and for that reason I once again urge you most strongly to lend your support – not in the interests of industry, the health sector or the authorities, but solely in the interests of the children and their parents. (Applause)
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

