<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Quality assurance in higher education</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0261/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-13</DATE>
    <ITEM>10</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ljudmila NOVAK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ljudmila Novak</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>1</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>3</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    This report was produced on the basis of the need to improve European cooperation in the area of higher education, and especially in the area of the improvement of quality. Higher education must become more transparent and even more reliable in the eyes of students and the citizens of Europe and also in the eyes of those living in other continents. The report calls for the establishment of common bases for an internal system of quality assurance and for external assessment on the basis of common guidelines and criteria. In this way we wish to encourage all institutions of higher education to develop strict internal mechanisms for quality assurance and to apply the results of all assessments in order to bring about further improvement. It is equally important that the results of assessments be made accessible to the public. The standards and guidelines as proposed by the European Association for Quality Assurance in Higher Education have already been adopted – specifically at the meeting of ministers for higher education, which was held on 19 and 20 May 2005 in Bergen within the framework of the Bologna process. However, these common general standards and guidelines cannot be an impediment to development, and we need to encourage diversity and innovation among higher education institutions. Ministers have also welcomed the proposal to establish a European register of quality assurance agencies, and have called upon the competent authorities to pursue the further development of the practical aspects of implementation. Our report also stresses that, in order to avoid disparities, European Union activities in the area of quality assurance in higher education should be developed in line with the Bologna process, in which 45 European countries are involved. As the process continues it will be necessary to establish a European register of reliable quality assurance agencies, and it will also be necessary to establish criteria and rules of operation for such agencies. For the purposes of assessment or additional assessment aimed at enhancing their international standing in relation to their needs and profile, higher education institutions will be able to choose independently from the agencies in the Register, in accordance with national legislation or agreements with the competent authorities. Equally, cooperation between agencies is desirable, with the aim of establishing mutual trust and the mutual recognition of assessments. This will contribute to the more rapid recognition of qualifications in the case of people studying or working in another country. The more the European Union improves the quality of education on all levels, the greater will its opportunities be for at least coming close to the goals of the Lisbon Strategy. Here we should not overlook the fact that the people associated in this community can learn a great deal from each other, if of course we are able to cooperate and successfully exchange our experiences and examples of good practice. I firmly believe that each country has specific positive experiences and knowledge that can be shared with others. At this time of rapid development and economic competition, our cooperation in the area of education and science is all the more necessary and urgent if we wish to keep pace with developments on other continents. I trust that all Member States and competent institutions will take this report seriously and will strive to improve quality in the area of higher education, something that will undoubtedly also bring greater satisfaction to students, professors and researchers as well as to us citizens, while at the same time improving mutual cooperation and economic growth in the European Union.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

