<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Quality assurance in higher education</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0261/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-13</DATE>
    <ITEM>10</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ljudmila NOVAK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Tomáš Zatloukal</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>CS</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, there can be little doubt that most Members of this House would agree that education, and above all higher education at university level, is one of the key prerequisites for achieving the Lisbon goals. Higher education in Europe must be improved in order to make it more transparent and to enhance its reputation, both for our citizens and for students and researchers from other continents. Few would question the fact that development and the ability to compete on the global market depend on levels of education. Research is a key aspect of technological development, and the latter is closely connected to national prosperity. Since universities are centres for both cutting-edge research and teaching, the assessment of such institutions is of both academic and public interest. In order to ensure that higher education in all fields is of as high a standard as possible, a common set of standards and procedures for assessing individual universities, based on a wide range of criteria, should be used. It would be in the interests of individual Member States to find out how their universities perform in international comparisons, since it is the Member States which confer the right to award academic degrees, and which, in the majority of cases, also fund study towards such degrees. The Council has recommended that the Member States should set up quality assurance agencies in the field of education and accreditation. If such assessment agencies are to perform the tasks assigned to them, they in turn should undergo regular assessments, in order to guarantee that they are fully independent and professional. This would ensure that their findings would be regarded as accurate and not subject to any doubt. Those most affected by the problems in question, namely students and university employees, should also be involved in the overall assessment system. Quality assurance at European level necessitates the drawing up of a trustworthy list or register of independent and reliable quality assurance agencies. In conclusion, I should like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs Novak, for her excellent work.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

