<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Quality assurance in higher education</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0261/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-13</DATE>
    <ITEM>10</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ljudmila NOVAK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Christa Prets</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, a lot has been said today about Lisbon and about the importance of education. One of Lisbon’s objectives is further European cooperation in quality assurance in higher education. There are various criteria by which quality must be measured. The Member States’ own quality criteria are every bit as important as those of individual universities or those that apply on an international level to European higher education competing with other countries. What this means is that it is necessary to set up quality assurance systems and accreditation agencies to – as we have already heard – evaluate institutions of higher education, or to improve those that already exist and make them more international, following that up with a Europe-wide register or list of quality assurance agencies from which the institutions of higher education would choose a suitable one, which would then carry out the assessment. The assessment should rely on the standards and procedures adopted at Bergen, although these should not be regarded as static and unchangeable. Education is a living and constantly developing field; the requirements should be adapted to changing times and new developments, and I would add that cooperation with the higher education community is indispensable in this. The agencies are supposed to interlink with those in other Member States, and this they must do. If we establish standards, we will end up recognising more degrees, diplomas and types of training, of which there is such an urgent need in a single educational area. Although mobility is a quality criterion, it can have extremely negative effects where the number of students from a neighbouring country oscillates between 30% and 50%, with the consequence that the indigenous students lose out – as they do at present in Austria. I realise that the Austrian Government has left a certain amount undone in this respect, but I ask the Commissioner for his support in defusing this conflict situation, for doing so will be very important, not least in terms of its effect on the public perception of the European Union.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

