<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Quality assurance in higher education</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0261/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-13</DATE>
    <ITEM>10</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ljudmila NOVAK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Mieczysław Edmund Janowski</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>UEN</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I am grateful to Mrs Novak for the report before us today. The quality of academic learning is not simply a matter of receiving full mutual recognition for higher education qualifications. There is a much greater issue involved as well, namely the search for truth. As stated by the Commission in 2002, the European educational model should serve as an example to the rest of the world where quality is concerned. The decisions taken at Bologna, Prague and Bergen are therefore crucial, and one of their main features is European accreditation. Accreditation agencies must be transparent and able to resist pressure of any kind. There is scope for abuse in connection with accreditation. Demographic factors mean that institutions compete strongly against each other for students, because their very existence depends on the latter. On the other hand, the immediate introduction of overly strict provisions may lead to serious difficulties for certain institutions that have not yet achieved their full potential. In such cases, it is important to give the institutions a chance to remedy their shortcomings. A great leap forward in academic education has also taken place in my country, Poland. For example, some 300 private institutions of higher education have come into being there over the last 15 years, which is extraordinary. All aspects of research and teaching must also have a moral dimension. In the interests of good quality learning, it is essential to nurture the relationships between teacher and pupil and between lecturer and student. We should remember the words of Solomon: ‘How much better is it to get wisdom than gold! And to get understanding rather to be chosen than silver!’.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

