<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Quality assurance in higher education</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0261/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-13</DATE>
    <ITEM>10</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Ljudmila NOVAK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>0</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ján Figeľ</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SK</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, thank you very much for these essentially positive and supportive positions that will further inform the decisions on recommendation. I would like to emphasise the word ‘recommendation’, because it is the States that have the authority and right to decide. We shall hold a meeting at the level of education ministers in November. I am convinced that we have now entered the decisive second half of the Bologna process and that the credibility of the entire Bologna process is strongly linked to quality, which under the proposed system should be a matter of mutual trust. That is also why this issue is so very important for the future of European higher education, and for its attractiveness and status in the world, and here I naturally agree with many other speakers. Mr Janovský remarked that this is the higher goal – to make Europe regain its attractiveness and become a benchmark and arena for global themes or discussions, and for education reform policy. One question posed by Mrs Prets specifically concerned Austria and the situation in that country. At a university level, the situation reflects the decision of the European Court of Justice last July. It is part of the primary law of the Union, that is, the Treaty plus the case law of the Court of Justice, and it is important that the States implement the Treaties as agreed. But the Commission is ready and willing to share its expertise, and to provide specific assistance in the search for ways to proceed in the future. This would, on the one hand, satisfy the terms of the EU Treaty, and on the other hand, provide a response to the specific problems or difficulties that we have in connection with mobility. But it would be premature to conclude this discussion now, since the working group has only just started its work with the specialists from the European Commission and the Member States, including Austria. That is all, for my part – I would like to thank you not only for your report, but also for the proposal supporting that of the Commission, which, despite certain modifications, preserves its original character and meaning.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

