<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Proinsias De Rossa</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to discuss the report from the point of view of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, on behalf of which I drew up an opinion. I argued that there should be a gradual opening-up of the various programmes to all of our neighbourhood policy countries. It has been proposed that they should be opened up to a number of neighbourhood countries but, given the very good work these programmes have done in encouraging the strengthening of people-to-people contacts, a general consensus should be reached on opening up these programmes more widely, where this can be done effectively. I am keen to ensure that the Erasmus Mundus programme will be continued under this heading post-2009, together with the inter-university programme set up last year, which aims to develop democracy and understanding between our various countries. One of the obvious failings of the current proposals, in my view, was the almost complete lack of any reference to developing democratic citizenship. Mention was made of citizenship, but I felt that there was a lack of emphasis on the democratic role. Given that the Commission and the Council had already accepted that this was a necessity and had already agreed to set up the inter-university programme in Venice, this should be supported. I am disappointed that there appears to be a dispute between two Commission DGs as to who should fund this programme in the future. I hope that the problem can be resolved as a matter of urgency.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

