<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Françoise Castex</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, for whose opinion I am the draftsman, is in favour of the Commission’s initiative for the Erasmus and Leonardo da Vinci programmes and, in particular, of integrating higher vocational training into the Erasmus programme. Bringing the two together in this way signals our desire not to single out students according to their field of study, be it academic and general, or vocational. I congratulate the rapporteur, Mrs Pack, on the quality of her report and thank her for having taken account of the greater part of the opinions of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, in particular as regards lifelong education and training, which together are acknowledged as being one of the keys to growth and as guaranteeing the quality of jobs. Lifelong training should be a right and should be the specific responsibility of businesses, and these factors should be recognised at Community level as a fundamental social right. Thanks to these programmes, a European space for training and education is gradually being created, and we have a great need of this space to support the labour market. We need greater harmonisation and convergence of qualifications, and we need the skills of European employees to be guaranteed throughout the EU, and thus rewarded appropriately. This seems to us to be an effective guarantee against social dumping.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

