<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Erna Hennicot-Schoepges</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to begin by congratulating Mrs Pack not only on her excellent report, but also on her personal commitment to promoting the mobility of young Europeans. The Erasmus programme owes a great deal to her tenacity, and the budget increase that she is calling for fully reflects her commitment. Furthermore, I should like to remind you of the speech made by Mr Barroso in Berlin and of the speeches made by all of the group leaders within Parliament as part of the 70 cents for culture campaign, all of whom promised an increase in the ‘culture’ budgets. Three remarks need to be made on the subject of the reform as it is presented to us. The internal market would be more competitive and businesses more mobile if young apprentices were better prepared for being mobile. The protectionist instincts of many small-scale businesses would be thwarted by the practical experience that the Leonardo da Vinci programme gives to young people by allowing them to carry out work placements in other countries. The budget estimate that has been made for 150 000 apprentices is insufficient. The Erasmus programme is too elitist, as the sums allocated to the recipients are not enough to fund the total cost of their mobility. The only people who are therefore eligible for this programme are students whose parents can pay the remaining sum, unless the Member States assume responsibility for doing so, which is not the case at present. Finally, university students would be more mobile if the Council tackled the real problems, namely those relating to the transferability of grants, students’ status, their social security and the right to work, which are all issues that could be addressed, given that they were mentioned in the Commission Green Paper of 1996. The Commissioner will perhaps be able to inform us as to how the work is progressing. Mr President, culture is priceless, but it does come at a cost. If we want to give Europe a soul, funding has to be granted. The Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats will be supporting Mrs Pack’s proposal.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

