<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Sepp Kusstatscher</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, let me start by complementing Mrs Pack. If we want to bring Europe together, it is through education that we are most likely to be able to do so. We have here the most diverse range of educational initiatives, which promote the exchange of knowledge and skills between the European states, make it easier for citizens from different cultures to meet one another and provide them with support in learning languages, above all the languages of their neighbours. I particularly approve of the attempt to bring the various measures under one roof, am glad to see the Balkan states being made eligible for grants, and welcome the explicit intention to support initiatives for political education. I do think, though, that there is room for further improvement, in that more account needs to be taken of those who are socially disadvantaged and in that procedures need to be simplified – and let me observe that not all the difficulties are of the EU’s making. I have practical experience of running projects, in the course of which I discovered that the problems in the Member States themselves are often even worse than at EU level. What I do not agree with is the cuts made to the Leonardo programme. I am opposed to any reduction in funding for vocational education. The fact that practical training costs more than purely theoretical education cannot be a reason for cutting funding for it. It is both dishonest and inconsistent to announce 2006 as the European Year of Job Mobility while at the same time making funding cuts.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

