<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Adamos Adamou</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the Lisbon Strategy, as formulated after the spring Council, subjects education to the needs of the market and emphasises lifelong learning and education solely as a means of promoting low-paid permanent jobs. Constant calls are being made for greater private investment in the sector of scientific research in order to serve the needs of big business. At the same time, innovation and novelty are not orientated towards promoting technology and the quality of life. The Lisbon Strategy formulated overlooks the increased need for public spending on and investment in education, for bursaries and for detailed programmes for lifelong learning supporting informal education which, at the same time, are not accessible to a large slice of the population. The extension of lifelong learning, in cooperation with the business element is one of the basic objectives set by Lisbon. With this programme, universities will open their doors for the purpose of specialising workers in new professions, who will then provide cheap manpower for businesses which invest their money in the university in question. This will create a vicious circle for young people, who will be dismissed and then, once they have been retrained, will be recruited as cheap workers in new professions. It proves that the Commission's objective is not lifelong learning; it is lifelong exploitation. To conclude, it is obvious that, if these policies are implemented, we shall basically start making education subject to the whims of enterprises and sacrificing it to competitiveness and profit. It will mean the subjection of research to the commands and needs of businesses and a reduction in the state's contribution. We consider that the Member States of the Union can develop education and lifelong learning without it being coloured by speculation and unilateral adherence to the so-called needs of the market and to competitiveness. That is why the Confederal Group of the European United Left/Nordic Green Left cannot vote in favour of the proposal to establish a programme in the field of lifelong learning.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

