<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ljudmila Novak</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    There is increasing talk of a crisis in the European Union. Since we know that we will only be able to overcome the problems of the modern world and the challenges of globalisation with a strong Community, we must make constant efforts to preserve cohesion between the nations of this Community. We may be greatly assisted in this by the very programmes offered by the report on lifelong learning. Our future lies in the young people who will soon be making decisions on politics, economics and all the other aspects of our life. It is therefore all the more important that as many young people as possible are involved in international education programmes even at an early stage of their education. In this way they also become much more motivated to learn languages, to get to know other countries and to display greater tolerance towards other nations and cultures. At the same time, we have found that those countries that have invested greater funds in education have advanced more rapidly and now rank amongst the most highly-developed countries. I therefore support rapporteur Doris Pack in her efforts to secure more money than hitherto in the financial perspective for education. The rapporteur is also trying to secure support for people with special needs, who are important and equal members of our society. Given that we wish to be a community with social sensitivity, we must devote special attention to them. It is also equally important to involve as many small- and medium-sized enterprises as possible in these projects, as well as people with vocational education, in order to motivate them for lifelong learning and help them to acquire new and useful expertise. Since an additional benefit of the European Union is the fact that our nations can learn from each other, I support cooperation and mobility in the area of lifelong learning, which is becoming both a need and a reality for people in all walks of life.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

