<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Åsa Westlund</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SV</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>16</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, every year, thousands of students from the whole of Europe are given the opportunity to study abroad, thanks to the programmes we are now talking about. For many students, these exchanges are, in actual fact, the most practical advantage of the whole EU project. By studying abroad, they not only gain new knowledge and new experiences of another culture, but also disseminate knowledge and in that way help increase the quality of European education which, in turn, is one of the cornerstones of the Lisbon process. Through tomorrow’s vote, we shall simplify the administrative routines, which may lead to quite a few schools and universities participating more actively in the programmes and encouraging more students to study abroad. I am also pleased that, during this process, we in the Socialist Group in the European Parliament have protested against the proposed cuts in vocational education and training desired by the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats and that we have also supported continuing to provide plenty of opportunities for people who have already completed their professional education to study abroad. Vocational education and training do in actual fact make a very important contribution to the EU economy and to the way in which the labour market operates. Thus, encouragement needs also to be given to people who have completed their professional education to move around more. It should not only be those at university who get to study abroad. Where funding is concerned, I should also be delighted to contribute money to these programmes but, at the same time, I think that all the budget issues should be dealt with simultaneously so that we really are forced to prioritise what is important. I shall therefore support those amendments that are in keeping with Parliament’s report on the budget as a whole, that is to say the Böge report.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

