<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Tomáš Zatloukal</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>CS</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>17</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the current debate centres on an initiative backed by representatives of all the relevant parliamentary committees, whatever their political persuasion. This is because most of us understand that the proposed integrated action programme is one of the steps that must be taken if the European Union is to become an advanced knowledge-based society with sustainable economic growth, more and better jobs, greater cohesion and stronger culture. I must stress, however, that in my opinion it is essential for each Member State to draw up its own national lifelong learning strategy if the lifelong learning system is to function effectively. The financial instruments under debate today are and will be necessary for the implementation of these strategies. It goes without saying that they are also indispensable for the successful implementation of the various components of the action programme, and I therefore fully support the rapporteur’s calls for more funding for this initiative. One of the many reasons why this proposal deserves our support is that it makes provision for the mobility of individual secondary school students and adult learners by introducing new types of mobility action into the Comenius and Grundtvig sub-programmes, and provides new opportunities to make contributions in kind to the implementation of projects. Those involved in organising lifelong learning programmes and applying for funding under the associated financial instruments will undoubtedly welcome any reduction in the red tape associated with these procedures. I therefore support the proposal to simplify administrative procedures according to the level of grant. Education is cited in key EU documents as a crucial component of future prosperity and growth. Without adequate funding, however, the latter goals will remain out of our reach, and will never make it off the drawing board, as is the case in a number of Member States. I should like to thank the rapporteur for her work.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

