<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Guy Bono</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>18</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, allow me first of all to congratulate the rapporteur, Mrs Pack, on the work she has done on this subject, so important for the future of the European Union. I should just like to say a few words to point out that the vote within the Committee on Culture and Education has enabled significant progress to be made, in particular with regard to the mobility of apprentices. The specific conditions attaching to the status of apprentices are today preventing these apprentices from fully participating in the Community mobility plan. Only 0.15% of a given age group in France and 1% in Germany today benefit from the Leonardo da Vinci programme. The vote within the Committee on Culture and Education represents significant qualitative progress, as it has made eligible for this programme the support measures taken by all of the organisations involved in promoting the mobility of apprentices. Such progress should enable the objective set by the European Commission – that of securing at least 150 000 work placements by 2013 – to be achieved. We are hopeful that this progress will not be called into question. Mobility of young people – and particularly of apprentices – in vocational training constitutes one of the tools enabling a real spirit of enterprise and innovation to be created in Europe. This is one of the prerequisites for achieving the objectives set by the Heads of State or Government as part of the Lisbon Strategy.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

