<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Lifelong learning</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0267/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>6</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Doris PACK</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ján Figeľ</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SK</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>20</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I would like to reiterate my thanks not only for the support, but also for the truly constructive atmosphere during the discussions. This shows the kind of maturity that is needed in order for education and vocational training to be put at the centre of European Union policy and cooperation among Member States. There are some suggestions and remarks that I would like to make. We must realise that it is still premature to comment on budget figures, although the initial level of political support has been very strong. Thanks to the position adopted by Parliament, both the budget and the two budget-funded programmes for culture and youth are receiving strong support, and this is giving rise to the expectation that they will be successful areas for future cooperation within the enlarged Union. An appeal to launch programmes for third countries is also under way. The programme itself is expected to receive 1% of the total amount budgeted for cooperation with other countries. These countries are as yet unnamed, but I would like to stress that just as Erasmus Mundus has included and will continue to include cooperation with third countries, the Tempus and Tempus+ programmes will also provide for such cooperation. Several speakers referred to lifelong learning as a right. This represents a great change. We are striving to create the systems, conditions, strategies and programmes for lifelong education in the Member States, and to ensure participation and a real place for people within this system. By comparison, although there is considerable scepticism and apathy in Europe, there are continents where the debate is still focussed on the fundamental right to basic education, while we are now talking about the right to lifelong learning. This provides an excellent example of cooperation among the States. From the standpoint of vocational courses or training, the ‘Copenhagen’ process and the Bologna process are now much more visible. I am convinced that the current proposal to introduce the European Qualification Framework, which is the subject of consultations with the Member States, will give a great boost to mobility and to the recognition of qualifications. I would also like to reiterate what has been said by Mr Thomas Mann, that part of the quota for the placement of university students in companies will be shifted from the current Leonardo da Vinci programme to the Erasmus quota under the future programme. This is something that also deserves notice. I would like to conclude with a few words concerning the institutions mentioned by Mr Pavilionis – institutions earmarked for support. If the European Parliament and the Council reach a consensus, the Commission can support the inclusion of institutions in the list of nominees. In the European Inter-University Centre in Venice discussions are taking place on how to adapt the regulation on human rights, and we want to be prepared for the future and to find a solution that will enable the continuation of financing for this institution. This is basically all I wanted to discuss. I am pleased to note that education has become a matter of consensus between the committees, as well as between political groups and individuals. This is a sound premise for success.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

