<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ingeborg Gräßle</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, let me say that the Committee on Budgets holds Mrs Gröner in high regard for her work and also for incorporating the figures from the Böge report in her own. We stand right behind these figures. It is because culture gains nothing from a weakened rapporteur or from an enfeebled parliament in which different figures are used virtually every month that we strongly urge that these figures be taken as a basis. What will happen when the Luxembourg figures come in? If we were to adopt a policy other than that regarded as right and proper by the Bureau of this House and by the Conference of Committee Chairmen, the simple fact is that culture would have gained nothing. We are very happy about the ‘Youth in Action’ programme, because it takes on board a large number of suggestions made – not least in former years – by the Court of Auditors and has taken simplification as its watchword. This is a highly interesting approach, and one to which we wish to give our firm backing. Speaking as the rapporteur on the reform of the Financial Regulation, I have to say that I regard these items as very important and useful. I note with regret the way in which you have, in this programme, demanded a plethora of derogations from the Financial Regulation and have been given them. I personally would have set greater store by altering the Financial Regulation itself in such a way that one could work, under the ‘Youth in Action’ programme, with a large number of smaller organisations and smaller grants. The aspects of the programme that have been presented I regard as very important. We have submitted two more amendments that would bring about additional improvements in this area: one has to do with the establishment of a database to facilitate the notification of all those organisations that complain about the vast number of documents that they have to submit, and making it possible for all this data to be recorded once and for all, leaving only amendments to be done. This would both save the Commission administrative effort and make things easier for the recipients of grants, and that in turn would have a direct effect on the image of the European Union. If subsidies are more readily obtainable, the demand for them will rise, and that is something we regard as needed, particularly by small programmes. The same applies in the case of the amendment on the ‘proportionality of documents and grants’, which gives the Education and Culture Directorate-General every opportunity to act as it thinks right and proper in the implementing provisions.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

