<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Piia-Noora Kauppi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, recent events show that Europe’s younger generation is just as divided on the question of our continent’s future as their parents. On the one hand, the numbers of students and young jobseekers crossing EU borders in search of new experience and career prospects is constantly increasing. On the other hand, we can see how many young people feel disconnected from this new multinational reality. Indeed, young voters were instrumental in the French and Dutch rejections of the Constitution. Some on the political extremes, both left and right, celebrate this disaffection and claim vindication for their old-fashioned ideas. However, I think most would view this with concern, for, if the younger generations are not propping up the EU, making it more democratic and inclusive in the process, who is? Mrs Gröner’s report therefore comes at a critical time. The Youth in Action programme is not merely an information campaign on the EU; it is something far more valuable. By increasing cross-border exchanges and getting young people involved in civic activities, the programme can help counter prejudice, broaden horizons and fight apathy. In the process it can influence and introduce them to the necessity and value of European cooperation, something all too many of their leaders are currently unable and unwilling to do. I would like to highlight a few points. The programme’s initiatives must build on existing grassroots locally-based youth organisations to the greatest extent possible. They should not be bureaucratically managed from Brussels. Second, people as young as 13 should be eligible as a rule, not as an exception, and, of course, gender balance should be upheld. Finally, the range of countries with which youth partnerships are struck should be the largest possible. The final related point, beyond today’s agenda but which we will eventually need to tackle, is how to improve conditions for young people to settle in another EU country. Too often an extended period of student exchange coupled with some work experience results in young people losing some of their national study and social entitlements. To avoid them being penalised in this way, we need to improve the transferability of some key social entitlements across the EU, especially for young people.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

