<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Rolf Berend</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the ‘Youth in Action’ programme that the Commission has put forward, to which our committee’s rapporteur, in her even-handed report, has proposed various improvements for us to vote on, has demonstrated its suitability as a means of adding value to youth policy throughout Europe. The new youth programme has been made significantly simpler than its predecessor, with, for example, a flexible and less bureaucratic procedure for applying for funding, which is what this House has always argued for. Moreover, the programme is now funded by only one budget line rather than four, as was formerly the case. My group is at one with the rapporteur as regards the adjustment of age limits for participants, ensuring the exclusion of discrimination, and both the equal participation of disadvantaged young people and the involvement of young people in the evaluation and ongoing monitoring of the programme’s objectives. The extension of the programme to more countries, the greater importance of European cooperation in youth work and the more generous age limits make it necessary for the financial framework to be increased to – as has already been said – EUR 1.128 billion, but I would like to emphasise that in this we are being consistent with the Böge report. Turning to the weighting of the actions, my group endorses the proposed indicative levels for the minimum funding of Actions 1 to 5. As the Commissioner emphasised, the report entrenches the possibility of staging youth seminars and the European youth weeks, thereby making them a component of European youth policy. I congratulate the rapporteur and thank her for the good cooperation.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

