<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Christa Prets</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the programme bears the name of ‘Youth in Action’, but the fact is that youth is always in action; the question is with which actions we can help them, where we can support them, and what sort of motivation we can offer them. This programme is certainly one possible option, and offers them a choice of ways in which to develop themselves or build networks at the European level. If they are to do that, though, there is an urgent need for real simplification where administration is concerned. Youth organisations need help not only with the submission of applications – the Youth Forum on its own cannot do it – but also with the disbursement of funds, which is quite crucial, as the young people are waiting for their money. Their activities are up and running and they need to be paid for. If they are not, the young people, who have no money of their own, find it difficult to repay their advances, and so I address an urgent appeal to the Commission that these payments should be made at least three months after they are agreed to. Youth Week is very important as a permanent component of this programme, in that it enables the young people – and us too – to engage in dialogue. By voicing their concerns here, young people get to know the institutions and are listened to by them. Rather than allowing what they say to us to go in one ear and out of the other, we should take it away with us and ponder it. That disadvantaged young people should be guaranteed participation on a basis of equality is something that goes – as it must, in this context – without saying, for it is only in this way that young people will be able to understand other people who are in a disadvantaged position and help work towards a shared and sympathetic Europe.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

