<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Athanasios Pafilis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, through the continuing Youth in Action programme, the European Union is trying to nanny young people, to create the illusion that it is interested in their participation in policy and to turn them into passive recipients and applauders of its anti-grass roots policy, which also creates impasses for young people. In truth, when one third of young people are unemployed, when a large proportion are literally being crushed by flexible forms of employment, when the prevailing ideology is cultivating unbridled individualism, does the title of the Youth in Action programme not sound ironic and insulting? When the entire philosophy of the policy of the European Union is to subject everything to the maximisation of the profits of big business, when for that purpose previous rights are abolished, exposing young people to wretched and cynical exploitation, is it not a mockery to make available a few million euros so that they can cash in on the miserable future which capitalism has in store for them? Is it not hypocritical to state that it is cultivating the solidarity of young people when the imperialist policy of neo-colonialist wars sends hundreds of thousands of young people to death, hunger and poverty? The programme finances actions which will promote the so-called values of the European Union; in other words, the creation of disenfranchised workers and scientists, so that maximum profit can be returned to big business. It promotes voluntary – in other words unpaid – labour and social consent. It proposes the creation of voluntary special qualifications for missions to countries outside the European Union, so as to create agencies for promoting its policy. At the same time, it is financing state-funded organisations which have nothing to do with the neo-grass roots movement and which, of course, fully accept the policy of the European Union, presenting them as allegedly representing the youth of the countries. The way to combat the problems of young people is in organised struggle, in quarrelling with the policy of the European Union and the European Union itself, in order to pave the way at national and international level for deep changes and reversals for the benefit of the peoples.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

