<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Rolandas Pavilionis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>LT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>UEN</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    One of the very important points of this renewed programme, which was raised by colleague Gröner, is the fostering of tolerance in young people towards other cultures and other languages. It is clear that the creation and promotion of a culture of tolerance among young people, as well as the encouragement of cooperation between the youth of different nations, is an important guarantee of the success of the entire European Union. It is also clear that education and expansion of young people's horizons have a special role to play in the process of fostering a culture of tolerance. Thus, the priority of learning and the accessibility of education regardless of race, nationality, gender, religion or social status must stand out in the whole philosophy of this programme's implementation. It is particularly important that this programme becomes accessible to the young in countries neighbouring the European Union, especially those countries in the grip of autocratic regimes. In this regard, the experience of Lithuania's youth of cooperating with young people in Belarus, particularly in an academic sense, may be a good example to the whole of Europe. We thus acquire one of the most effective instruments in the expansion of democracy and the spreading of European values. The Union for Europe of the Nations supports this report.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

