<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Pál Schmitt</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>HU</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the 2000-2006 Youth programme resulted in a great number of developments. In many cases it brought considerable progress in the lives of youth communities in Hungary. However, the programme failed to achieve some of its objectives. For instance, it failed to reach young people living in rural areas. Disadvantaged youths living in small rural settlements have not been able to get involved in the programme easily. Therefore we must ensure that starting from 2007 as many rural youths as possible are able to get involved in the programme. It would be more helpful to youth communities of countries participating in the programme if the details, information material and some kind of a database were more accessible. We know that some progress has already been made in this direction, but it would be important to make more of the successful projects accessible, so that youths and youth organisations can get to know them. These projects will set their imagination in motion, and will help them acquire useful experience. Another positive step forward is that settlement-level and local government youth work is relied on to an ever-increasing extent. This is the right way forward, because the principle of subsidiarity must be implemented consistently in youth affairs. It is important that local youth work becomes an integral part of international youth cooperation. Please allow me to call your attention to the fact that the Hungarian Parliament concluded a cooperation agreement, a programme agreement with the Serbian Parliament involving a tolerance programme. Within this programme tolerance camps will be organised for young people, which may contribute to the prevention of nationality-based or ethnically motivated incidents involving Hungarian and Serbian youths. In the course of these events, young people will meet artists, politicians and sportspeople well-known in both countries. They will create a virtual parliament where they can deal with human rights and minority issues. I am certain that the Youth in Action programme will provide opportunities for youths in many countries to understand and get to know one another better, which will create a strong foundation for taking action against all forms of discrimination and will raise the tolerance levels of young people. Congratulations, Mrs Gröner!
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

