<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Youth in Action</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0263/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>7</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Lissy GRÖNER</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ján Figeľ</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SK</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    I would like to thank the rapporteur, the various committees and also the political groups and individuals for their contributions and viewpoints. I realise that the times we live in are not easy, but there is hope. For young people, it started with the White Paper and continued with the Youth programme, which is continuing and remains popular. The proposal on the table reaffirms and extends existing options and financial support, and widens the spectrum of countries and geographical areas, as well as the age brackets. For the first time in our history, a summit of Heads of State or Government has adopted special conclusions in the form of the European Youth Pact. We have spoken with young people this year about youth issues and, later this week, I will discuss these matters in Cardiff with representatives of Member States and European youth. In response to some of the suggestions that have been put forward, I would like to state that the flexibility inherent in the programme should be very apparent during December Youth Week in Brussels. It can serve to link up various programmes, for instance those on culture and youth, sports and youth, and social inclusion and youth. On the subject of financial rules and regulations, I am a strong advocate of simpler, more transparent and speedier procedures. This is why we have incorporated more than one hundred proposals into the draft amendment on financial regulation for the European Union. The proposal is now in the hands of Parliament and the Council. I am confident that it will receive a very positive response in both bodies and that it will be beneficial for all areas concerned. I also would like to say that the European Commission supports the proposal put forward by Mrs Grässle on behalf of the Budget Committee, as well as many other amending motions. In conclusion, I would like to recommend strongly that the programme be implemented as complementary to and compatible with other programmes, such as the lifelong learning programme or the citizenship programme. These have great potential if they are coordinated, if they complement each other and if they are coherent. And my last remark: I would be very happy if next Thursday, following your vote, I could convey a message to the youth of Europe that the programme Youth in Action will be one of the first to receive support within the constraints imposed by the financial outlook, as an instrument for the future European Union in 2007 to 2013. Thank you for considering this approach.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

