<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Alexandra Dobolyi</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>HU</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, first of all I would like to thank the rapporteur for his wonderful work. I am certain that he had invested a considerable amount of time in it. Globalisation is an irreversible fact. As a result, cultural supply and the system of relationships between people and other nations have expanded to an incredible extent. National particularities are relaxed in some areas, and as a result of the interaction between cultures, national identity has acquired a new significance. The new circumstances cast a different light on national and common European identity. In this context I would like to stress that in a globalised world culture is one of the most important means of strengthening, deepening and promoting common European identity, while preserving the multicultural diversity of nations. The evaluation conducted by the Committee, based on extensive consultation, pointed out that rationalisation and strengthening are a requirement in this area of community activities, as well. It is important to stress that in order to achieve effective results and avoid unnecessary duplication, community activities must be closely interconnected in the areas of culture and education, youth, sport, research and discrimination. Community activities must supplement one another and must be harmonised. In order to achieve higher efficiency, the extent of cooperation between Member States and regional programmes should be increased as much as possible. I trust that the proposed programme may contribute to a better coordination of community activities, focusing on the benefits provided by added European value. Finally, I would like to emphasise that the role of cultural foreign policy has acquired a new significance, and its objective is to facilitate the creation of nation states with higher levels of culture, standards, education and democracy. This would result in a community of European states that is fully able to renew itself, with a strong sense of self-knowledge and self-esteem. And as the Commissioner mentioned in his introduction, I hope that the proposals for amendment ... (The speaker was cut off.)
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

