<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Bogusław Sonik</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>1</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Parliament’s draft resolution on the Culture 2007 programme (2007-2013) is likely to promote creativity and strengthen mutual awareness of the culture and history of the nations of Europe, as well as boosting cooperation in this field. One of the most important steps we could take towards this goal would be to identify the protection of cultural heritage of European significance as one of the fundamental goals of the Culture 2007 programme. The Commission’s draft fails to offer clear support for projects relating to the European tradition or to the common roots that are an integral part of the identity of contemporary Europe. After all, it was the culture of our continent, that was centuries in the making, which shaped European identity, and continues to do so today. This culture also encourages the recognition of our common heritage and civilisation, as noted by John Paul II during a speech before the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe. As a member of the Association of European Capitals of Culture, I have had first-hand experience of the enthusiasm generated by the European Capital of Culture initiatives among the people of our continent. Such initiatives allow millions of citizens to participate in artistic, informative and instructive projects of enormous educational merit. This effort on the part of artists and cultural operators gives us good reason to be proud of the wealth of talent and the diversity of artistic inspiration founded on the achievements of our European tradition. We should not forget that Europe was divided for 50 years. The aim of this programme should be to raise awareness of the culture of the nations of Central and Eastern Europe across Western Europe. This culture, including those aspects of it inspired by Christian values, was stifled by Communist totalitarianism. In my opinion, the proposal to change the minimum budget for projects eligible for support is therefore very much to be welcomed, and this is a point upon which I disagree with the Commissioner. Reducing the minimum project budget from EUR 60 000 to EUR 30 000 per year would increase the number of cultural operators able to participate in the programme. This would be a significant change, particularly in the new Member States, where such operators face much greater problems in financial terms than operators in the old Member States. There is every justification for allowing a larger number of entities to benefit from the proposed funding, provided that they meet the programme’s substantive objectives.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

