<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Doris Pack</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, this programme represents a challenge to what we call European cultural policy, for the absence of a real cultural policy puts at risk the idea that the European Union should unite not merely states but also peoples, particularly at a time when the European Union cannot be other than seriously concerned about its own future. Such a European cultural policy could well help to bring together the needs of the cultural world and those of the public, thereby addressing the soul of Europe as nothing else can, and with it, people’s hearts, for it is with their hearts, more than with their minds, that people will be prepared to vote ‘yes’ in a referendum. We take the view – although I note that the Commission does not – that the cultural actions should be biased towards the starting-up of small and medium-sized projects, for it is these that can help to make visible the cultural riches of the European Union’s individual regions and promote real public awareness of them. I hope that I will, for a change, find more sympathy for this idea from the Council than from the Commission. While ministers of culture, and even the President of the Commission, are wont to make pious utterances stressing the significance of culture, and to sing its praises as an agent of integration, cohesion and citizenship, they should also ensure that sufficient funding is available for it. Even with what we propose to add to it, the programme really is not adequately fitted out. I very much hope that pious sentiments will be backed up by actions!
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

