<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Guy Bono</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, allow me first of all to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Graça Moura, on the work he has done on such a crucial subject as the ‘culture’ programme. I should like quickly to go back over four points, which seem to me to be important and which I defended within the Committee on Culture and Education on behalf of the Socialist Group in the European Parliament. Firstly, as regards the horizontal aspect of the programme, it must be noted that the Commission’s proposal reflects good intentions, which are along the right lines. No one need oppose strengthening the coherence of the programme in order to put a stop to the fragmentation, which for so long has characterised the EU’s action with regard to culture. However, there are the intentions, on the one hand, and the resources proposed, on the other. I therefore come to my second point: the matter of the budget. It is no use the European Union setting ambitious objectives, such as promoting cultural diversity and cultural cooperation, if the budget available is not adjusted. We have therefore called for a logical increase in the budget allocated to this programme so that it can fulfil the task assigned to culture, namely that of contributing to the development of a European culture and a European identity, both of which will enable countries to put a stop to their excessive national self-interest and, consequently, to come out of the crisis that the EU is currently going through. My third point concerns the commemoration sites. We have called for a clear distinction to be made between cultural organisations and the sites, not because we believed that these sites are not important, quite the opposite. As such, we would hope that the Commission will guarantee that the budget for the ‘citizenship’ programme, in which we have asked for the sites to be included, is increased accordingly. Finally – and this will be my final point – I was keen that the cultural industries, which provide so many jobs, should be mentioned in the recitals for this programme. This was particularly the case for Amendments 7, 11 and 13, adopted by the Committee on Culture and Education. A recent study by Eurostat showed that the cultural industry contributed significantly to the European economy. With this in mind, it would be desirable to carry out a study highlighting the importance of these industries for the European economy.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

