<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Claire Gibault</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the report by Mr Graça Moura on the Culture 2007 programme for the period 2007-2013 wholly fulfils the expectations of culture professionals. It is balanced, consistent and demanding. It attaches great importance to the content of the proposals, it prioritises cultural diversity and it is committed to the development of European citizenship. I thank Mr Graça Moura for his listening skills and for the quality of the dialogue that we have been able to establish. I too am particularly delighted that it was possible for the cultural industries to be recognised in a recital of this report. I personally took a tough stand in calling for them to be included in this programme, and even if this result still falls far short of the mark, the progress made is by no means insignificant and deserves to be pointed out. I will continue to defend the position whereby the cultural industries contribute to promoting European culture: they generate employment and give economic added value to the cultural sector. There is even less reason to neglect the cultural industries inasmuch as they are the ideal vehicle for developing European culture and for underpinning its diversity. There is, unfortunately, a fly in this particular ointment. None of my colleagues in the Committee on Culture and Education will dispute the fact, because if there is, in truth, one point on which we are unanimously in agreement, it is that of the budget. I deplore the fact that culture should still be considered by the Commission as a luxury, secondary to the most crucial requirements. Is it really the case that culture is nothing but a luxury and that it is only secondary to the most crucial requirements? Violence exists; it is aimed at destroying culture. One form of violence is to argue that culture is pointless. I am therefore profoundly shocked by the meagre sum in the budget package allocated to culture. However, there remains a glimmer of hope in my opinion, Commissioner. The Unesco Convention, which has just been approved by a huge majority a few days ago, is a great victory for Europe and demonstrates once again that, when Europe is united, it is strong. It is also a great victory for European culture. With its diversity finally recognised, it now remains for Europe to assert itself on the international stage. However, it will only be able to pursue its role of ambassador if you give it the financial resources to do so. I will conclude by simply saying to you, Commissioner, that it is up to you to act in order to obtain a decent and respectable budget for culture, one that does not remain below 1% of the overall budget.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

