<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Helga Trüpel</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner Figel', ladies and gentlemen, over recent months, this House has seen a campaign waged in support of culture, which called for a European cultural budget amounting to 70 cents per inhabitant per annum. At present, we allocate EUR 35 million to the overall European cultural budget, and that, being equivalent to the amount received by a major theatre in Germany, is a shameful figure. Now that the Wall has come down and we have 25 Member States, we really want Europeans to encounter each other anew; we really want cultural exchange and more information; we want Western and Eastern Europe to have a real opportunity to establish contact with each other, but the present budget makes that impossible. The reason why my group has raised the figures that the Commission proposed or that have now emerged from the Committee was that we need 10 times as much as we have at present. We now get no more than 7 cents, but we need 70 cents. With them, we would have a real chance of getting a cultural offensive for Europe moving. I can go along with the Commission’s basic approach, and its three great goals of transnational mobility, transnational exchange of cultural values and inter-cultural dialogue, for all of these tie in very well, not only with the fostering of contemporary culture, but also with the management of cultural heritage. I cannot agree to Mr Graça Moura’s proposal, in his additional amendment, for a fourth objective, for an exclusive emphasis on heritage upsets the good balance that we have worked to achieve between contemporary art and heritage management. It is for that reason that we shall not be supporting that additional amendment. I am glad to see that the narrowly sectoral approach has been done away with, and that there is a real desire for real interdisciplinary cooperation with our cultural projects. I, too, take the view that smaller projects should be given more opportunities.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

