<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Miguel Portas</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>GUE/NGL</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    For the Commission and the Council, culture is a matter of the EU’s visibility, which has been, and continues to be, the real aim of the ‘Culture’ programme. The first plus point of the Graça Moura report is that it distances itself from this view that cultural creations can be used for the purposes of political promotion. This is not the only plus point, in fact. The Commission and the Council want maximum visibility with minimum resources, and therefore channel aid into a few actions, bodies and initiatives. This is a bad move. In the name of visibility, there has been a shortfall in Europe of so many projects that rely on it. This is a further trend that the report seeks to rectify, on its own terms. It supports projects up to two years, simplifies procedures for obtaining financial support, makes a commitment to transparency in application processes and places value on heritage and linguistic diversity in the programme’s objectives. These are more than enough reasons to vote in favour of the report. The British Presidency continues to block the financial perspective. As we know, Mr Blair has his priorities elsewhere, but I feel that everyone present is agreed on one point; the proposal of EUR 600 million is the rock-bottom minimum if the Union wishes to present itself to cultural creators and producers as an institution that still gives some value to the words it says. I would like to think that the men and women of the Committee on Culture and Education will be up to the task of assessing the final proposal from the perspective of that value. I hope, too, that the Council understands the message.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

