<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Erna Hennicot-Schoepges</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>11</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to congratulate our rapporteur on his report. My criticisms are not, of course, directed at his report, but instead concern the mindset with which the matter of culture is addressed by the Council and by the Commission. The Constitution would have given us the foundation for tackling a common cultural policy, based on the diversity of cultures and on mutual acceptance of the principles of freedom and of human rights. However, the Constitution did not go so far as to grant culture the status of a real Community policy, which was an argument for not voting in favour of it. The objective that should be achieved by increasing our knowledge of others is precisely the objective sought by all of our countries. Doing away with the fear of others is a prerequisite for attaining a life led in peace in a society of genuine cultural pluralism. Learning about differences: that is the objective of a common cultural policy. Among the Commission’s objectives, the mobility of persons leads me once again, Commissioner – and I am well aware that you yourself are not the person with responsibility – to ask the following question: where, in all of this, is the work of the Council on problems related to social security, taxation and status, which prevent people from being truly mobile, not to mention its work on the lack of financial resources to support real exchanges between the new Member States and the old ones? The Commission has held on to intercultural dialogue as an objective. It was high time this problem was highlighted. Greater synergy between education and culture was the subject of one of the amendments tabled by our Parliamentary committee. Greater synergy is necessary, and all the more so given that, since 1998, and under the UK Presidency, employability – a terrible term – has been part of European texts as a principle for education. It is a mistake to think that greater emphasis on culture in school curricula would be a waste of time. Creativity and a lively mind are qualities that are acquired through an appreciation of the arts, just as a culture of tolerance and the prevention of violence are founded on respect for artistic feeling and on the cultivation of the senses. As from now, the budget for 2006 has been revised downwards, to EUR 36 million instead of EUR 38 million. I note that, despite the fine speeches made by Mr Barroso and by all the group leaders in front of a small number of active contributors to the cultural sector, their words are not about to be followed up by actions. Point duly made.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

