<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Nikolaos Sifunakis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>EL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the Culture 2007 programme is the main means for implementing Community action in the field of culture. It sets a series of important objectives, such as the cross-border mobility of cultural agencies in Europe, the transnational movement of artists and cultural works and cultural dialogue, objectives which cannot be implemented satisfactorily by the Member States due to their transnational character. However, we must not forget that the programme is also the means for financing these objectives. We cannot therefore set objectives for culture without at the same time proposing what the financial resources will be with which we shall achieve them. Consequently we, as the European Parliament, must propose a specific amount in the budget. However, when we talk about the objectives of the programme, we must emphasise that the maintenance and knowledge of cultural heritage must be expressly included in the objectives of this programme. Among these plans, prime position must continue to be given to actions which aim to rescue the architectural heritage of Europe. Another point which we must also keep an eye on is facilitating the participation of small agencies in the programme, which is often difficult. Our rapporteur, Mr Graça Moura, who has done an excellent job, is well versed in this subject and his report takes account of the needs of small cultural agencies and, by extension, of small countries.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

