<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Bernat Joan i Marí</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>14</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    – Mr President, as we face the financial perspective of Culture 2007 we are very worried about an issue that the European Union has not yet properly addressed: the promotion of marginalised languages and of minority languages within the EU. I would like to refer specifically to the budget problems for the European Bureau for Lesser Used Languages, whose main goal is to maintain real language diversity in the European Union. According to the Charter for Regional and Minority Languages, each linguistic community has the right to maintain and develop its own language and pass it on to future generations. In the European Union we have official languages, minority languages and languages like Catalan that, being majority languages in their own country, are not in the first or second groups. The EU has to provide support for all these languages and for linguistic diversity in Europe. That means a budget is needed for minority languages and for the European Bureau for Lesser Used Languages. I know that is against the Jacobinist language policy that is practised in some European states, but the EU will work to promote diversity, democracy and freedom and to maintain real equality between languages in the European Union.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

