<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Marianne Mikko</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ET</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, esteemed rapporteur, ladies and gentlemen. The ‘Culture 2007’ report that is presently before Parliament, after being accepted at the cultural commission, has lost all the amendments referring to the preservation of the memory of the crimes of Stalinism. In terms of total number of deaths, Stalinism was no less tragic than Nazism. Mass deportation and concentration camps were part of the arsenal of both regimes. In my homeland, Estonia, nearly 10% of the population was deported and killed under the leadership of Stalin. Elderly people and children represented more than half of the number of those deported. Even pregnant women were shown no mercy. Stalinism and Nazism are two sides of the same ideology. They were conceived together. They divided Europe through the Hitler-Stalin pact. After the expansion of the European Union, we cannot avoid passing judgment on the crimes of Stalinism, which were mainly committed in Eastern Europe. That judgment alone symbolises that we are members of one European family. The bearers of a misanthropic ideology remain a threat to us. Their face changes as necessary, but inside, Neo-Nazis, national Bolsheviks, neo-Stalinists and so on are nevertheless brothers in arms. In the name of Europe, we must not let the crimes of Nazism or Stalinism be forgotten. The Cultural Commission agreed to transfer the preservation of the memory of Nazism and Stalinism to the ‘Citizens for Europe’ programme. It is no secret that the ‘Citizens for Europe’ programme received even less funding than ‘Culture 2007’. Therefore, I would like to receive public and clear confirmation from Commissioner Figel’ that transferring the commemoration of the victims of terror to the ‘Citizens for Europe’ programme will result in the additional funding and attention that it deserves.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

