<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Maria Badia I Cutchet</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>16</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we European citizens must take pleasure from the approval of this programme: a cultural programme, renewed for 2007-2013. It demonstrates the importance that the European Union attaches to the citizens, adopting a programme aimed at improving the dissemination of the culture and history of all of the peoples of Europe, at conserving and protecting the cultural heritage of the Union and promoting artistic, literary and audiovisual creativity. This programme, furthermore, is essential for facing the challenge of enlargement and also in terms of developing an awareness of European citizenship, because only through the dissemination of our common cultural values can we illustrate the different foundations of our European identity. But this programme will also be open to many countries that are not Members of the European Union. Given, therefore, the programme’s very ambitious objectives, we must have a budget to match. In this regard, I believe that the needs defined by the European Cultural Foundation in July 2004, calling for an annual budget of EUR 315 million, quite reasonably pointed to the need for a more generous budget. I therefore support the rapporteur’s call for a budget greater than the EUR 408 million proposed by the Commission. I would like to end by expressing my satisfaction at the adoption of the UNESCO Convention on the Protection and Promotion of the Diversity of Cultural Expressions; my satisfaction at its approval, but above all at the fact that the European Union has spoken with one voice and has demonstrated, once again, that when it acts together it achieves results. Please allow me, Mr President, to call on the Member States to ratify this instrument, and the sooner the better, since it represents significant progress in the recognition of cultural and linguistic diversity.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

