<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Culture 2007</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0269/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-25</DATE>
    <ITEM>8</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Vasco GRAÇA MOURA</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>4</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ján Figeľ</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SK</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP></GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>1</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>18</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Thank you very much for your numerous expressions of encouragement and for your statements advocating European cultural cooperation. Let me remind you that only a few years ago, and certainly before Maastricht, many would have said that this is not an agenda for Parliament, the Union or the Commission. More, much more is needed today. There is also greater political will for this kind of cooperation, and I am confident that it will bear fruit, because it is necessary. The first reason for this is globalisation, and the risk it brings of losing our identity. The second is European integration itself, which does not mean the integration or harmonisation of cultures, but the shaping of a community of cultures, where diversity is an asset and where unity is based on common values. Never before have themes and phenomena like identity, citizenship and culture been so intensively discussed and elaborated on in European institutions. I see this as a sign of the times, a signal that we are moving from the very basic post-war, coal-and-steel agenda to more demanding themes that call for greater maturity. Regarding some of the suggestions concerning culture, for example those of Mr Bono and others, I think that the new reasoning within the proposal defines the space for the culture industry very well. As for little and large, we already have a high rate of rejection: 70-75%. This means that further fragmentation will not result in a higher success rate, but we do want to achieve higher rates in the case of bilateral and trilateral dimensions and projects. My preference would be to give very strong support to Member States, to help them generate so-called matching funds, or financing that is complementary to European funds, which would help small or medium-sized operators in the cultural space. And, I repeat, the main responsibility for cultural policy lies with the Member States. We are willing and able to support and complement this, but not to replace it. Mrs Hennicot-Schoepges’ remarks about using taxation and social insurance to promote the mobility of artists belong to the culture ministers’ agenda. Their next meeting is scheduled for November. I am convinced that it is in the wider interests of everyone, not just ministers, but also all players in the field of culture. Mr Joan i Marí, I recently met with the European Bureau for Lesser-Used Languages (EBLUL). The EBLUL has enlarged its membership to 19 states, and I believe has a chance to develop its relationship with the European Union. May I remind you of the integrated lifelong learning programme that we discussed a few moments ago, which represents a new chance for the development of minority and regional languages. Today, we have many more official languages, and there is naturally more room for linguistic diversity. This is a value that calls for further investment. Mrs Mikko, Stalinist gulags will be included among our commemorative events. History is the teacher of life, but it is important that individual Member States also take steps to promote historical awareness. We should not expect the Union to take over a basic responsibility of the Member States – to remember their history and to promote an understanding of it in cooperation with their neighbours and with the entire European Union. I want to assure you that adequate attention and financing will be provided to this end, despite or perhaps because of the shift to the citizenship programme, since this is more a matter of civic maturity than of culture alone. In this context we have also financed special events such as the anniversary of Solidarity in Poland. There will also be other reasons. I am convinced that this can provide an impetus for such commemorations. These were the main points I deemed it necessary to comment on. I am also very grateful to you for supporting 70 instead of 7. On the one hand, the Commission welcomes it, and on the other hand, it is necessary that the Member States come to perceive culture as an integral component of European cooperation, because culture enables a better understanding of the present and future of a united Europe. A united Europe is much more about culture than about trade or geography. It is about the values that culture embodies.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

