<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European transport networks and energy</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0283/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mario MAURO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ingeborg Gräßle</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, for the public, the trans-European transport and energy networks are Europe at its most tangible. We all need infrastructure, and therefore we can all experience the European added value in this field. The report by Mr Mauro treads remarkable new paths in some areas. For the first time, the European Parliament is officially given a basis in the comitology procedure and is involved along with the Council in drawing up the priority list. That is welcome and desirable. The selection of projects is important to us, project monitoring equally so; that is why the comitology procedure is so significant and important. Incidentally, such involvement falls within the normal duties of national parliaments. This means that a little normality is coming to Parliament’s work. For this reason, we think it important that such things are also implemented. Democracy is not something one can pick and choose, but rather a fundamental procedure. I would appeal to Commissioner Barrot to give us a helping hand here and make these things possible. We regard the energy sector with some sadness. We are aware that currently only 1.7% of the priority list is cofinanced, and this proportion will fall still further. In the long run, we have to ask ourselves fundamental questions here. Our rapporteur has given the Commission several hard nuts to crack. Multiple financing from EU coffers, which is still forbidden under the Financial Regulation, should no longer be prohibited. The recovery of transport funds in the event of irregularities or failure to complete the project within 10 years is an innovative request, and we expect the Commission to enable its implementation, because this is important to us.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

