<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European transport networks and energy</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0283/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mario MAURO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Herbert Bösch</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, first of all, on behalf of my group, I should like to offer my thanks and sincere congratulations to Mr Mauro for his report. He has the broad support of our group. Until 1 May 2004, the trans-European transport network of the 15 EU Member States consisted of 75 200 kilometres of roads and 78 000 kilometres of railways. After 1 May 2004, this was extended by 14 500 kilometres of roads and 16 000 kilometres of railways. The Commission’s initiative to reassess and increase the resources for the period 2007–2013 is therefore more than welcome. To review what has happened to the old 14 priority networks from a somewhat critical perspective, too, it must be said that this is disappointing. Not a great deal has happened in this regard. At the same time, on the basis of this dispassionate analysis, we can also declare our support for the undertaking of the Heads of State or Government that is the Lisbon Strategy. The report by Mr Böge on the financial perspective subscribes to this in full. In contrast to many of the Heads of State or Government, we are declaring our support for what was agreed in Lisbon. We shall support the Commissioner on this path. We have also learnt from past experience that sometimes all it takes is a certain critical mass of cofinancing from Brussels to kick-start one trans-European network or another. We believe that the Commission’s views could signify this financial critical mass. For this reason, we shall gladly support the Mauro report when it comes to the vote.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

