<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European transport networks and energy</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0283/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mario MAURO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Sepp Kusstatscher</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I take a rather more critical view. It is to be hoped that the political authorities start to realise that so much traffic is indefensible for reasons of energy consumption, climate change, adverse health effects and environmental degradation. A drastic change in transport policy is needed. Failure to do so will result in the following scenario, which I venture to predict using the example of the Brenner Base Tunnel. A colossal building site will surround the area for at least 15 years. There is no point in the tunnel unless there are routes feeding into it, but the construction of those is a very long way off. The existing railway line will continue to deteriorate, particularly on the Italian side. An underground line is being built for high-speed passenger trains on the assertion that the intention is to take action against road freight transport. Construction will be much more expensive than is now being maintained. As is the case with the Messina Bridge, the taxpayer will bear all the risks. The burden on human beings and nature along the Brenner line will continue to increase in spite of the Brenner Base Tunnel. A couple of people will become richer, though. The Brussels coffers have whetted their appetite.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

