<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European transport networks and energy</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0283/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mario MAURO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Anna Elżbieta Fotyga</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>UEN</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>9</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on the granting of financial aid in the field of the trans-European transport and energy networks is urgently needed, and the approach it takes is very much on the right lines. None of the solutions put forward in either the proposal or the Mauro report could be called controversial. At the same time, however, it is hard to view the regulation in isolation from the list of priority projects included with the proposed measures. I should like to take this opportunity to focus on one such project, which forms part of the planned establishment of a common energy market in the EU. I refer to the proposal for a Baltic gas pipeline. When deciding on how to back this project, the European Union chose the more expensive option, since the agreements previously concluded with Russia provided for a cheaper solution, namely a second leg for the Yamal pipeline. It follows that the option chosen had been put forward at a later date. As Commissioner Barrot has said, the European Union gave preference to a solution that provides added value and ensures security of supply to certain EU Member States. At the same time, however, this solution disrupts and actually threatens the security of supply to other Member States, namely the new Member States such as Poland and the Baltic States. Furthermore, the project has certain negative political implications. This type of debate inevitably leads to a scaling down of political relations between the latter Member States and Russia, and to the deterioration of such relations.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

