<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European transport networks and energy</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0283/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mario MAURO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Gilles Savary</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>12</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to begin by congratulating the rapporteur, Mr Mauro, as well as Mr Bösch, who has been of great assistance to us in this work. I am speaking on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism and I would like to say that this regulation is long awaited. It contains many innovations for better managing the funds that are going to be invested in the trans-European transport networks, such as multi-annual programming, which is necessary and which is attached to each project, automatic decommitment, so that the funds do not remain unused indefinitely, the increase in rates of intervention, the establishment of European coordinators or the new loan guarantee instrument. This is therefore a regulation of very high quality, but it contains a significant mistake: we have considerably increased the rates of intervention, we have considerably extended the geographical scope of the trans-European networks, we have doubled the number of priority projects, and we do not yet have any budget! In other words, though we now have the key to the coffers, the coffers are empty. I believe that we must avoid the loss of credibility that we suffered in relation to the big Essen projects. I therefore believe that it is extremely important that we pursue the budgetary battle to its end, because otherwise we will suffer a very considerable loss of credibility, which would be a very great disappointment for all of the regions of Europe. Furthermore, it seems to me that the spending adjustment variable is what are being called projects of common interest, which are not priority projects. In this regard as well, I fear that many regions and many local authorities in Europe are deluding themselves. The regulation is deceptive: it says that it funds everything, not just priority projects, but also projects of common interest within countries. We are very well aware, though, that we do not have the resources for that and that we will focus solely on cross-border projects and the big priority projects. I therefore believe, Commissioner, that it needs to be put differently. In the absence of the resources to cover everything, we must explain that we will intervene wherever there is Community added value, that is to say, essentially the great cross-border projects.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

