<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Trans-European transport networks and energy</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0283/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>4</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mario MAURO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Alessandro Battilocchio</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>IT</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>15</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I speak on behalf of the new Italian Socialist Party. I thank Mr Mauro and Mr Barrot for the excellent work that has been done and for the important content of the proposal. At a time when Europe is divided on many fronts, I find it indeed essential to send out a message expressing our willingness to take specific action on the need for cohesion within our borders. I therefore fully agree with the content of the report: the TEN projects bring people closer together, reduce distances and inequalities, and eliminate borders. Thus they deserve our utmost commitment. I am therefore in favour of increasing our contribution to cross-border projects, which bring Europe closer to the local dimension and connect the public sphere with the private. I should like to have seen greater European Union support for energy networks: together with transport, they form the foundations of a European economy that can compete at world level. I hope, therefore, that the new rules will soon be approved and, above all, I hope there will be a swift solution to the problem of the financial perspective for the period in question. In that respect I appeal particularly to the UK and Austrian Presidencies, and I hope that President-in-Office Blair can give us something new and positive tomorrow to revitalise the debate.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

