<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Food additives</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0191/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mojca DR?AR MURKO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>María del Pilar Ayuso González</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>ES</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>4</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, I would like to begin by congratulating the rapporteur, Mrs Murko, and expressing my gratitude for the wonderful cooperation that is going to allow us to approve this proposal at first reading, with the compromise amendments we have achieved, including with regard to traditional products and the use of nitrites therein. Both the rapporteur and the Commissioner have explained the content of these proposals more than sufficiently. These proposals are intended to update and supplement the existing Community legislation, adapting it to recent technical and scientific advances and also to the judgments of the Court of Justice. I therefore believe that the compromise we have achieved is a good one, which fulfils the objectives of those judgments. I should, however, say that this revision - a technical amendment, as the Commissioner has called it - only plays a role that we could describe as a temporary fix. I therefore believe it is important for the Commission to present its proposal for a general revision of the legislation on food additives and sweeteners, and also that announced on sports drinks. Sports drinks are sold with little control, both in gymnasiums and in supermarkets; you can find sports drinks all over the place. Food additives are the result of constant technological advances that do not just allow us to enjoy better quality food products, but also offer the consumers a high degree of food safety. Nevertheless, it is necessary to prevent inappropriate use and to keep reviews up to date, in order prevent a lack of knowledge and media pressure from having a negative impact on consumer confidence and harming the image of foods containing these additives, despite the fact that they are not harmful, but rather are an improvement in food safety. I would like to say, finally, that I do not agree with the amendments presented by the Verts/ALE Group and, in particular, those which call for the Commission to present a report revising all of the existing authorisations for additives. This amendment reproduces the requirements of framework Council Directive 89/107/EEC on food additives, Annex II of which stipulates that all additives will be kept under constant observation and will be evaluated whenever necessary.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

