<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Food additives</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0191/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mojca DR?AR MURKO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Åsa Westlund</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>SV</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>5</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I should like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs Drcar Murko, and Commissioner Kyprianou for the desire for mutual understanding they have shown in the course of this work. The Socialist Group in the European Parliament obviously welcomes the Commission’s proposal to limit the use of those substances in what are known as jelly mini-cups that have led to tragic accidents involving choking. We also welcome the Commission’s proposal to establish the level of nitrates and nitrites on the basis of added values in, for example, meat products instead of, as at present, on the basis of residual levels. We believe that this will lead to safer monitoring for consumers. We want these restrictions to enter into force as quickly as possible, and we have therefore been anxious to reach a rapid agreement with the Council. We are also pleased that, under the agreement with the Council, the use of soybean hemicellulose is to be limited so as not to make life more difficult for allergy sufferers. We should, however, have liked to have seen lower upper limits for nitrates and nitrites. We should also have liked to bring about a ban on the use of antibiotics in foodstuffs since such use may lead to increased resistance, and we should have liked to have seen a more thorough investigation of the risks associated with the sweetener aspartame, but on these points a majority of the committee was opposed to us. Now that the Commission has, both in writing and orally here in the Chamber, stated that it takes our concern about the long-term use of aspartame and antibiotics in foodstuffs seriously, we shall support the compromise with the Council and so vote against the other amendments. We wish, however, to call on the Commission to return as quickly as possible to these issues, thoroughly to revise these directives on the basis of the need to limit the use of additives in foodstuffs, and to take greater account of the situation of vulnerable groups. More and more people are rightly expressing concern about the level of additives in food and about the long-term consequences of their use. We in the EU must take this concern extremely seriously.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

