<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Food additives</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0191/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mojca DR?AR MURKO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Marios Matsakis</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    . – Mr President, although this is a very lonely debate, it is nevertheless a very important piece of legislation because it deals with what we knowingly – or in many cases, unknowingly – ingest. It is also a somewhat complicated and controversial piece of legislation in places, and therefore much credit should go to the rapporteur for achieving a valuably balanced report. I wish to pick up on a couple of aspects that I feel need to be noted further. First, it is right to ban jelly mini-cups with gel-forming food additives in order to prevent choking in children, but the banning of gel-forming food additives in general is unwise because these substances are only hazardous when used in jelly mini-cups. If used in other products, they are perfectly safe; so I fully support the principle that we should not place a blanket ban on all substances, and should only ban unsafe products. Secondly, with regard to the newly authorised sweetener erythritol, I agree with the rapporteur that its laxative effect, even if at very low percentage levels, should be made known in the form of product labelling. As a matter of principle, I believe that it is an unquestionable right of the consumer to know exactly what he eats or drinks. That right surely supersedes any marketing tactics or side-effects. I thank the Commissioner for staying so late with us. The use of antibiotics is very unwise in any foods because of the danger of microbial resistance and allergenic reactions.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

