<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Food additives</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0191/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-10-26</DATE>
    <ITEM>5</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Mojca DR?AR MURKO</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Christa Klaß</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PPE-DE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, Commissioner, the purpose of the revision of the two directives is to align them with the legislation in force. In particular, scientific developments and technical progress have to be taken into account. New substances are being authorised and, very importantly, the positive list of permitted additives needs to be revised. We have discovered that what is really needed is a fundamental revision of food additives. Unfortunately, that is not possible at the present time, however, and so we have to make corrections. It is, of course, a healthy exercise to strive to market foodstuffs that are as pure as possible, free from additives. Yet modern society is very demanding when it comes to foodstuffs: they have to be good, look fresh, taste good, and retain these characteristics for as long as possible. We are seeing increasing consumer take-up of the semi-prepared and prepared products on offer. There are many reasons why the modern housewife can no longer get by without these convenience products; chief among these being lack of time for housekeeping and lack of knowledge of cooking and nutrition. Who still knows nowadays how to make a stew, potato dumplings or mashed potato? The foodstuffs industry fills these gaps. It has to use the auxiliary substances needed to meet the demands of consumers. We have come a long way in this regard: long shelf lives and instant products enable a wide variety of fast, time-saving meals. Consumers also make demands as regards food safety, however. That is why we are standing here today, on behalf of the consumer, demanding safety by means of equivalent standards and lists for the whole of the EU. I support the report by my colleague Mrs Drcar Murko and thank her for her careful treatment of the issue. Nevertheless, I should like to make a plea, late in the day, for consumers to visit a farm once more – in spite of all the modern achievements – to buy and sample food in its original form, as it were. Let us give our children the chance to learn cooking and housekeeping, then they can decide for themselves.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

