<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Information to air passengers</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0310/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-11-16</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christine DE VEYRAC</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jörg Leichtfried</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>6</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    (DE) Mr President, Commissioner, Mr President-in-Office, Mrs De Veyrac, ladies and gentlemen. First of all, I would like to congratulate Mrs De Veyrac very sincerely on her report and on the end result of her work. You have demonstrated in this case how real commitment can lead to agreement, and we expect that in the case of this dossier, which is vital for air safety, it will be possible to reach agreement at first reading – a very welcome outcome indeed. This is all the more remarkable given that this result has been achieved in a very short period, just three months. We have not only managed to reach agreement on this here in this House, but also, and this is the most remarkable thing, agreement has also been reached between Parliament, the Council and the Commission, which is very rarely possible in such a short time. On the other hand, this makes it all the more regrettable that such an important dossier is once again being debated just before midnight. The probable reason for that is that we are not just dealing with run-of-the mill resolutions, no matter how important they may be, but with a law that will probably ensure that many human lives are spared in the future. With regard to its content, this report deals with and improves upon some very important provisions regarding increased safety in the air transport sector, and goes well beyond the Commission proposal. The key points needed to ensure greater safety for Europe’s air passengers are a single common list based on harmonised criteria combined with a flight ban for the airlines on that list, and of course comprehensive passenger information. The possibility of integrating airlines from third countries is also very important. I am also delighted that we have succeeded in taking account of the rights of airline employees in the regulation. The importance of this has been demonstrated by the case of the FlyAir pilot dismissed because of whistle blowing. We have shown that by means of a European law we can effectively safeguard the interests of the public. I hope that this will serve as a model for further legislative proposals.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

