<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Information to air passengers</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0310/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-11-16</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christine DE VEYRAC</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Jeanine Hennis-Plasschaert</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>NL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>ALDE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>7</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, one uniform black list on the basis of common criteria is the only way forward. That is also the firm belief of my group, the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe. Whilst the proposal relating to this was well intended, this House’s Committee on Transport and Tourism quite rightly regarded it as too weak. Harsh though this may sound, the dramatic events of the past year seem to have served as a wake-up call to many, making us realise that it is pointless simply to bundle the national black lists. A ragbag, not automatically valid in law across whole of the EU, is a superficial gesture that provides no added value. It may, of course, prove to have some value, for we in the Netherlands have a saying that roughly translates as ‘to promise and give nothing is comfort to a fool’, it is precisely this image we wanted to move away from. In this light, this proposal is typically an area in which the EU can demonstrate its added value, for let us be honest: the fact that, to take an example quoted earlier, Onur Air was at one point grounded in the Netherlands, only to be able to take off in Belgium, does, of course, remain absurd. Such practices will simply lead to confusion among travellers, not to mention to potentially unsafe situations. Consequently, a uniform list, based on common European security criteria, is the only way forward, and is understandable to both travellers and European consumers. The many amendments demonstrate this House’s ambitious approach to improving air safety. Thanks to the Commission’s very helpful and willing attitude in this respect, combined with the Council’s decisiveness, we were able to swiftly table an agreement at first reading. When the proposal was discussed in the Committee on Transport and Tourism, I repeatedly called for new rules for a black list being linked to the existing SAFA (Safety Assessment of Foreign Aircraft) Directive, and to expand the competences of EASA, the European Aviation Safety Agency. I am delighted with the results we have achieved together, and with the Commission’s pledges to table proposals in the very short term, in which the EASA’s competences will be expanded and strengthened. The Commissioner indicated a moment ago that those promises were honoured as early as this afternoon. This is again a step in the right direction, for which I am indebted to you, Commissioner Barrot. We are committed to coherent and clear legislation, with the aim of increasing security and clarifying information for the traveller – something to which nobody can have any objection. Finally, I thank Mrs De Veyrac for all the work she has done in this area.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

