<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Information to air passengers</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0310/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-11-16</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christine DE VEYRAC</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Eva Lichtenberger</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>DE</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>Verts/ALE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>8</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would also like to offer my heartfelt thanks, particularly to Mrs De Veyrac, who has demonstrated great commitment in her work on this dossier, the scope of which grew significantly during that process, which cannot have been any easy situation. She took suggestions on board where that was possible, and where it was not, she kept us informed in a fair-minded way. So the process was extremely positive. With regard to content, I regarded the consumer protection aspect of this dossier as being particularly important. It is a crucial element in a world where consumers must also have adequate information to make choices as passengers. If that information is available, it will restrict another trend that could otherwise create difficulties for us, by which I mean the flagging out of carriers in order to circumvent strict safety requirements. I believe that if particular attention is paid to safety, we can halt this trend. We have taken an important step with the black list, but the most important step, implementation, still lies ahead. I say that because a common list requires criteria, checks and checks on checks. It is particularly important for this to be enforceable in third countries and capable of extension to those countries. I regard that as key. I am, however, pinning my hopes on the list having a more wide-ranging impact. Reputable travel companies will in future shy away from doing business with partners who cannot guarantee complete safety. This is an important issue for consumers and for the safety of every one of us.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

