<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Information to air passengers</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0310/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-11-16</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christine DE VEYRAC</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Bernard Wojciechowski</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>PL</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>NI</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>10</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, I believe that the amendments tabled by the rapporteur are a step in the right direction. Their aim is improved passenger safety, more transparent information on carriers and standard conditions for carrier companies from outside the Community. The guiding principles upon which Mrs De Veyrac has based her report will go a long way towards improving the standard of services offered by airlines, which is what matters most for passengers. One can only hope that extending the remit of the European Aviation Safety Agency to allow it to issue certificates will not lead to corrupt practices, but instead genuinely help to improve passenger protection standards. Such issues notwithstanding, I believe that the rapporteur’s demands are entirely legitimate, and I should like to lend my backing to her draft. I believe that if we adopt it as it stands, we will improve the quality of services and make it easier for passengers to choose the right carrier. This would automatically mean that companies that did not meet safety requirements would be forced off the European market. I would therefore call on the House to vote in favour of this report, for the sake of all air transport passengers.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

