<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Information to air passengers</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0310/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-11-16</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christine DE VEYRAC</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Ulrich Stockmann</NAME>
    <COUNTRY></COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>13</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    (DE) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, flying is safe in Europe, and we want it to remain that way in future, despite high growth rates in air traffic. That is the purpose of the regulation before us today, whose urgent adoption is backed across the political spectrum. I would like to thank the rapporteur for her excellent work. A European black list based on common criteria will in future eliminate confusion around decisions on safety issues, as was the case with Onur Air. I am sure that publishing this list will put very strong pressure on airlines that show insufficient regard to international safety regulations, and also to travel companies that have worked with such airlines in the past. Inclusion in the black list will inevitably damage such a carrier’s image and probably drive it out of business, resulting in a clear gain in terms of safety. The duty to provide passengers with information on the identity of the operating air carrier in cases where these has not happened in the past will lead to a marked strengthening of passengers’ rights. We can address small travel agencies’ fears that they will be overburdened by having to provide information by distinguishing between information relevant to safety and information on a change to another, safe airline, and by treating these two different types of information with differing levels of urgency. I welcome Commissioner Barrot’s plans to extend EASA’s powers to support for third-country airlines with safety problems. If we want to achieve that we will of course have to free up a little more money.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

