<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DEBATE-SPEECH>
  <BILL>
    <TITLE> Information to air passengers</TITLE>
    <CODE>A6-0310/2005</CODE>
    <DATE>2005-11-16</DATE>
    <ITEM>1</ITEM>
    <RAPPORTEUR>Christine DE VEYRAC</RAPPORTEUR>
    <ISSUEAREA>3</ISSUEAREA>
    <PASSED>1</PASSED>
    <RCV>1</RCV>
  </BILL>
  <SPEAKER>
    <NAME>Gilles Savary</NAME>
    <COUNTRY>FR</COUNTRY>
    <GROUP>PSE</GROUP>
    <STATUS>
      <ISPRESIDENT>0</ISPRESIDENT>
      <ISCOUNCIL>0</ISCOUNCIL>
      <ISCOMMISSION>0</ISCOMMISSION>
      <ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>0</ISOTHERBUREAUCRAT>
      <ISRAPPORTEUR>0</ISRAPPORTEUR>
      <ISCOMMITTEEREP>0</ISCOMMITTEEREP>
      <ISAUTHOR>0</ISAUTHOR>
      <ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>0</ISONBEHALFOFGROUP>
    </STATUS>
  </SPEAKER>
  <SPEAKER-NUMBER>19</SPEAKER-NUMBER>
  <TEXT>
    Mr President, some of us in this Parliament have lived through the dreadful experience of the Erika and Prestige maritime disasters and have witnessed the lamentable spectacle of the Member States pushing aside the European Union. For once, in the field of air safety, Europe has had a head start on events – I do not know whether we should be delighting in this, however, unfortunately – since we created the European Aviation Safety Agency in 2002 and the Commission proposed this regulation to us back in February, before the tragic summer we have experienced. I would therefore like to thank Mrs de Veyrac for the work she has done, since Parliament has considerably improved the text. For a long time it has vacillated between subsidiarity and Community added value. We are seeing genuine Community added value today since we have a Community blacklist, each Member State’s list will be distributed amongst all of the other Member States, and the European Union and the Commission have their degree of autonomy. This text therefore goes a long way. I would like to hark back to the maritime field. It has taught us that it was not a question of carrying out inspections. It is a question of knowing how frequent those inspections should be. It is also a question of knowing who is responsible. We have done this in the maritime field, and tomorrow we will probably have to do so for air transport. Finally, as you know, Commissioner, the human factor is very important in air accidents. The majority of them are the result of human failings. It is therefore very important that we provide for rules relating to the monitoring of the training of crews and a very high level of training that is harmonised at European level. You have opened up the door by extending the competences of the European Aviation Safety Agency. I understand the Council’s reservations. I believe that you will have the support of Parliament, Commissioner, since this is the direction we must take if we are to take on our responsibilities towards the public and the users of air transport.
  </TEXT>
</DEBATE-SPEECH>

